<!-- $Id: mIntCategory.cls,v 1.4 2007/11/18 02:48:41 wbeeler Exp $ -->
<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-4" "../../support/dtd/v3mDomain.dtd">-->
<spec id="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" sectionCode="HMPOCG" lastEdit="2008-06-05T10:35:18" rendered="2011-06-22T11:42:04"><header><title>Domain: Clinical Genomics</title><version>V 00-00</version><ballot type="NormativeStandard" number="1"/><date>6/22/2011</date><authlist><author><role>Co-Chair, Facilitator &amp; Primary Contributor</role><name key="a1">Amnon Shabo (Shvo), Ph.D.</name><affiliation>IBM Research Lab in Haifa</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="shabo@il.ibm.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">shabo@il.ibm.com</email></author><author><role>Co-Chair</role><name key="a12">Kevin S. Hughes, M.D., FACS</name><affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital, Partners HealthCare</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="KSHUGHES@PARTNERS.ORG" show="embed" actuate="auto">KSHUGHES@PARTNERS.ORG</email></author><author><role>Co-Chair</role><name key="a13">Mollie Ullman-Cullere</name><affiliation>Harvard-Partners Center for Genetics and Genomics</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="MULLMANCULLERE@PARTNERS.ORG" show="embed" actuate="auto">MULLMANCULLERE@PARTNERS.ORG</email></author><author><role>Co-Chair</role><name key="a14">Scott Whyte</name><affiliation>CGEY Health</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="scott.whyte@capgemini.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">scott.whyte@capgemini.com</email></author><author><role>Vocabulary Contributor</role><name key="a5">Usha Reddy, Ph.D.</name><affiliation>IBM Life Sciences</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="ushareddy@us.ibm.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">ushareddy@us.ibm.com</email></author><author><role>Modeling &amp; Vocabulary Contributor</role><name key="a51">Shosh Israel, Ph.D.</name><affiliation>Hadassah University Hospital</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="israels@hadassah.org.il" show="embed" actuate="auto">israels@hadassah.org.il</email></author><author><role>Publishing Facilitator</role><name key="a521">Grant Wood</name><affiliation>Intermountain Healthcare Clinical Genetics Institute</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="grant.wood@intermountainmail.org" show="embed" actuate="auto">grant.wood@intermountainmail.org</email></author><author><role>Contributor and RCRIM liaison</role><name key="a522">Phil Pochon</name><affiliation>Covance</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="Phil.Pochon@covance.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">Phil.Pochon@covance.com</email></author><author><role>Modeling and Vocabulary Contributor</role><name key="a523">Perry Mar</name><affiliation>Partners HealthCare - Clinical Informatics Research and Development</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="PMAR@PARTNERS.ORG" show="embed" actuate="auto">PMAR@PARTNERS.ORG</email></author><author><role>Modeling &amp; Vocabulary Contributor</role><name key="a524">Chuanbo Xu</name><affiliation>Perlegen</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="Chuanbo_Xu@perlegen.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">Chuanbo_Xu@perlegen.com</email></author><author><role>MnM Facilitator (retired)</role><name key="a525">Charlie Mead, MD MSc</name><affiliation>Booz Allen Hamilton</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a53">Pravat Das</name><affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a54">Jennifer Fostel, Ph.D.</name><affiliation>NIH - National Center for Toxicogenomics</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a55">Brent Gendleman</name><affiliation>5AM Solutions</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a6">Rick Haddorff</name><affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a7">Jim Holeman</name><affiliation>HP Nonstop Enterprise Division</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a91">Anajane Smith</name><affiliation>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a92">Derek Walker</name><affiliation>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a93">Sue-Jane Wang, Ph.D.</name><affiliation>US. Food and Drug Administration</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a935">Mathieu Wiepert</name><affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation></author><author><role>Storyboard Contributor</role><name key="a94">Katie Wittrup</name><affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation></author></authlist><legalese copyRightDate="2011" copyRightOwner="Health Level Seven, Inc." copyRightNotation="All rights reserved." renderer="RoseTree 4.2.54" renderNotation="This document was rendered into XML using software provided to HL7 by Beeler Consulting LLC." contactEmail="HQ@HL7.org" contactName="HL7 Headquarters Staff" contactNote="Comments or questions about this document may be may be addressed to:"/></header><front><div1 id="spec-preface"><head>Notes to Readers</head><p>The Clinical Genomics SIG has developed two topics - the Pedigree Topic (Family History), and the Genotype topic. The Pedigree Topic was approved by the membership as normative during the May 2007 ballot cycle and the final version is included in this Normative Edition. The Genotype topic has been approved as a DSTU. The second update to this DSTU passed ballot in January 2007 and is included in his Normative Edition. The Clinical Genomics roadmap is to progress the DSTU to normative in a step-wise approach starting with an implementation guide for genetic variation. The latter can be found in the Clinical Genomics Domain currently under ballot. The reader is encouraged to use the implementation guide because it is a further constraining of the DSTU models and provide more elaborated and accurate description of how the models can be used to represent genetic variation data. </p><p>Since its formation, the Clinical Genomics SIG has been developing
HL7 V3 standards to enable the exchange of interrelated clinical and personalized genomic data between interested parties. In many cases the exchange of genomic data is done between disparate organizations (healthcare providers, genetic labs, research facilities, etc.) and acceptable standards are crucial for the usefulness of genomic data in healthcare practice. It is envisioned that the use of genomic data in healthcare practice will become ubiquitous. Today, there are already several examples of the use of genomic data in healthcare and a few of them are presented in detail in the specifications' storyboards (e.g., Tissue Typing, Cystic Fibrosis, Pharmacogenomics and others use cases are presented briefly in the strategic direction of the SIG). These storyboards, unlike other ballot packages, are considered informative serving the purpose of illustrating the use of the Genotype models as the basic units of genomic data encapsulation. Indeed, the Genotype models (GeneticLocus and GeneticLoci) can be utilized by any group in HL7 that needs to convey genomic data. </p><p>The core Genotype model is the GeneticLocus model. It consists of various types of genomic data relating to a specific DNA locus including sequencing, expression and proteomic data. Within the GeneticLocus model we have utilized existing bioinformatics markups to represent raw data received from genomic facilities. Examining and constraining these markups is a work in progress and thus this part of the GeneticLocus model is
considered informative as well.     </p><p>The FamilyHistory model is aimed at describing a patient's pedigree with genomic data. Note that this model utilizes the GeneticLocus and GeneticLoci models (as CMETs) to carry the genomic data for the patient's relatives. The requirement for an elaborated Clinical Genomic Family History model has been identified while working on the BRCA (Breast Cancer) Storyboard. The Family History storyboard includes parts of the full BRCA storyboard as examples of how one might use the Family History model and interaction set.     </p></div1><div1 id="navigate-divs"><head>Message Design Element Navigation</head><artree role="NAVIGATE"><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="POCG_RM000040UV01-rmi" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Clinical Genomics Family History" refIdentifier="POCG_RM000040UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="POCG_HD000040UV01-hmd" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refIdentifier="POCG_HD000040UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="POCG_MT000040UV01-msg" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refIdentifier="POCG_MT000040UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem></artree></div1></front><body><div1 id="intro-POCG_DO000000UV-ic" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><head>Overview</head><div2 id="spec-scope" lastEdit="2006-03-10T15:55:37"><head>Introduction &amp; Scope</head><p>The Clinical Genomics domain addresses requirements for the interrelation of clinical and genomic data at the individual level. Much of the genomic data is still generic, for example the human genome is in fact the DNA sequences believed to be the common sequences in every human being. The vision of 'personalized medicine' is based on those correlations that make use of personal genomic data such as the SNPs (Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms) that differentiate any two persons and occur about every thousand bases. Beside normal differences, health conditions such as drug sensitivities, allergies and others could be attributed to the individual SNPs or to differences in gene expression and proteomics.</p><p>The emphases the Clinical Genomics domain are the personalization of the genomic data and the 'intelligent' linking to relevant clinical information. These links are probably the main source from which geneticists (genomicists?) and clinicians could benefit. The cases where genomic data are used in healthcare practice vary in complexity and extent of the data used, since the current testing methods are still very expensive and not widely used. We can see simple testing like identifying genes and mutations as well as full sequencing of alleles and the use of micro-arrays to identify the expression of vast number of genes in each individual. Naturally, the Clinical Genomics SIG has been focusing on tests that are routinely done in healthcare, while preparing the information infrastructure standard for more futuristic cases.</p><p>At a first sight it seems that genomic data sets are yet another type of observations. While this is true of course, there are a few characteristics that might distinguish it from typical observations such as blood pressure or potassium level: </p><list role="unordered"><item><p>The amount of data: potentially it could be the entire human genome</p></item><item><p>The personalization of the data is evolving as new discoveries are constantly made</p></item><item><p>The complexity of the data: not only the DNA sequences (...AGCT...) need to be represented, but also SNPs, annotations (automatic and manual), gene expression, protein translation, and more</p></item><item><p>The emerging standard formats being used by bioinformatics communities, for example: BSML (Bioinformatic Sequence Markup Language), MAGE-ML ( Microarray and GeneExpression Markup Language)</p></item><item><p>Various standard organizations and many stakeholders are involved</p></item><item><p>The clinical-genomic correlations are represented in variety of different ways depending on the point of view (clinical research, pharmaceutical or healthcare)</p></item></list><p>The Clinical-Genomics SIG develops HL7 standards to enable the exchange between interested parties of the clinical and personalized genomic data. In many case the exchange of genomic data is done between disparate organization (providers, labs, research facilities, etc.) and acceptable standards are crucial for the usefulness of the data in healthcare practice. </p></div2></div1><dmimdivn identifier="dmims-POCG_DO000000UV" name="Domain Message Information Models" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="dmims-POCG_DO000000UV-ic"><dmim identifier="POCG_DM000023UV" name="Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model" familiarName="Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DM000023UV-rmi" sortPrefix="99|99|99|CLINICAL GENOMICS DOMAIN INFORMATION MODEL" lastEdit="2008-06-05T10:35:18"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_DM000023UV" name="Description" parent="POCG_DM000023UV-rmi" id="desc-POCG_DM000023UV-rmi" lastEdit="2008-06-05T10:35:18"><p>The Clinical Genomics DIM is the result of our effort to look for the commonalities in each genomic-oriented storyboard that we have been working on (i.e., Tissue Typing, Cystic Fibrosis, BRCA and Pharmacogenomics). The first model we developed was called the Genotype model and it described a single locus on chromosomal or mitochondrial DNA. We then developed a model to describe a set of genetic loci and we now have two core models within the Genotype Topic: GeneticLocus and GeneticLoci. In parallel, we developed a Clinical Genomics Family History model. The DIM is an integration of these three models. For deatiled description of each class in the DIM, please refer to the respective walk through of each of the above-mentioned models. The trial use of this draft standard by its early adopters will guide the crystallization of this DIM into a more generic model for this domain.</p><p>In this ballot cycle we present two new models <emph role="strong">for comments only</emph>: (1) a genetic test order model is introduced at the end of the GeneticLoci model description (since it uses the GeneticLoci model as a CMET) and (2) a query model which is presented below. </p><p><emph role="strong">The Clinical Genomics Query Model:</emph></p><p>General:</p><p>HL7 V3 has a framework for domain-specific query models described in the following path of the V3 ballot package: Specifications Infrastructure / Messaging / Query Infrastructure. It states that the Query Infrastructure domain specifies the formation of information queries and the responses to these queries to meet the needs of healthcare applications using the HL7 version 3 messaging standard. In addition, the Query Infrastructure domain asserts that the variety of potential queries is almost unlimited and HL7 does not try to cover every possible query. Rather, the Query Standard provides general methods by which to structure query/response pairs. The technical committees responsible for functional domains apply these methods to develop specific query/response pairs for those domains' needs.</p><p>The Clinical Genomics Query Model:</p><p>The Clinical Genomics SIG develops a Query model based on the Query Infrastructure described above. It model is presented for the first time in the January 2007 ballot cycle - for comments only. The model is based on a query-by-parameter approach where the domain groups pick attributes in their domain and declares them to be parameters of the domain query, while constraining them if necessary. We picked a few central attributed from the GeneticLocus and GeneticLoci models and placed them as parameters in the Clinical Genomics Query model. The development is done step-wise and in the future we'll add parameters from the GeneticTestOrder model as well as the FamilyHistory model. </p><p>Query Interaction:</p><p>The basic interaction where a query message could be used is as follows: an application sends a query message to another application where certain parameters have been populated with data values. The receiving application parses the query message and uses the parameters with their assigned values to query its repository of HL7 Clinical Genomics messages or any other repository where there is a clear mapping between its data model and the HL7 Clinical Genomics models. All messages that meet the criteria set by the parameters and values will be returned to the sending application. Thus, the response is always a set of zero to many valid HL7 instances.</p><p>Note that an HL7 interaction where this message can be used has not been developed yet. So the model presented here for comments only is a static model. Nevertheless, it's encouraged to experiment with this model and simulate a query scenario in clinical genomics and see if at all it can meet the requirements or perhaps this query paradigm is too simplistic for the clinical genomics domain. </p><p>The figure below shows the Query model. </p><p><graphic alt="Draft of the Clinical Genomics Query model" source="T-POCG_RM000090.gif"></graphic></p></descriptive><diagref ref="POCG_DM000023UV.gif"/></dmim></dmimdivn><subdivn identifier="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Pedigree Topic" familiarName="Pedigree" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="02" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><storydivn identifier="sbs-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Storyboards" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="sbs-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><descriptive identifier="sstop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="sstop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><story identifier="POCG_ST000040UV01" name="Pedigree Family History" familiarName="Family History" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="POCG_ST000040UV01-str" sortPrefix="02|FAMILY HISTORY" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:27"><descriptive identifier="purp-POCG_ST000040UV01" name="Purpose" parent="POCG_ST000040UV01-str" id="purp-POCG_ST000040UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:27"><p>The objective of this storyboard is to illustrate the way a patient's pedigree with clinical and genomic data could be represented for risk analysis purposes in the context of breast and ovarian cancers and other diseases. The initial context for this storyboard was set by the BRCA storyboard which is still under development. The UML Activity Diagram below as well as the Presentation section further on are taken from the BRCA storyboard, illustrating the use of family history data in this case.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="POCG_SN000040UV01" name="Genotype Family History" familiarName="Family History" parent="POCG_ST000040UV01-str" id="POCG_ST000040UV01-POCG_SN000040UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="02|FAMILY HISTORY" baseClass="Pedigree" lastEdit="2008-06-04T16:50:43"><p><emph role="strong">Summary</emph></p><p>The Family History storyboard and its HL7 Pedigree Model is part of the HL7 Clinical-Genomics SIG effort to design various higher-level models of using genomic data in healthcare practice, that utilize the basic model of a Genotype (described at this point as the Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model). The need to represent a patient's pedigree information as associated with clinical and genomic data was introduced in the BRCA (Breast Cancer) storyboard which is still under development.</p><p>The BRCA storyboard includes a sample outline for the way the patient's pedigree should look:</p><graphic source="FMsampleData.gif"></graphic><p>Populating the above outline with actual data might result in a spreadsheet found in the following link:</p><graphic source="T-FMsampleDataSheet.gif"></graphic><p><emph role="strong">Presentation</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item>Ms. Eve Everywoman has a family history of breast and ovarian cancer, and she is not of Ashkenazi Jewish descent.</item><item>She believes she is at high risk of developing breast cancer.</item><item>She goes to see her clinician (Medical oncologist, surgical oncologist , radiation oncologist, primary care provider) who takes a thorough family history.  This history is recorded in the chart and the electronic medical record.</item><item>The clinician reviews the family history, decides what genetic syndrome her family might have, and categorizes the patient as to degree of risk (Perhaps high, medium, or low risk).  The clinician thinks the patient is at high risk of having a BRCA1/2 mutation.</item><item>The clinician compares her Family History to tables of risk (Claus, Myriad) and runs computer models (algorithms such as BRCAPRO, see http://www.isds.duke.edu/~gp/brcapro.html).  This gives a percentage risk of carrying a mutation and/or a risk of developing breast and/or ovarian cancer.  Her risk of a mutation is 25%, because her father's 4 sisters had ovarian caner.</item><item>The patient is considered to be at high risk of having a mutation, and this information is given to her.</item><item>She is referred to a Risk Clinic.</item><item>She agrees to go to the Risk Clinic.</item><item>Ms Eve Everywoman's Genetic History details are sent to this clinic (the HL7 Interaction <artref alt="POCG_IN000001" ref="POCG_IN000001UV"></artref> is used), including her Family History, the syndrome suspected and her level of risk.</item><item>The counselor at the risk clinic (Nurse geneticist, genetic counselor, MD, etc.) reviews the family history information collected by the primary clinician, edits it and adds additional details.</item><item>The Counselor reviews the family history, decides what genetic syndrome her family might have, and categorizes the patient as to degree of risk (Perhaps high, medium, or low risk).  The Counselor thinks the patient is at high risk of having a BRCA1/2 mutation.</item><item>The clinician compares the family history to tables of risk (Claus, Myriad) and runs computer models (algorithms such as BRCAPRO).  This gives a percentage risk of carrying a mutation and/or a risk of developing breast and/or ovarian cancer.  Her risk of a mutation is 25%, because her father's 4 sisters had ovarian caner.</item><item>The patient is considered to be at high risk, and she is told she is a candidate for genetic testing.  This includes a thorough discussion of the pros and cons of testing.  This discussion is recorded in the electronic medical record.</item><item>Ms. Eve Everywoman wants to have testing, but as she is not affected, it is the standard of care to test a living affected relative first.</item><item>The Counselor suggests that her Aunt, Ms. Jeanne Aunt, is the most appropriate candidate for testing.  Ms. Jeanne Aunt had ovarian caner, and is still living.</item><item>Ms. Eve Everywoman agrees to contact Ms. Jeanne Aunt.</item><item>Ms Eve Everywoman signs consent to release her own Family History details to Ms Jeanne Aunt and her Provider.</item><item>Ms. Jeanne Aunt is a 39-year-old woman had been diagnosed with ovarian cancer at age 35.</item><item>Ms Jeanne Aunt agrees to discuss testing, and provides the name and address of the Risk Clinic she will attend.</item><item>Ms Eve Everywoman's FH details are sent to this clinic (the HL7 Interaction POCG_IN000001 is used).</item><item>The counselor at the risk clinic (Nurse geneticist, genetic counselor, MD, etc.) reviews the family history information collected by the primary clinician through a pedigree drawing program, and changes the Proband* to Ms Jeanne Aunt, edits it and adds additional details (The family history message had had Ms Eve Everywoman as the Proband (Self), and Ms Jeanne Aunt as the aunt.  The pedigree from the point of view of Ms Jeanne Aunt must have Jeanne Aunt as the Proband (Self) and must show Ms Eve Everywoman as the niece).</item><item>The Counselor reviews the family history, decides what genetic syndrome her family might have, and categorizes the patient as to degree of risk (Perhaps high, medium, or low risk).  The Counselor thinks the patient is at high risk of having a BRCA1/2 mutation.</item><item>The clinician compares the family history to tables of risk (Claus, Myriad) and runs computer models (algorithms such as BRCAPRO).  This gives a percentage risk of carrying a mutation and/or a risk of developing breast and/or ovarian cancer.  Ms. Jeanne Aunt is virtually at 100% risk of having a mutation.</item><item>The patient is considered to be at high risk, and she is told she is a candidate for genetic testing.  This includes a thorough discussion of the pros and cons of testing.  This discussion is reviewed in the electronic medical record.</item><item>Ms. Jeanne Aunt wants to have testing.  She signs an informed consent document.</item><item>The order for testing is issued, and the informed consent, and the family history are included with the lab requisition.  All are MESSEGED to the blood drawing facility. In case the family history is messaged separately, then HL7 Interaction POCG_IN000001 is used.</item><item>The blood is drawn, and sent to the central testing facility along with the informed consent, the family history, the results of Ms Jeanne Aunt's test, and the lab requisition.</item><item>At the central testing facility, the specimen is checked in, and the DNA is separated and PCRed.</item><item>Full gene sequencing of BRCA1 and BRCA 2 are undertaken.</item><item>The sequence is assessed for mutations.</item><item>Identified mutations are assessed for functional significance by determining if they are truncating (deleterious), or if they are irrelevant (No change in amino acid coded by that codon).  All other mutations are compared to known mutations to determine if information is available on their functional significance.</item><item>The actual mutation, and the assessment of functional significance are sent to the counselor.</item><item>In this case, a mutation is identified in BRCA1 and the mutation is Deleterious.</item><item>The counselor discusses the result with the patient.</item><item>Management decisions (Screening, chemoprevention, prophylactic surgery) are probably beyond the scope of this storyboard.</item><item>Ms Jeanne Aunt agrees to share this information with Ms Eve Everywoman's Clinician.</item><item>This information is sent to Ms Eve Everywoman's Clinician.</item><item>Ms. Eve Everywoman wants to have testing.  She signs an informed consent document.</item><item>The order for testing is issued, and the informed consent, and the family history are included with the requisition, as well as the results of Ms Jeanne Aunt's test.  All are MESSEGED to the blood drawing facility.</item><item>The blood is drawn, and sent to the central testing facility along with the informed consent, the family history and the lab requisition.</item><item>At the central testing facility, the specimen is checked in, and the DNA is separated and PCRed.</item><item>Full gene sequencing is not needed.  Testing only for the identified mutation is undertaken.</item><item>The DNA is assessed for that specific mutation.</item><item>The mutation is not found.</item><item>The normal result is sent to the counselor.</item><item>The counselor discusses the result with the patient.</item><item>Management decisions (Screening, chemoprevention, prophylactic surgery) are probably beyond the scope of this storyboard.</item></list><p><emph role="strong">* Glossary:</emph></p><p>Proband: First affected family member coming to medlcal attention.</p><p>Consultand:  Individual (s) seeking genetic counseling/tetsing.</p><p>These definitions are based on: Bennett RL, Steinhaus KA, Uhrich SB, O'Sullivan CK, Resta RG, Lochner-Doyle D, Markel DS, Vincent V, Hamanishi J. Recommendations for standardized human pedigree nomenclature. Pedigree Standardization Task Force of the National Society of Genetic Counselors.  Am J Hum Genet. 1995 Mar;56(3):745-52.
</p><p><emph role="strong">The Family History Shared Model</emph></p><p>Following the above sample of a patient's pedigree as well as the contextual presentation, we have developed an HL7 model to allow the representation of such a pedigree with an unlimited depth of generations. This model is described in detail (including a walk-through) in the section: "Refined Message Information Models".</p></descriptive><diagref ref="POCG_ST000040UV01.gif"/><intref ref="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Original New Notification From Originator" refFamiliarName="Original Pedigree" refIdentifier="POCG_IN000001UV01" sequence="1"/></story></storydivn><approledivn identifier="roles-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Application Roles" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="roles-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><descriptive identifier="arop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="arop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gapprole" alt="the discussion of application roles"/> and their relationships in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><artree><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="POCG_AR000002UV01-ar" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Receiver Pedigree Receiver" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Receiver" refIdentifier="POCG_AR000002UV01"/></artreeitem><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="POCG_AR000001UV01-ar" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Informer Pedigree Sender" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Sender" refIdentifier="POCG_AR000001UV01"/></artreeitem></artree><approle identifier="POCG_AR000002UV01" name="Pedigree Event Receiver Pedigree Receiver" familiarName="Pedigree Receiver" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="POCG_AR000002UV01-ar" sortPrefix="02|20|99|22|PEDIGREE RECEIVER|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="yes" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:35"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_AR000002UV01" name="Description" parent="POCG_AR000002UV01-ar" id="desc-POCG_AR000002UV01-ar" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:35"><p>A role of receiving a person's pedigree from a Pedigree Sender.</p></descriptive><intref role="receives" ref="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Original New Notification From Originator" refFamiliarName="Original Pedigree" refIdentifier="POCG_IN000001UV01"/></approle><approle identifier="POCG_AR000001UV01" name="Pedigree Event Informer Pedigree Sender" familiarName="Pedigree Sender" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="POCG_AR000001UV01-ar" sortPrefix="02|20|99|25|PEDIGREE SENDER|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="yes" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:40"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_AR000001UV01" name="Description" parent="POCG_AR000001UV01-ar" id="desc-POCG_AR000001UV01-ar" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:40"><p>A role of sending a person's pedigree to a Pedigree Receiver.</p></descriptive><intref role="sends" ref="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Original New Notification From Originator" refFamiliarName="Original Pedigree" refIdentifier="POCG_IN000001UV01"/></approle></approledivn><triggerdivn identifier="tes-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Trigger Events" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="tes-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><descriptive identifier="teop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="teop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gtrigger" alt="the discussion of trigger events"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><trigger identifier="POCG_TE000001UV01" name="Pedigree Event Original New Notification" familiarName="Original Pedigree Notification" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="POCG_TE000001UV01-te" role="Interaction based" sortPrefix="02|20ORIGINAL|05||05|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:48"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_TE000001UV01" name="Description" parent="POCG_TE000001UV01-te" id="desc-POCG_TE000001UV01-te" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:55:48"><p>This is a notification of the availability of a person's pedigree to be sent to another pedigree application.</p></descriptive><intref role="fires" ref="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Original New Notification From Originator" refFamiliarName="Original Pedigree" refIdentifier="POCG_IN000001UV01"/></trigger></triggerdivn><rmimdivn identifier="rmims-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="rmims-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><descriptive identifier="rmop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="rmop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><rmim identifier="POCG_RM000040UV01" name="Pedigree Event" familiarName="Clinical Genomics Family History" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="POCG_RM000040UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="02|20|99|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-16T15:35:41"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_RM000040UV01" name="Description" parent="POCG_RM000040UV01-rmi" id="desc-POCG_RM000040UV01-rmi" lastEdit="2007-07-16T15:35:41"><p><emph role="strong">The Clinical Genomics Family History Model</emph></p><p>Following the above sample of a patient's pedigree as well as the contextual presentation, 
	we have developed an HL7 model to allow the representation of such a pedigree
	with an unlimited depth of generations. The model addresses the Family History requirements
	and represents a patient's pedigree while making use of the Genotype model for genomic
	data.     Each family member object is represented in relation to another family member who
	'scopes' its role and is designated by a code taken from the HL7 vocabulary "RoleCode", domain ="PersonalRelationshipRoleType". </p><p>General Notes:  </p><p>The Family History model is used in a message interaction designed to serve the need of information exchange between two disparate pedigree applications (see section on message interactions). This interaction does not serve other needs like sending genetic lab orders accompanied by family history. For the latter, there is a need to use Lab messages that might use this model as a payload.</p><p>The model utilizes the GeneticLocus model (the Genotype Topic) in order to
	capture genomic data in any resolution needed. For that end, the GeneticLocus model was
	packaged as an internal CMET and was also moved to the HL7 Common Domains in the V3 Ballot
	Package. It is utilized in this model as one of the choices in the main Clinical Genomics
	choice box (see the model walk through below). 
	The model suggests the use of the Clinical Statement shared model (under
	development in HL7) to represent the clinical data. Meanwhile, it has a generic
	ClinicalObservation class to hold common clinical data (e.g., problems, diagnoses,
	reactions to drugs, allergies, etc.).      </p><p><emph role="strong">Model Walk-Through</emph></p><p><emph role="strong">Starting Point - FamilyHistory:</emph></p><p>The starting point of the model is the FamilyHistory Observation class. This
	class has several associations, one of which is subject participation of the Patient role
	played by a Person entity. The latter scopes the Relative class which can hold information
	about the patient's relatives. This constitutes the backbone of the model. In addition, the
	entry point is associated with risk analysis results and with problems that can not be
	attributed to specific family members.</p><p><emph role="strong">Attributes of FamilyHistory:</emph></p><list role="unordered"><item>id: holds a unique identifier of this family history instance</item><item>code: the code attribute shall hold a code representing Family History data in general, for example: the LOINC code 10157-6, HISTORY OF FAMILY MEMBER DISEASES or any other code that carries similar semantics.</item><item>statusCode: indicates whether the act of family history observation as a whole has completed, still active, etc. (based on the HL7 RIM Act State Machine)</item><item>methodCode: The methodCode holds the identification of the program creating the family history data</item></list><p><emph role="strong">Patient &amp; Person:</emph></p><p>The Patient role class is the root of the pedigree but in terms of data, it only captures an id assigned by the family history application on behalf of the provider hosting the family history application. Note that the id is optional and so is the class Provider (the scoping entity of the Patient role). Person is the player entity of Patient and holds general information about the person like gender, birth time, deceased indication, etc.</p><p>Note that the gender attribute of the Person class is an "administrative gender" and the way to represent genotypic / phenotypic gender is to populate an instance of the clinical observation class in the clinical genomic choice box.</p><p><emph role="strong">Clinical and Genomic Data:</emph></p><p>At the right side of the Patient role there is a 'subjectOf2' participation that
	associates the patient (as a 'subject of') to a choice box of zero to many clinical
	statements as well as genomic data represented by the GeneticLocus model. Note that this
	association is shadowed at the bottom of the model, associated with the Relative class,
	which represents a role of a patient's relative.</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">ClinicalObservation</emph></p><p>The ClinicalObservation class represents any clinical data that
			is part of the Person clinical history. Currently, the class has the classCode of 'OBS'
			which means that it is capable of representing only observations. However, the full
			expression of a clinical statement will be available when this single class will be
			replaced by the HL7 Clinical Statement model (under development). The Clinical Statement
			model will provide the 'grammar' of how various discrete acts (observations, procedures,
			substance administrations, etc.) are associated to a meaningful clinical statement.
			Nevertheless, in the January 2007 ballot we added a recursive ActRelationship (sourceOf) to the clinical observation to address use cases where a richer clinical statement is need, as introduced to us by early adopters of the model. The addition of this association is in consistent with the Clinical Statement model, so that when eventually this single observation is replaced with the Clinical Statement model or a derivative of it, this current addition is in consistent with it and will not require substantive changes to the family history implementations.</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">DataEstimatedAge</emph></p><p>The DataEstimatedAge class is used to hold the
					estimated age of the subject at the effective time of the observation (e.g, the diagnosis
					time). The diagnosis is represented by the source observation , i.e., the
					ClinicalObservation class. It is used due to the absence of an age attribute in all HL7
					classes. We have proposed to RIM harmonization  the addition of an age attribute to the Act
					class as well as other classes, but were asked to try and model this piece of information
					using associated observations like this class.   The data type is an interval to allow a
					range of ages such as in cases when the patient only remembers that the diagnosis was made
					when the family member was in her forties for example.  </p><p>The code attribute shall hold a code representing age of subject at the effective time when the source observation was made for that subject. Its purpose is to allow parser applications to understand this class without referring to its name.</p></item></list></item><item><p><emph role="strong">A_GeneticLocus (CMET)</emph></p><p><p>This CMET is the main model we are developing at the HL7
				Clinical Genomics SIG. In principle, the GeneticLocus model can hold relevant genomic data
				in any resolution required. In the BRCA storyboard, it could be information on mutations
				that the patient's relatives have or full DNA sequences of the patient's genes at
				stake.</p></p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">A_GeneticLoci (CMET)</emph></p><p>This CMET allows the association of data on a set of loci such as genetic test panel results or gene expression assay.
			</p></item></list><p><emph role="strong">informant:</emph></p><p>This class optionally represents the source of information from which this family history was collected.
</p><p><emph role="strong">PedigreeAnalysisResults:</emph></p><p>This class represents the results of analysis done to the data captured in the
	family history pedigree.   Use the code attribute to identify the disease or variation for
	which the probabilities/risks/etc. are calculated.   Use the methodCode to hold the
	algorithm used to analyze the pedigree.    </p><p><emph role="strong">Attributes of PedigreeAnalysisResults:</emph></p><p>* code: identifies the disease or variation for which the probabilities/risks/etc. are calculated. Note that this class can be populated as many times as needed, for each clinical condition which is the is the focus of the risk calculations</p><p>* negationInd: can be used to represent the fact that there is no risk found for this family history and the clinical condition in the code attribute</p><p>* methodCode: holds the type of the algorithm used to analyze the pedigree (e.g., BRCAPRO)</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">risk</emph></p><p>The risk association links the FamilyHistory class to the PedigreeAnalysisResults class and represents the risk associated with that family history. The risk Act Relationship is defined in the RIM as follows: "A noteworthy undesired outcome of a patient's condition that is either likely enough to become an issue or is less likely but dangerous enough to be addressed." The patient condition in this model is the patient's family history and the risk is represented through the classes associated with PedigreeAnalysisResults class.</p><p>Consequently, the PedigreeAnalysisResults class and the observation classes associated with it are in 'risk' mood (moodCode= RSK) to express the fact that these are not observations that happened, rather they represent a risk associated wit the family history.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">InputParameters</emph></p><p>The controlVariable association links PedigreeAnalysisResults to
			input parameters used in the analysis like sensitivity and specificity in the BRCAPRO
			algorithm. For example, if the code attributes holds "sensitivity" then the value attribute holds the sensitivity itself. </p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Choice</emph></p><p>The component association links PedigreeAnalysisResults to a choice box that contains several options to represent the actual results:</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">AnalysisResult</emph></p><p>This class is a catcher for any analysis that cannot be represented through the other classes in this choice box.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Probability</emph></p><p>The value holds a probability of having what is represented in the PedigreeAnalysisResults.code attribute (e.g., disease, variation). 
					The code attribute holds a value that indicates that this is a probability observation.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">PercentageRisk</emph></p><p>The value holds a percentage risk of having what is represented in the PedigreeAnalysisResults.code attribute (e.g., disease, variation).
					The code attribute holds a value that indicates that this is a percentage risk observation.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Relative Risk</emph></p><p>The value holds a relative risk of having what is represented in the PedigreeAnalysisResults.code attribute (e.g., disease, variation).
					The code attribute holds a value that indicates that this is a relative risk observation.</p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">Age &amp; Probability</emph></p><p>The pertinentInformation association links Age to Probability and multiple traversals of the Age class along with Probability can hold
					pairs of age-probability data for what is represented in the PedigreeAnalysisResults.code attribute (e.g., disease, variation). </p><p>The code attribute shall hold a code representing the concept of   "Age" in general (e.g., the value 397659008 "Age" in SNOMED CT).</p></item></list></item></list><p><emph role="strong">Relative:</emph></p><p>This refinement of the HL7 Role Class represents a patient's relative and is
	scoped by the Person entity which plays the Patient role in the first traversal of the model
	(see further explanation in the "Person and Relative" bullet below). The cardinality of
	this association is 0..* which allows for the representation of any number of relatives who
	all relate to the Person who scopes the role.     
	The Relative class has a classCode = "PRS", defined as "links two people in a
	personal relationship... the character of the relationship must be defined by a
	PersonalRelationshipRoleType code..." The latter code is defined by the Relative.code
	attribute whose value set is drawn from the domain "PersonalRelationshipRoleType".
	Appendix E includes a table that shows the codes of this domain. Using values from this
	domain it is possible to designate the relation to the patient or to the patient's family
	member. Thus, in this model it is possible to use, for example, the code GRMTH
	(grandmother) for Relative associated directly to the patient, or use the code NMTH
	(mother) for Relative associated to the mother of the patient. This makes the model more
	flexible.  </p><p>The basis of this part of the model is in the RIM definition of family member relationships which are based on the relationship between a scoping entity and a role. For example, the code CHILD is defines as "The player of the role is a child of the scoping entity", and the same goes for any type of family relationship. Note that this is valid not only to the relationship between the patient and a relative directly associated with the patient, rather this is true for any relationship between family members on this pedigree, for example, between the patient's mother  (the scoper) and her father (the role).</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">SubjectEstimatedAge</emph></p><p>This choice box is associated with the Relative class and holds</p><p>two classes concerned with estimated ages of the subject as follows:</p><list role="unordered"><item><p><emph role="strong">DeceasedEstimatedAge</emph></p><p>The DeceasedEstimatedAge class is used to hold
					the estimated age when the subject died. It is used due to a lack of age attribute in all
					HL7 classes. We have proposed to RIM harmonization the addition of age attribute to hold
					the deceased age as well as the subject age at the time a diagnosis was made (see above in
					the DataEstimatedAge class description), but were asked to try and model this piece of
					information using associated observations like this class. </p></item><item><p><emph role="strong">LivingEstimatedAge</emph></p><p>The LivingEstimatedAge class is used to hold the
					estimated age of a living relative whose birth date is unknown. </p></item><item>For a living subject, the code shall represent semantics similar to the LOINC code "21611-9" that represents the concept of an estimated age (as opposed to precise age). For a deceased subject, the code shall represent semantics similar to the LOINC code 39016-1 (AGE AT DEATH). </item></list></item></list><p><emph role="strong">subjectOf Shadow</emph></p><p>This class is a shadow of the subjectOf2 class associated with Patient and thus
	also includes all its associated classes. This means that the same clinical and genomic
	data structures attached to the patient could be optionally attached to any of his/her
	relatives represented by the Relative class. It could be that the clinical data of any of
	the persons involved in this pedigree model exist elsewhere (in the same message or
	document, or in the person medical records). In this case it is possible to point to that
	data by including stub classes which only hold ids of the actual data, thus enabling
	applications to get the information if needed.</p><p><emph role="strong">Person and Relative</emph></p><p>The Person class allows the representation of personal information like gender
	and birth time of each of the patient's relatives. It is also linked back to the Relative
	class, an association which enables a recursive traversal a pedigree at any level of depth
	in a pure XML hierarchical fashion (i.e., only by nesting elements). Note that in each new
	traversal of this recursive association, the scoping Person represents another family
	member, and consequently the Relative class relates to this family member and not directly
	to the patient. </p><p>In general, the issue of recursion and XML hierarchy relate to the
	representation of pedigree data which is hierarchical by nature but could be represented in
	various ways using XML nesting elements on the one hand or mother and father ids for each
	relative thus constituting the hierarchy via links and pointers and not via nesting
	elements. The latter format also allows the flat outline of the pedigree. These issues are
	discussed in more detail in the documentation available from the HL7 Clinical Genomics SIG
	page in the HL7 site. </p><p><emph role="strong">Relative - Mother and Father Identifiers</emph></p><p>In a flat XML representation of a pedigree it is often required to maintain
	mother and father ids for each relative, in order to allow the family history application
	to reconstruct the pedigree. These ids should be placed in the id attribute of the Person
	class. That class should be populated for each parent if available. The first XML sample in
	appendix D shows a flat representation of a pedigree with the ids populated in the Person
	class (XML element is relationshipHolder.id).</p><p>It is required to use globally unique ids as mandated from the use of the II data type for
	the id attribute. Regarding the generation of thses ids, there can be two situations: (1)
	The application generating the pedigree has a 'root' OID dedicated to this purpose and it
	extends it for each pedigree it creates. Then, it generates arbitrary unique ids for each
	relative who doesn't have a globally unique id and places it in the extension component.
	The concatenation of the pedigree root and relative extension creates a globally unique id
	for the person; (2) The application knows a globally unique id of a relative and uses it.
	Note that in a certain pedigree there can be a mixture of the two situations. </p></descriptive><rmimref role="parent" ref="POCG_DM000023UV-rmi" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model" refFamiliarName="Clinical Genomics Domain Information Model" refIdentifier="POCG_DM000023UV"/><diagref ref="POCG_RM000040UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="POCG_HD000040UV01-hmd" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Event" refIdentifier="POCG_HD000040UV01"/></rmim></rmimdivn><hmddivn identifier="hmds-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="hmds-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><descriptive identifier="hdop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="hdop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><hmd identifier="POCG_HD000040UV01" name="Pedigree Event" familiarName="Pedigree Event" parent="POCG_RM000040UV01-rmi" id="POCG_HD000040UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="02|20|99|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-03-20T15:51:51"><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="POCG_HD000040UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="POCG_RM000040UV01-rmi" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refFamiliarName="Clinical Genomics Family History" refIdentifier="POCG_RM000040UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="POCG_MT000040UV01-msg" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Event" refIdentifier="POCG_MT000040UV01"/></hmd></hmddivn><msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="msgs-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><msgtype identifier="POCG_MT000040UV01" name="Pedigree Event" familiarName="Pedigree Event" parent="POCG_HD000040UV01-hmd" id="POCG_MT000040UV01-msg" sortPrefix="02|20|99|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-02-26T23:59:02"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="POCG_MT000040UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="POCG_HD000040UV01-hmd" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Event" refIdentifier="POCG_HD000040UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Original New Notification From Originator" refFamiliarName="Original Pedigree" refIdentifier="POCG_IN000001UV01"/></msgtype></msgtypedivn><interactiondivn identifier="ints-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Interactions" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="ints-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><descriptive identifier="inop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree" name="Reference" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="inop-POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gintact" alt="the definition of Interactions"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><interaction identifier="POCG_IN000001UV01" name="Pedigree Event Original New Notification From Originator" familiarName="Original Pedigree" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-Pedigree-ic" id="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="02|20ORIGINAL|05|05|FROM ORIGINATOR|" baseClass="Pedigree" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-03-10T16:45:36"><descriptive identifier="desc-POCG_IN000001UV01" name="Description" parent="POCG_IN000001UV01-int" id="desc-POCG_IN000001UV01-int" lastEdit="2006-03-10T16:45:36">A number of pedigree applications are in use by healthcare professionals (e.g., CAGENE) as well as by patients (e.g., the US Surgeon General Family History Program), which each have their own internal proprietary format of representing data for pedigree drawing and maintenance of family history information. We envision that any pedigree application will be able to send and receive an individual's family history information using this HL7 specification, either electronically or through import/export routines that will be developed for each Pedigree application. Note that this is a general purpose information exchange, i.e., it's not designed to serve use cases such as lab orders or specific patient care scenarios.  For example, the interaction can serve the following short storyboard (derived from the "Family History" storyboard presented in the Clinical Genomics domain):

Ms. Martha Francis is 48 years old.  Her mother had ovarian cancer and was found to have a deleterious BRCA1 mutation.  She has two sisters, a husband and a daughter.  She is not of Ashkenazi Jewish descent

She makes an appointment at a Risk Clinic.  The Clinic instructs the patient to use the Surgeon General's Family History Tool to prepare for the visit.  She downloads the Surgeon General's Family History Tool onto her computer at home, and enters her family history.

She then exports the data as an HL7 MESSAGE, places it on Portable Media (CD, Flash drive) and brings it to her Risk Clinic appointment.

The counselor at the risk clinic (Nurse geneticist, Nurse Practitioner, Genetic Counselor, MD, etc.) imports the HL7 MESSAGE into CAGENE, a pedigree drawing program that runs risk models.  The counselor edits the data after confirming and clarifying various issues with the patient, and adds additional information that had not been entered at home.

The patient is considered to be at high risk, and she is told she is a candidate for genetic testing.  This includes a thorough discussion of the pros and cons of testing.  The patient decides not to have testing, and leaves.</descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="POCG_AR000001UV01-ar" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Informer Pedigree Sender" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Sender" refIdentifier="POCG_AR000001UV01"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="POCG_AR000002UV01-ar" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Receiver Pedigree Receiver" refFamiliarName="Pedigree Receiver" refIdentifier="POCG_AR000002UV01"/><teref role="trigger" ref="POCG_TE000001UV01-te" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event Original New Notification" refFamiliarName="Original Pedigree Notification" refIdentifier="POCG_TE000001UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="POCG_MT000040UV01-msg" sectID="hmpocg" sectType="SB" refName="Pedigree Event" refIdentifier="POCG_MT000040UV01"/></interaction></interactiondivn></subdivn><indexdivn identifier="cindx-POCG_DO000000UV" name="Common Message Elements Indexes" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="cindx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-1" name="Common Message Elements Defined in this Domain" parent="cindx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-icc1id"/><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-2" name="Common Message Elements Used by this Domain" parent="cindx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-icc2id"/></indexdivn><indexdivn identifier="indx-POCG_DO000000UV" name="Interaction Indexes" parent="POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="indx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="indx-List-1" name="Interaction Index by Application Role" parent="indx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-ic1id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-2" name="Interaction Index by Trigger Event" parent="indx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-ic2id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-3" name="Interaction Index by Message Type" parent="indx-POCG_DO000000UV-ic" id="POCG_DO000000UV-ic3id"/></indexdivn></body></spec>

