<!-- $Id: mIntCategory.cls,v 1.4 2007/11/18 02:48:41 wbeeler Exp $ -->
<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-4" "../../support/dtd/v3mDomain.dtd">-->
<spec id="REDS_DO010001UV-ic" sectionCode="HMREDS" lastEdit="2011-08-01T16:29:51" rendered="2011-08-01T16:31:54"><header><title>Domain: Clinical Decision Support</title><version>V 00-00</version><ballot type="MixedContent" number="1"/><date>8/1/2011</date><authlist><author><role>Lead Editor &amp; Co-Chair</role><name key="1">Guilherme Del Fiol, MD, PhD</name><affiliation>Duke University</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="guilherme.delfiol@duke.edu" show="embed" actuate="auto">guilherme.delfiol@duke.edu</email></author><author><role>Co-chair</role><name key="1">Robert Greenes, MD, PhD</name><affiliation>Partners Healthcare/Brigham &amp; Women's Hospital</affiliation></author><author><role>Co-chair</role><name key="2">Robert A. Jenders, MD, MS</name><affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center/University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation></author><author><role>Co-chair</role><name key="2">Robert Jenders, MD, MS</name><affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center/UCLA</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="jenders@ucla.edu" show="embed" actuate="auto">jenders@ucla.edu</email></author><author><role>Co-chair</role><name key="3">Kensaku Kawamoto, MD, PhD</name><affiliation>Duke University</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="kawam001@mc.duke.edu" show="embed" actuate="auto">kawam001@mc.duke.edu</email></author><author><role>Co-chair and M&amp;M Facilitator</role><name key="4">Craig Parker, MD</name><affiliation>Arizona State University</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="craigparkermd@gmail.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">craigparkermd@gmail.com</email></author><author><role>Co-chair</role><name key="4">R. Matthew Sailors, PhD</name><affiliation>University of Texas, Houston</affiliation></author><author><role>Co-chair</role><name key="5">Robert Greenes, MD</name><affiliation>Arizona State University</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="greenes@asu.edu" show="embed" actuate="auto">greenes@asu.edu</email></author><author><role>Editor</role><name key="5">Guilherme Del Fiol, MD, MS</name><affiliation>Intermountain Healthcare, Salt Lake City</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="6">Howard Strasberg, MD, MS</name><affiliation>Wolters Kluwer Health</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="Howard.Strasberg@wolterskluwer.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">Howard.Strasberg@wolterskluwer.com</email></author><author><role>Editor/M&amp;M Facilitator/Co-chair</role><name key="6">Craig Parker, MD, MS</name><affiliation>Intermountain Healthcare, Salt Lake City</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="7">James J Cimino, MD</name><affiliation>Clinical Center, National Institutes of Health</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="ciminoj@cc.nih.gov" show="embed" actuate="auto">ciminoj@cc.nih.gov</email></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="71">James Cimino, MD</name><affiliation>Columbia University, New York</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="72">Robert Dolin, MD</name><affiliation>Kaiser Permanente</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="73">Thom Kuhn</name><affiliation>American College of Physicians</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="74">Saverio Maviglia, MD, PhD</name><affiliation>Partners Healthcare, Boston</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="75">Roberto Rocha, MD, PhD</name><affiliation>University of Utah, Salt Lake City</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="76">Howard Strasberg, MD</name><affiliation>WoltersKluwer Health</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="8">Bob Dolin, MD</name><affiliation>Semantically Yours</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="bobdolin@gmail.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">bobdolin@gmail.com</email></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="8">Saverio M Maviglia, MD, MSc</name><affiliation>Partners Healthcare</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="smaviglia@partners.org" show="embed" actuate="auto">smaviglia@partners.org</email></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="9">Thom Kuhn</name><affiliation>American College of Physicians</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="tkuhn@acponline.org" show="embed" actuate="auto">tkuhn@acponline.org</email></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="9">Roberto Rocha, MD, PhD</name><affiliation>Partners Healthcare</affiliation></author><author><role>Contributor</role><name key="9">Clayton Curtis, MD</name><affiliation>Veterans Health Administration</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href=" Clayton.Curtis@va.gov" show="embed" actuate="auto"> Clayton.Curtis@va.gov</email></author></authlist><legalese copyRightDate="2011" copyRightOwner="Health Level Seven, Inc." copyRightNotation="All rights reserved." renderer="RoseTree 5.0.10" renderNotation="This document was rendered into XML using software provided to HL7 by Beeler Consulting LLC." contactEmail="HQ@HL7.org" contactName="HL7 Headquarters Staff" contactNote="Comments or questions about this document may be may be addressed to:"/></header><front><div1 id="prefNotes"><head>Notes to Readers</head><p>The goal of the Infobutton standard is to facilitate the integration of knowledge resources into clinical information systems in order to reduce barriers to the access of knowledge resources at the point of decision making, helping clinicians and patients meet their information needs. The specification consists of a standard mechanism for clinical information systems to request context-specific knowledge from knowledge resources (<emph>knowledge request</emph>). This specification was approved as an HL7 Normative standard following its successful ballot during the HL7 May 2010 ballot cycle.  A preliminary version of this specification was approved as a DSTU in January 2008. The specification was widely validated and adopted by key stakeholders in the US and abroad during this trial period. The draft standard was selected by HITSP as the preferred standard for the retrieval of medical knowledge (HITSP/T81).   </p><p>Although both the knowledge request and knowledge response interactions are described in this specification, <emph role="strong">the specification only includes the knowledge request information model.</emph></p></div1><div1 id="navigate-divs"><head>Message Design Element Navigation</head><artree role="NAVIGATE"><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Knowledge Request Message Model" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_RM010001UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="REDS_HD010001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Knowledge Request" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_HD010001UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="REDS_MT010001UV01-msg" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_MT010001UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem></artree></div1></front><body><div1 id="intro-REDS_DO010001UV-ic" ballotStatus="MixedContent" ballotNumber="1"><head>Overview</head><div2 id="spec-scope" lastEdit="2011-04-29T10:34:14"><head>Introduction &amp; Scope</head><div3 id="prefNotes"><head>Notes to Readers</head><p>The <emph>Context-aware Knowledge Retrieval</emph> specification also includes and accompanying informative document entitled <emph>Context-aware Knowledge retrieval (Infobutton), knowledge request. URL-Based Implementation Guide</emph>. This implementation guide provides a specification for URL-based implementations of the Context-aware knowledge retrieval (Infobutton) standard. The intent of this specification is to support the majority of implementations that offer URLs as the primary or exclusive communication protocol. The ultimate goal is to enable a future, stepwise transition from a URL-based to a Services-Oriented approach.</p></div3><div3 id="prefChange"><head>Changes from Previous Release</head><list role="unordered"><item>Based on affirmative comments received during the May 2010 ballot cycle, the term "electronic health record" was replaced with the broader term "clinical information system" throughout the specification.  </item></list></div3></div2></div1><dmimdivn identifier="dmims-REDS_DO010001UV" name="Domain Message Information Models" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="dmims-REDS_DO010001UV-ic"><dmim identifier="REDS_DM000001UV" name="Structured Documents master DMIM" familiarName="Structured Document" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DM000001UV-rmi" sortPrefix="99|99|99|STRUCTURED DOCUMENTS MASTER DMIM" lastEdit="2009-11-21T14:02:19"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_DM000001UV" name="Description" parent="REDS_DM000001UV-rmi" id="desc-REDS_DM000001UV-rmi" lastEdit="2009-11-21T14:02:19"><p>REDS_DM000001UV is a copy reference to the Structured Documents Domain Message Information Model - POCD_RM000001.UV - reproduced here for ease of review</p><p>Clinical decision Support collaborated with Structured Documents, Medical Records, Structured Product Labeling and Patient Care to develop the domain model for a structured document in order to harmonize model development between the technical committees.  This DMIM reflects the product of that collaboration and is the more general supertype model of the the Order Sets Document RMIM REDS_RM020001UV included in this ballot.</p></descriptive><diagref ref="REDS_DM000001UV.gif"/></dmim></dmimdivn><subdivn identifier="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Context-aware Knowledge Retrieval (Infobutton) Topic" familiarName="Context-aware Knowledge Retrieval (Infobutton)" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="10" baseClass="Context-aware Knowledge Retrieval (Infobutton)" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><div2 id="intro-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><head>Introduction</head><div3 id=""><head>Topic Overview</head><p>Clinicians face numerous knowledge needs during the course of patient care. To a large extent, these knowledge needs are related to gaps in medical knowledge that clinicians need to fill in order to make, confirm, or carry out a patient care decision. Ultimately, knowledge gaps lead to suboptimal decisions, compromising the quality of care. </p><p>With the advent of the World Wide Web, numerous online health knowledge resources have become available. Although these resources have demonstrated great potential to resolve clinicians' and their patients' knowledge needs, a number of barriers hinder a more efficient and effective use of these resources, slowing their dissemination. In essence, both patients and providers become overwhelmed with the vast amount of information available, raising the need for tools that help them identify relevant, context-specific, high quality knowledge in a timely manner.</p><p>To lower barriers to the access of knowledge resources at the point of need, researchers have proposed context-aware integration of knowledge resources into clinical information systems (CIS), such as electronic health record (EHR) and personal health record (PHR) systems. Tools that provide this type of integration have been generically denominated <emph>infobuttons</emph>. The goal of the present specification is to facilitate the context-aware integration of knowledge resources into CISs.</p></div3><div3 id=""><head>Technical Background</head><p>In a typical infobutton implementation, a CIS places hyperlinks adjacent to clinical concepts, such as medications, laboratory tests, and problems. These hyperlinks embed a knowledge request with a set of attributes that capture the context of the interaction between the user and the CIS. Context can be expressed in terms of attributes that characterize (1) the clinical concept of interest (e.g., a medication, a laboratory test result, a problem list entry); (2) the patient (e.g., demographics); (3) the CIS task (e.g., order entry, laboratory results review, problem list review); (4) the knowledge user (e.g., discipline, specialty, language, patient vs. provider); and (5) the care setting (e.g., outpatient, inpatient). When a user clicks on an infobutton, the following steps are followed: 1) a request for knowledge is sent to a decision support system known as infobutton manager; 2) Using these context attributes, the infobutton manager produces a refined knowledge request, for example, asking for specific content topics that are thought to be most relevant in the particular context (e.g., diagnosis, treatment). The refined knowledge request is submitted to one or more relevant knowledge resources; 3) the knowledge resources responds with knowledge content that fulfills the knowledge request; 4) the infobutton manager processes the content from the multiple resources and sends it to the CIS. </p><p>Figure 1 depicts a typical implementation approach to knowledge integration using the Context-Aware Knowledge Integration standard specification. As indicated in the diagram, the present Knowledge Request specification enables a CIS (e.g., EHR, PHR) to request context-specific knowledge from knowledge resources. A specification for the response of knowledge resources will be addressed in a separate future specification.</p><graphic source="REDS_EX010001.gif" alt="Figure 1 - Typical implementation approach to knowledge integration using the HL7 Context-Aware Knowledge Integration standard specification. The numbers adjacent to the arrows refer to the narrative steps in the paragraph above. The call out boxes indicate the events represented by each of the steps.."></graphic><p>Infobutton managers are one of many possible implementation mechanisms for context-aware knowledge integration. In other alternative implementations, infobuttons submit requests for knowledge directly to a knowledge resource without the mediation of an infobutton manager. In addition, knowledge can be integrated into a CIS through mechanisms other than infobutton hyperlinks. This standard specification is agnostic of any particular implementation and is designed to support a variety of context-aware knowledge integration approaches.
		</p><p>The following notes should be considered when reading this specification:</p><list role="unordered"><item>Although both the knowledge request and knowledge response interactions are described in this specification, the specification only includes the knowledge request information model. An information model for the knowledge response will be part of a separate specification.</item><item>The specification does not determine how the components involved in a knowledge integration scenario should be implemented.</item><item>The specification does not specify a standard indexing and content structure for knowledge resources. However, knowledge resource developers can use this standard as a guideline to define their indexing and content structure, enabling their product to more effectively respond to a CIS that submits knowledge requests based on this specification.</item></list></div3><div3 id=""><head>Encoding Rules and Processing</head><p>To be compliant with this standard, implementers are not required to handle all the data elements defined in the knowledge request RMIM. In order to promote rapid adoption, the following directives should be followed:</p><list role="unordered"><item>A CIS SHOULD formulate knowledge requests as complete as possible, using as many context data elements as possible, preferably using coded data.</item><item>Except for required classes and attributes, knowledge resources MAY process only the elements that they can handle, ignoring other elements. For example, if a knowledge resource does not use patient.administrativeGender as a content index, the resource MAY ignore this attribute whenever it is included in a knowledge request.</item></list><p>These directives allow a CIS to create knowledge requests that can be fulfilled by knowledge resources with varying levels of sophistication. The approach also enables less sophisticated knowledge resources to quickly achieve compliance without major modifications to their content and indexing structure. Still, resources MAY be gradually enhanced aiming at fully exercising the message model described in this specification.</p></div3></div2><storydivn identifier="sbs-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Storyboards" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="sbs-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><descriptive identifier="sstop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Reference" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="sstop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><story identifier="REDS_ST010001UV01" name="Infobutton" familiarName="Context-aware knowledge retrieval" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_ST010001UV01-str" sortPrefix="10|" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2009-11-24T14:01:29" class="changed"><descriptive identifier="purp-REDS_ST010001UV01" name="Purpose" parent="REDS_ST010001UV01-str" id="purp-REDS_ST010001UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2009-11-24T14:01:29"><p>The following storyboard depicts a typical context-aware knowledge retrieval transaction. Although the present specification focuses primarily on the <em>Knowledge Request</em> step, the storyboard also includes the <em>knowledge response</em> step in which a knowledge resource fulfills a knowledge request. As previously mentioned, the latter step will be covered in a separate future specification.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="REDS_SN010001UV01" name="Infobutton Act Infobutton Storyboard Narrative" familiarName="Infobutton Storyboard Narrative" parent="REDS_ST010001UV01-str" id="REDS_ST010001UV01-REDS_SN010001UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|" baseClass="Infobutton" lastEdit="2009-11-24T14:01:52" class="changed"><p>Table 1 - Storyboard: Knowledge request originated from a problem list.</p><table><tbody><tr><td>Step</td><td>Specification</td><td>Actor</td><td>Description</td></tr><tr><td>1</td><td>Knowledge request</td><td>EHR</td><td>A clinician is reviewing a problem list module of an EHR and is unfamiliar with a rare disease (Camurati-Engelmann Disease) that the patient, a 15-year-old female, has. The problem list module provides an infobutton link next to the "Camurati-Engelmann Disease" problem. The user clicks on the infobutton link. </td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>Knowledge request</td><td>EHR</td><td>Context data available to the EHR captured and submitted in a knowledge request to the knowledge resource. </td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Knowledge response</td><td>Knowledge resource</td><td>The knowledge resource receives the request and looks for content in its content collection that is deemed to be relevant based on the elements included in the knowledge request.</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Knowledge response</td><td>Knowledge resource</td><td>The knowledge resource submits a knowledge response with content that may be relevant in this particular context. </td></tr></tbody></table></descriptive><diagref ref="REDS_ST010001UV01.gif"/><intref ref="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition New Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Knowledge Request" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010001UV01" sequence="1"/></story></storydivn><approledivn identifier="roles-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Application Roles" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="roles-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><descriptive identifier="arop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Reference" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="arop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gapprole" alt="the discussion of application roles"/> and their relationships in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><approle identifier="REDS_AR010002UV01" name="Infobutton Definition Completion Fulfiller Knowledge Resource" familiarName="Knowledge Resource" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" sortPrefix="10|02|10|10|KNOWLEDGE RESOURCE|" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2010-06-15T11:47:55" class="changed"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_AR010002UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" id="desc-REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" lastEdit="2010-06-15T11:47:55"><p>An application role that fulfills knowledge requests for context-aware knowledge from the clinical information system.</p></descriptive><arref role="parentrole" ref="REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Completion Fulfiller Knowledge Resource" refFamiliarName="Knowledge Resource" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010002UV01"/><arref role="child" ref="REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Completion Fulfiller Knowledge Resource" refFamiliarName="Knowledge Resource" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010002UV01"/><intref role="sends" ref="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Complete Fulfillment Request" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Knowledge Response" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010002UV01"/><intref role="receives" ref="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition New Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Knowledge Request" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010001UV01"/></approle><approle identifier="REDS_AR010001UV01" name="Infobutton Definition Creator Placer Clinical Information System" familiarName="Clinical Information System" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_AR010001UV01-ar" sortPrefix="10|02|15|05|CLINICAL INFORMATION SYSTEM|" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2010-06-15T11:47:43" class="changed"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_AR010001UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_AR010001UV01-ar" id="desc-REDS_AR010001UV01-ar" lastEdit="2010-06-15T11:47:43"><p>A clinical information system or clinical information system module that prepares context-aware requests for knowledge requests and submits these requests to knowledge resources.</p></descriptive><arref role="parentrole" ref="REDS_AR010001UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Creator Placer Clinical Information System" refFamiliarName="Clinical Information System" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010001UV01"/><arref role="child" ref="REDS_AR010001UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Creator Placer Clinical Information System" refFamiliarName="Clinical Information System" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010001UV01"/><intref role="sends" ref="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition New Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Knowledge Request" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010001UV01"/><intref role="receives" ref="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Complete Fulfillment Request" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Knowledge Response" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010002UV01"/></approle></approledivn><triggerdivn identifier="tes-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Trigger Events" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="tes-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><descriptive identifier="teop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Reference" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="teop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gtrigger" alt="the discussion of trigger events"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><trigger identifier="REDS_TE010001UV01" name="Infobutton Definition New Notification" familiarName="Knowledge Request" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_TE010001UV01-te" role="User request" sortPrefix="10|02|05||05|" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" class="changed" lastEdit="2010-06-15T11:48:38"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_TE010001UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_TE010001UV01-te" id="desc-REDS_TE010001UV01-te" lastEdit="2010-06-15T11:48:38"><p>Context-aware knowledge request event initiated by the CIS (e.g., as a result of a user clicking on an Infobutton). </p></descriptive><statrans transitionFQN="NEW" focalClass="InfobuttonEventNotification"><rmimref role="focalRMIM" ref="REDS_RM010001UV-rmi" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refIdentifier="REDS_RM010001UV"/></statrans><intref role="fires" ref="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition New Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Knowledge Request" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010001UV01"/><intref role="fires" ref="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Complete Fulfillment Request" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Knowledge Response" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010002UV01"/></trigger></triggerdivn><rmimdivn identifier="rmims-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="rmims-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><descriptive identifier="rmop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Reference" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="rmop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><rmim identifier="REDS_RM010001UV01" name="Infobutton Definition New" familiarName="Knowledge Request Message Model" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="10|02|05|" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" class="changed" lastEdit="2010-06-15T11:49:57"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_RM010001UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" id="desc-REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" lastEdit="2010-06-15T11:49:57"><div1 id=""><head>RMIM attribute walk-through</head><p><emph role="strong">KnowledgeRequestNotification class</emph></p><p>This class represents the root of the KnowledgeRequestNotification RMIM. The following are definitions of the attributes of the KnowledgeRequestNotification class:</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">KnowledgeRequestNotification.id</emph>: Represents the globally unique instance identifier of a knowledge request.</item><item><emph role="strong">KnowledgeRequestNotification.effectiveTime</emph>: creation time of the knowledge request.</item></list><p><emph role="strong">KnowledgeRequestNotification Relationships</emph></p><p>This section describes classes related to the root KnowledgeRequestNotification class:</p><p><emph role="strong">MainSearchCriteria</emph>: represents the main subject of interest in a knowledge request (e.g., a medication, a lab test result, a disease in the patient's problem list). When multiple instances of this class are present, knowledge resources MAY determine whether to join the multiple instances using the AND vs. OR Boolean operator.The following are attributes of the mainSearchCriteria class:</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">MainSearchCriteria.code</emph>: indicates that the type of this Observation class is KnowledgeSubjectObservationType.</item><item><emph role="strong">MainSearchCriteria.value</emph>: the primary knowledge subject of interest (e.g., a medication, a laboratory test, a condition). 
<p>CD data type restrictions for mainSearchCriteria.value: 1) displayName SHALL be always present, so that knowledge resources that do not support a given code system MAY still process the request using displayName as a search keyword; 2) If code is present, codeSystem SHALL be also present; 3) originalText represents the human readable representation of the code as displayed to the user in the CIS and SHOULD be used only if different than the displayName.</p></item></list><p><emph role="strong">SeverityObservation</emph>: specifies the interpretation of a laboratory test result (e.g., 'high', 'low', 'abnormal', 'normal'). This class MAY be used to support implementations where the MainSearchCriteria consists of a laboratory test result. Supports questions such as "what are the causes of high serum potassium?"</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">SeverityObservation.code</emph>: a code that defines that the type of the observation is  SeverityObservation.</item><item><emph role="strong">ObservationInterpretation.code</emph>: a code that represents the value of the observation interpretation (e.g., high, low, normal)..</item></list><p><emph role="strong">SubTopic</emph>: narrows down the knowledge request by specifying a subdomain of interest r(e.g., indications, contra-indications, dose) related to the MainSearchCriteria knowledge subject. In Infobutton implementations, the SubTopic may be selected by the user from an Infobutton page that presents a list of content areas that are relevant in a specific context (e.g., "contra-indications of digoxin", "adverse effects of digoxin"). </p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">SubTopic.code</emph>: defines that the type of this Observation class is KnowledgeSubtopicObservationType </item><item><emph role="strong">SubTopic.value</emph>: a code that represents a knowledge subtopic of interest (e.g., diagnosis, treatment, adverse effects).</item></list><p><emph role="strong">TaskContext</emph>: the task that the user is performing in the CIS when a knowledge request is initiated (e.g., order entry, laboratory results review, problem list review, medications list review).</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">TaskContext.code</emph>: a code that represents the task that is being performed in an CIS system.</item></list><p><emph role="strong">Encounter</emph>: the type of patient encounter (e.g., inpatient, outpatient) in which the knowledge request takes place..</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">Encounter.code</emph>: a code that represents the type of encounter (e.g., inpatient, outpatient).</item></list><p><emph role="strong">DeliveryLocation</emph>: clinical facility where the patient care is taking place at the time the knowledge request is initiated. MAY be used by the request filler to identify potential local knowledge resources (e.g., local protocols) that are specific to the facility where the patient care is being delivered.</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">DeliveryLocation.id</emph>: identifier of the facility where the patient care takes place.</item></list><p><emph role="strong"><emph role="strong">KnowledgeRequestNotification </emph>Participants</emph></p><p>This section describes participants of the KnowledgeRequestNotification RMIM.</p><p><emph role="strong">AssignedEntity</emph>: entity (e.g., institution) that initiated the request. MAY be used by a knowledge request recipient to determine the knowledge resources that the requesting entity has access to (e.g., based on subscriptions). In addition, allows the identification of an individual within the institution, so that personal preferences can be considered by a knowledge request filler when processing the request.</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">AssignedEntity.name</emph>: username used by the entity (typically as part of an institutional subscription to a knowledge resource)</item><item><emph role="strong">AssignedEntity.certificateText</emph>: password associated with the username of the entity</item></list><p><emph role="strong">Organization</emph>: the entity within which the request is initiated.</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">Organization.id</emph>: identifier of the organization within which the request was initiated</item><item><emph role="strong">AuthorizedPerson</emph>: the individual who initiated the knowledge request</item><item><emph role="strong">AuthorizedPerson.id</emph>: username of the person who initiated the request. MAY be used by a knowledge request filler to apply personal preferences during the user's session.</item></list><p><emph role="strong">PatientContext</emph>: information about the patient that MAY be used by the CIS in a knowledge request to further specify the context in which a knowledge need arises.</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">PatientPerson.administrativeGenderCode</emph>: gender of the patient represented in the knowledge request.</item></list><p><emph role="strong">PerformerChoice</emph>: defines the type of Participants that act as the Performer (user who interacts with the system) and InformationRecipient (person who will consume the content). The <emph>performer </emph>and <emph>informationRecipient </emph>can be instantiated as a <emph>Patient </emph>or <emph>HealthCareProvider </emph>class. Three scenarios are possible: 1) when a care provider interacts with the system seeking knowledge to fulfill his/her own needs, both the <emph>performer </emph>and <emph>informationRecipient </emph>SHALL be a <emph>HealthCareProvider</emph>; 2) when a care provider initiates the knowledge request, but looking for educational information to be given to the patient, the <emph>ierformer </emph>SHALL be a <emph>HealthCareProvider </emph>and the <emph>informationRecipient </emph>SHALL be associated with a <emph>Patient</emph>; and 3) when a patient is looking for information to fulfill her own needs, both the <emph>performer</emph> and the <emph>informationRecipient </emph>SHALL be a Patient.</p><p><emph role="strong">Age</emph>: age of the patient as a numeric value.</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">Age.code</emph>: a code that indicates that the type of this observation is AgeObservationType.. </item><item><emph role="strong">Age.value</emph>: the patient's age as a numeric quantity. Units SHOULD be expressed in one of the following units (per the Unified Code for Units of Measure): years (a), months (mo), weeks (wk), days (d), or hours (h).</item></list><p><emph role="strong">AgeGroup</emph>: an observation that represents the patient's age in terms of a predefined coded age range (e.g., infant, neonate).</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">AgeGroup.code</emph>: a code that indicates that the type of this observation is AgeGroupObservationType.</item><item><emph role="strong">AgeGroup.value</emph>: a code that represents the patient's age group.</item></list><p><emph role="strong">PerformerChoice Relationships</emph></p><p><emph role="strong">LanguageCommunication</emph>: language of the <emph>performer </emph> or <emph>informationRecipient</emph>. In implementations, language of the <emph>performer </emph>MAY be used by to determine the language of the individual who initiated a knowledge request, while language of the <emph>informationRecipient </emph>MAY be used to determine the language of the individual who will consume the content. For example, when a clinician looks for patient education information, the clinician's language may be English, while the patient is a Spanish speaker. In this case, while the user interface for the clinician can be presented in English, the requested patient education content will be presented in Spanish.
			</p><list role="unordered"><item><emph role="strong">LanguageCommunication.code:</emph> A code that represents the person's language (e.g., English, Spanish).</item></list></div1></descriptive><rmimref role="parent" ref="REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition New" refFamiliarName="Knowledge Request Message Model" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_RM010001UV01"/><diagref ref="REDS_RM010001UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="REDS_HD010001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition New Knowledge Request" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Knowledge Request" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_HD010001UV01"/></rmim></rmimdivn><hmddivn identifier="hmds-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="hmds-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><descriptive identifier="hdop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Reference" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="hdop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><hmd identifier="REDS_HD010001UV01" name="Infobutton Definition New Knowledge Request" familiarName="Infobutton Knowledge Request" parent="REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" id="REDS_HD010001UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="10|02|05|KNOWLEDGE REQUEST|" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" class="changed" lastEdit="2011-08-01T16:29:51"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_HD010001UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_HD010001UV01-hmd" id="desc-REDS_HD010001UV01-hmd" lastEdit="2011-08-01T16:29:51"><p>See RMIM attribute walk-through.</p></descriptive><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="REDS_HD010001UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="REDS_RM010001UV01-rmi" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition New" refFamiliarName="Knowledge Request Message Model" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_RM010001UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="REDS_MT010001UV01-msg" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Event Notification" refFamiliarName="Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_MT010001UV01"/></hmd></hmddivn><msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="msgs-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><msgtype identifier="REDS_MT010001UV01" name="Infobutton Event Notification" familiarName="Event Notification" parent="REDS_HD010001UV01-hmd" id="REDS_MT010001UV01-msg" sortPrefix="10|20|99|NOTIFICATION" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-01-11T20:12:07"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="REDS_MT010001UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="REDS_HD010001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition New Knowledge Request" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Knowledge Request" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_HD010001UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition New Notification" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Knowledge Request" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010001UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Complete Fulfillment Request" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Knowledge Response" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010002UV01"/></msgtype></msgtypedivn><interactiondivn identifier="ints-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Interactions" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="ints-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><descriptive identifier="inop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Reference" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="inop-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gintact" alt="the definition of Interactions"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><interaction identifier="REDS_IN010001UV01" name="Infobutton Definition New Notification" familiarName="Infobutton Knowledge Request" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="10|02|05|05|" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" class="changed" lastEdit="2010-06-15T11:50:24"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_IN010001UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_IN010001UV01-int" id="desc-REDS_IN010001UV01-int" lastEdit="2010-06-15T11:50:24"><p> Infobutton knowledge request initiated by the CIS (typically as a result of a user clicking on an Infobutton). The knowledge request is submitted to the knowledge resource.</p></descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="REDS_AR010001UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Creator Placer Clinical Information System" refFamiliarName="Clinical Information System" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010001UV01"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Completion Fulfiller Knowledge Resource" refFamiliarName="Knowledge Resource" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010002UV01"/><teref role="trigger" ref="REDS_TE010001UV01-te" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition New Notification" refFamiliarName="Knowledge Request" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_TE010001UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="REDS_MT010001UV01-msg" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_MT010001UV01"/></interaction><interaction identifier="REDS_IN010002UV01" name="Infobutton Definition Complete Fulfillment Request" familiarName="Infobutton Knowledge Response" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="10|02|40|11|" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2009-11-24T15:33:29"><descriptive identifier="desc-REDS_IN010002UV01" name="Description" parent="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" id="desc-REDS_IN010002UV01-int" lastEdit="2009-11-24T15:33:29"><p>Knowledge resource response to an infobutton knowledge request. As previously mentioned, note that the message payload for this interaction is outside the scope of this specification.</p></descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="REDS_AR010002UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Completion Fulfiller Knowledge Resource" refFamiliarName="Knowledge Resource" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010002UV01"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="REDS_AR010001UV01-ar" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Creator Placer Clinical Information System" refFamiliarName="Clinical Information System" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_AR010001UV01"/><teref role="trigger" ref="REDS_TE010001UV01-te" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition New Notification" refFamiliarName="Knowledge Request" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_TE010001UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="REDS_MT010001UV01-msg" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Event Notification" refIdentifier="REDS_MT010001UV01"/><rcvrresp identifier="REDS_IN010002UV01_Resp1" name="Responsibility- 1" parent="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" id="REDS_IN010002UV01_Resp1-rsp"><teref role="responsetrigger" ref="REDS_TE010001UV01-te" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition New Notification" refFamiliarName="Knowledge Request" class="changed" refIdentifier="REDS_TE010001UV01"/><intref role="responseinteraction" ref="REDS_IN010002UV01-int" sectID="hmreds" sectType="SB" refName="Infobutton Definition Complete Fulfillment Request" refFamiliarName="Infobutton Knowledge Response" refIdentifier="REDS_IN010002UV01"/></rcvrresp></interaction></interactiondivn><annexdivn identifier="annx-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Implementation Guide for Context-aware Knowledge Retrieval (Infobutton)" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="annx-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" role="IG" baseClass="Infobutton" ballotStatus="InformativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><descriptive identifier="annxInt-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton" name="Introduction" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" id="annxInt-REDS_DO010001UV-Infobutton-ic" lastEdit="2011-06-15T14:53:39"><p>This Annex holds three Implementation Guides that have been developed for use with the Infobutton standard. </p><p><loc href="HL7_V3_IG_INFOBUTTON_R2_INFORMATIVE_2009SEP.pdf">URL-Based Implementations of the Context-Aware Information Retrieval (Infobutton) Domain, Release 2</loc></p><p><loc href="V3IG_INFOBUTTON_R3_INFORM_2010DEC.pdf">URL-Based Implementations of the Context-Aware Information Retrieval (Infobutton) Domain, Release 3</loc></p><p><loc href="V3_IG_SOA_KM_INFOBUTTON_DSTU_R1_2011MAR.pdf">Context-Aware Knowledge Retrieval (Infobutton) Service Oriented Architecture Implementation Guide, Release 1</loc></p></descriptive></annexdivn></subdivn><indexdivn identifier="cindx-REDS_DO010001UV" name="Common Message Elements Indexes" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="cindx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-1" name="Common Message Elements Defined in this Domain" parent="cindx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DO010001UV-icc1id"/><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-2" name="Common Message Elements Used by this Domain" parent="cindx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DO010001UV-icc2id"/></indexdivn><indexdivn identifier="indx-REDS_DO010001UV" name="Interaction Indexes" parent="REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="indx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="indx-List-1" name="Interaction Index by Application Role" parent="indx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DO010001UV-ic1id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-2" name="Interaction Index by Trigger Event" parent="indx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DO010001UV-ic2id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-3" name="Interaction Index by Message Type" parent="indx-REDS_DO010001UV-ic" id="REDS_DO010001UV-ic3id"/></indexdivn></body></spec>

