<!-- $Id: mIntCategory.cls,v 1.4 2007/11/18 02:48:41 wbeeler Exp $ -->
<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-4" "../../support/dtd/v3mDomain.dtd">-->
<spec id="REPC_DO000000UV-ic" sectionCode="HMREPC" lastEdit="2011-07-13T16:47:08" rendered="2011-07-14T14:45:11"><header><title>Domain: Care Provision</title><version>V 00-00</version><ballot type="MixedContent" number="1"/><date>7/14/2011</date><authlist><author><role>Patient Care Co-Chair</role><name key="01">William Goossen, PhD, RN</name><affiliation>Results 4 Care, Netherlands</affiliation></author><author><role>Patient Care Co-Chair</role><name key="02">Susan Matney, R.N., M.S.</name><affiliation>Clinical Analyst in the Clinical Informatics department at SIEMENS Medical Solutions, USA</affiliation></author><author><role>Patient Care Co-Chair</role><name key="03">Lawrence McKnight, MD.</name><affiliation> Physician Consultant, Siemens Medical Solutions</affiliation></author><author><role>Modeling &amp; Methodology Facilitator</role><name key="04">John Kufuor-Boakye, M.Sc</name><affiliation>HL7 Canada</affiliation></author><author><role>Vocabulary Facilitator</role><name key="05">Jeri M. Jones</name><affiliation> Senior Consultant, VHA VHIM Project CGI-AMS (CGIFederal)</affiliation></author><author><role>Publishing Facilitator</role><name key="06">Mary Ann Juurlink, B.Sc</name><affiliation>e-Health Program, Ontario Ministry of Health and Long-Term Care, Canada</affiliation></author></authlist><legalese copyRightDate="2011" copyRightOwner="Health Level Seven, Inc." copyRightNotation="All rights reserved." renderer="RoseTree 4.2.54" renderNotation="This document was rendered into XML using software provided to HL7 by Beeler Consulting LLC." contactEmail="HQ@HL7.org" contactName="HL7 Headquarters Staff" contactNote="Comments or questions about this document may be may be addressed to:"/></header><front><div1 id=""><head>HL7 Draft Standard for Trial Use</head><p>This is a Draft Standard for Trial Use of the Version 3 Care Provision: Allergy and Intolerance, DSTU Release 1 topic. This topic, in the Care Provision domain, was approved as a DSTU following a successful DSTU ballot during HL7 International's September 2007 ballot cycle and approved by HL7's TSC for an extension of 24 months in May 2011. </p><p>"Publication of this draft standard for trial use and comment has been approved by Health Level Seven, Inc. (HL7). This draft standard is not an accredited American National Standard. The comment period for use of this draft standard shall end 24 months from the date of publication. Suggestions for revision should be submitted at //www.hl7.org/dstucomments/index.cfm.  </p><p>Following this 24 month evaluation period, this draft standard, revised as necessary, will be submitted to a normative ballot in preparation for approval by ANSI as an American National Standard. Implementations of this draft standard shall be viable throughout the normative ballot process and for up to six months after publication of the relevant normative standard .</p></div1><div1 id="prefNotes"><head>Notes to Readers</head><p>Knowledge and awareness of a patient's adverse reactions to agents/substances is essential for quality of patient care and for patient safety. These adverse reactions can lead to the identification and recording of one of two clinical concerns, namely: Allergy Concern, and Non-Allergy Intolerance Concern.</p><list role="unordered"><item>Allergy Concern - An allergy is an acquired sensitivity to an agent/substance (allergen) that causes the patient's immune system to "hyper" react after exposure to that agent/substance. </item><item><p>Non-Allergy Intolerance - A non-allergy intolerance indicates the potential for a response to an agent/substance that is harmful or undesirable but is rarely life-threatening and is not mediated by the immune system via acquired sensitivity.     </p></item></list><p>The purpose of the transactions is to record and maintain discrete data relating to a patient's intolerance (allergy intolerance or Non-Allergy Intolerance) to exposure to agents/substances for subsequent referencing and clinical decision-making.    </p><p>The Patient Care Technical Committee announced the formation of a ballot group for the Allergies Intolerance with Release 1 (2nd DSTU ballot) passing DSTU in January 2007.  A few non substantive changes were required.      </p><p>All negative comments were addressed:  Storyboards were written, the Domain model for Allergy/Intolerance as well the Refined Message Information Models for; Allergy/Intolerance List, Allergy/Intolerance Group Negation Observations, Allergy/Intolerance Concern were completed.    </p><p>These changes were made and reflected in the September 2007 ballot.    </p><p>On March 10, 2008 the request to publish Allergies Intolerance Topic as a DSTU was approved by the Technical Steering Committee for a 2 year period.  </p><p><graphic source="T-REPC_NA000002.jpg"></graphic></p></div1><div1 id="prefAck"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The Patient Care technical Committee would like to recognize the contributions of the following authors / editors, developers and organizations without whom this document could not have been produced:   </p><p>Larry McKnight, Siemens Healthcare, USA  </p><p>William Goossen, PhD, RN  Results 4 Care, Netherlands </p><p>Susan Matney, R.N., M.S.  Clinical Analyst in the Clinical Informatics department at SIEMENS Medical Solutions, USA</p><p>Tom deJong, Novo-Pro Consulting, The Netherlands  </p><p>John Kufuor-Boakye, M.Sc  HL7 Canada </p><p>Mary Ann Juurlink, B.Sc  e-Health Program, Ontario Ministry of Health and Long-Term Care, Canada</p><p>Lloyd McKenzie, LM&amp;A Consulting, HL7 Canada   </p><p>Dan Russler Daniel Russler, MD, VP of Clinical Informatics, Oracle, USA   </p><p>Heath Frankel, BSc, Frankel Informatics, Australia </p><p>Special thanks to all those who take the time to review the ballot and submit comments.</p></div1><div1 id="navigate-divs"><head>Message Design Element Navigation</head><artree role="NAVIGATE"><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="REPC_RM000324UV01-rmi" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergy/Intolerance Concern" refIdentifier="REPC_RM000324UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="REPC_HD000324UV01-hmd" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Concern" refIdentifier="REPC_HD000324UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="REPC_MT000324UV01-msg" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Concern" refIdentifier="REPC_MT000324UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="REPC_RM000322UV01-rmi" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergy/Intolerance List" refIdentifier="REPC_RM000322UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="REPC_HD000322UV01-hmd" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance List" refIdentifier="REPC_HD000322UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="REPC_MT000322UV01-msg" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance List" refIdentifier="REPC_MT000322UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="REPC_RM000323UV01-rmi" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergy/Intolerance Summary Observation" refIdentifier="REPC_RM000323UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="REPC_HD000323UV01-hmd" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergy/Intolerance Summary Observation" refIdentifier="REPC_HD000323UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="REPC_MT000323UV01-msg" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergy/Intolerance Summary Observation" refIdentifier="REPC_MT000323UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem></artree></div1></front><body><div1 id="intro-REPC_DO000000UV-ic" ballotStatus="MixedContent" ballotNumber="1"><head>Overview</head><div2 id="spec-scope" lastEdit="2006-07-23T14:33:25"><head>Introduction &amp; Scope</head><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css"?><p><emph role="strong">Scope of Care Provision Domain: </emph>The Care Provision Domain addresses the information that is needed for the ongoing care of individuals, populations, and other targets of care. The "Act of Care Provision" is the recording of a process that defines the responsibility for supplying support to the target of care. It is a statement of SUPERVISION, MANAGEMENT, and CUSTODY.</p><p>The people or other entities associated with "Responsibility for Care," are divided into the providers and targets of care, where a patient may be considered both a provider and a target of care and where any person may carry multiple roles. The scope of the "Responsibility for Care" is defined in three "layers." (1) The Act of Care Provision represents a kind of responsibility defined by CareProvision.code, which usually represents the scope of responsibility described by a governmental license, a certification agency, or other legally recognized entity such as the patient themselves. (2) The reasons for the Care Provision further constrains the scope of responsibility to one or more "Concerns" (3) The third layer expresses the Care Plans or management plans. These plans further identify the expectations for specific actions to be performed via the component relationship. The first layer is required in a statement of responsibility; the second two layers, which constrain the first layer, are optional. </p><p>In the context of HL7, a "Concern" is worry about a state or process that has the potential to require intervention or management. A problem list is an example of a list of concerns. </p><p>For example, diabetes may be on the problem list. However, the scope of responsibility for an endocrinologist might be only the diabetes and not the other problems. Diabetes is then identified as the reason for the Care Provision. The expectation of the endocrinologist may only include recommendations for a modification to the diabetes care plan. This specific diabetes care plan modification is then a component of the Care Provision scope of responsibility.</p><p>In the same way in the public health arena, the responsibility for a population may be limited to managing an Outbreak of infectious disease. </p><p>Therefore, the essential concept in this Care Provision Domain is the recording of the responsibility for care provision. Management plans (care plans) for the subjects of concern may be included in the scope of the responsibility for care provision. </p><p>This domain also includes the transfer of responsibility for care and the updating of pertinent information about respective responsibilities between collaborating care providers, such as the communications that occur when a patient is discharged from the hospital to a home health agency. This domain recognizes the fact that care coordination often includes many types of providers that care for people, devices, facilities, and the general environment, not just clinicians delivering direct care to a patient. The pertinent information regarding care provision may include general summary information or granular primary information, but may not carry all the information known about a specific instance in the generating system. However, in general, the scope of the domain includes all the information needed for decision support by a care provider. At a minimum, the domain includes the identifiers and other data needed to query a source system for the additional information needed for care. The scope is formalized in the following scope statement.</p><p>The Care Provision Domain describes information structures and vocabulary used to communicate information pertinent to the care of living subjects, devices, geographic sites, and other physical entities by a responsible care provider. This domain supports multiple specifications appropriate to referrals and record communications supporting collaboration and the continuity of care between care providers.
	</p><p>Among other more generalized care activities that can be defined by analogy and interpretation of the scope above, the Care Provision Domain specifically supports:</p><list role="unordered"><item>Sharing of health record extracts and event summaries of the health record between collaborating providers (including the patient) in order to support the clinical decision support activities of the receiving persons or systems.</item><item>Request for the transfer of patient care responsibility of a specific type of care by a healthcare provider by a requesting healthcare provider, a responsible party, such as a care coordinator, advocate or family member or the patient themselves. </item><item>Acceptance or rejection of a request for care transfer as well as the ability to provide information about the intent to provide care to the requesting party. </item><item>Communication of a summary of relevant findings and outcomes of the care provided in response to a request for further information.</item></list><p><emph role="strong">Limits of Scope: </emph>The scope of the Care Provision Domain is also limited by its focus on Care Provision Act, "an HL7 Act that describes "the responsibility for supplying support to the target of care."</p><p>The Care Provision Domain is not intended to represent all the information communicated by systems that originate detailed pertinent information such as observation data or person registration data. The domains that support communication from these data generating systems tend to supply much more detail regarding the complex data context within which the data was generated. In that spirit, the intention of the Care Provision Domain is to communicate the instance identifiers and meta data for these granular instances of data such that the receiving system has enough information to query sending systems for more detail on specific items of pertinent information (assuming the sending systems support queries and instance identifiers).</p><p><emph role="strong">Readers: </emph>Please see the Glossary Section for terms important to the Care Provision Domain</p><p><emph role="strong">Care Provision Domain and Care Structures Topic Ballot Guidance</emph>:Except for the Care Structures Topic, all the other topics under the Care Provision Domain relate to implementation specifications. In contrast, the Care Structures Topic focuses on additional information in the Care Provision Domain that may be specified at <emph>RMIM development</emph> or at <emph>system runtime. </emph>After reviewing this Care Provision Domain Document, the next document to review is the Care Structures Topic document. </p><p><emph role="strong">Guidance to balloters on Provider Act Relationships: </emph>Further harmonization needs to occur on the specific structures, e.g. CMET's, used by various domains to describe the providers of care. The broad description of potential providers used in this domain needs to be able to be constrained to the providers supported by CDA, Patient Administration, and Personnel Management for patient-related use cases. The CMET's chosen for this domain are described in the CMET documents. </p></div2></div1><dmimdivn identifier="dmims-REPC_DO000000UV" name="Domain Message Information Models" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-ic" id="dmims-REPC_DO000000UV-ic"><dmim identifier="REPC_DM000000UV" name="Care Provision" familiarName="Care Provision" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-ic" id="REPC_DM000000UV-rmi" sortPrefix="99|99|99|CARE PROVISION" class="changed" lastEdit="2006-11-13T06:33:37"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_DM000000UV" name="Description" parent="REPC_DM000000UV-rmi" id="desc-REPC_DM000000UV-rmi" lastEdit="2006-11-13T06:33:37"><p><emph role="strong">1.2 Domain Message Information Model</emph></p><p><emph role="strong">1.2.1 Care Provision (REPC_DM000000)</emph></p><p><emph role="strong">1.2.2  <emph>Description</emph></emph></p><p><emph role="strong">1.2.2.1 Overall Organization of the Care Provision DMIM</emph></p><p>This domain-level document describes in detail the focal act of the domain, the Care Provision Act, which establishes the context for the entire domain.  </p><p>In addition to the Care Provision Act itself, this section includes a walk-through of the associations on the Care Provision Act. These associations include participations (to Providers and Targets of Care), reasons (to Conditions), components (e.g., to Care Statements), and pertinent information (to any additional information required for care, such as listed in the Choicebox Care Statement).</p><p>Most of the variability in the Care Provision DMIM will be expressed through patterns of detailed clinical information called Care Structures. The walk-throughs of these patterns are included in the Care Structures Topic section. These patterns are expressed in the topic section as RMIM's and HMD's. For now, the patterns are called CMET's, despite the limitation of their use to the Care Provision Domain. When these structures pass ballot in the Care Provision Domain, they may be submitted as shared CMET's for use by multiple domains. The CMET's described in the Care Structures Topic include many structures such as: Care Statement; Condition Tracking; Worklist; Care Plan; and Guideline, among others. These CMET's are utilized in the message specification topics such as the Care Transfer and Care Record Topics in order to simplify the illustrations. </p><p>However, in this section, the focus will be on the meaning of the Care Provision Act and on the associations surrounding the Care Provision Act. </p><p><emph role="strong">1.2.2.2 Care Provision Act in Patient Care</emph></p><p>An understanding of this act is central to the concept of patient care by professionals. Normally, a patient is completely responsible for his or her own care. However, when people are ill, it is difficult for them to be completely responsible themselves. Part of the process of healthcare is that patients request that healthcare providers help them with their care. This request to help is central to the contract between patients and their healthcare providers. It is also common in healthcare for one professional to request the help of another professional in the context of this contract with the patient. This Care Provision Act represents a statement about the scope of responsibility that is shared between the patient, sometimes family members, and one or more healthcare providers. The discussion that follows is intended to further elucidate the concept of shared responsibility and extends the patient-related concepts of care to Care Provision in general.  </p><p>Care Provision Act: The meaning of the Care Provision Act begins with an examination of the meaning of "Care" and the meaning of "Provision" in the context of this domain. </p><p><emph role="strong">Stipulated Dictionary Definitions: </emph></p><emph role="strong">Care</emph> (5): CHARGE, SUPERVISION, MANAGEMENT: responsibility for or attention to safety and well-being (under a doctor's...), (the ... of all the churches) CUSTODY: temporary charge   <p><emph role="strong">Provision </emph>(2a): the act or process of providing (the ... of a play area for the children)  </p><p><emph role="strong">Provide </emph>(3): to supply what is needed for sustenance or support (the Lord will...), (we'll have to ... for him)  Merriam- Webster's Third New International Dictionary Unabridged, copyright 1961-2002.   </p><emph role="strong">Guidance</emph>: In the HL7 Reference Information Model (RIM), the term "Act" always represents the record of the "process of doing." "Care Provision" represents a constraint on the definition of "Act" that takes the form, "The Act of Care Provision" where "Care Provision" is the noun form of the infinitive "to provide care." Therefore, the "Act of Care Provision" is the recording of a process that defines the responsibility for supplying support. It is a statement of SUPERVISION, MANAGEMENT, and CUSTODY.   <p>In healthcare, many workers are assigned to the care of facilities and devices as well as living subjects. This Act of Care Provision is to be used when the explicit accountability for the care of a living or non-living subject is a component of the intended semantic. In other words the subject of care is defined in the subject participation, which constrains the semantic of care provision, e.g. subject is in a patient role; subject is in the role of a manufactured device.</p><p>In healthcare, the condition of the medical device, home of the patient, or other non-living subjects may need to be managed as well as the conditions of the patients' bodies themselves. Accordingly, "Care Provision" is often combined with the HL7 concepts of "Condition Tracking" and "Care Plan," structures that are found in the Care Structures Topic.</p><p>Examples: equipment care, patient care, facility care, responsibility for population monitoring, responsibility for an environmental site.   </p><p>Other Examples of the Scope of Care Provision include: </p><list role="ordered"><item>preferred primary care provision: the primary care physician being the primary performer participation, author being the patient</item><item>referral from general practitioner to specialist: (a Care Provision in request mood, where the author participant is the GP, and the primary performer participation is the specialist)</item><item>case management: case manager is the performer to a patient or group of patient subject participants</item><item>coverage assignment: assigning nurses to patients each shift </item><item>environmental site care: the environmental site is the subject participant and a company is the performer participant  </item><item>population monitoring: a population is the subject participant and the government agency is the performer participant</item></list><p><emph role="strong">1.2.2.3 Care Provision DMIM Walk-through</emph></p><p><emph role="strong">CareProvision Focal Class</emph></p><p>The Care Provision act is used to describe all aspects of care provision like the name of care professionals and the patient details.  This central act has relationships to itself and several other acts. Most of these relationships connect directly to acts of the Care Statement eg (observation, activities, encounters). It also has Participations which define roles of entities, e.g. the role of patient or provider of care. The details of the Care Provision Domain are described hereafter, beginning with the attributes.</p><p><emph role="strong"><emph>CareProvision Attributes </emph></emph></p><emph role="strong">classCode:</emph> The vocabulary domain specified for Act.classCode includes PCPR (Patient Care Provision) as a specialization of the Act class.       <p><emph role="strong">moodCode: </emph>Like all Acts in the RIM, the Care Provision Act may be expressed in many moods.These moods distinguish the different aspects of the business lifecycle of a Care Provision Act. These moods, which are central concepts for the DMIM, are defined as follows:   </p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Code </emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Definition  </emph></td></tr><tr><td>RQO (request) </td><td>A "Care Transfer Request" is a question to another care provider regarding their ability to accept the responsibility of Care Provision for the subject. Typically the request is made by a care provider, recorded within one computer system, and then transmitted to a second system for analysis and response by the receiving care provider. However, support is also provided to allow the patient to self-refer themselves. A referring Responsible party such as a State or Court may also author a Care Transfer Request. In a Care Transfer Request, the receiving provider is listed as the performer. The scope of responsibility including CareProvision.code, reasons for care provision, and component care plans that set the specific expectations for care apply to the scope of responsibility for the receiver of the request.  </td></tr><tr><td>PRMS (promise) </td><td>A "Care Provision Promise" is the statement of commitment to accept the responsibility of Care Provision as specified in the promise. It is assumed the receipt of a request message triggers a promise across a messaging interface from the requesting party. Due to the patient safety implications of care responsibility, there is no support for the type of "Implicit Promise" found in the Lab Domain. An acceptance of responsibility must be communicated as an explicit Promise. In this case, the performer is the sender of the promise. Likewise, the scope of responsibility including CareProvision.code, reasons for care provision, and component care plans that set the specific expectations for care apply to the scope of responsibility for the sender of the promise.  </td></tr><tr><td>EVN (event) </td><td>An Event according to the RIM is a service that actually happens, may be an ongoing service or a documentation of a past service.  <p>For Care Provision, a Care Provision Event is a record, which summarizes the events that happened during care including who is responsible for the care provided. An author of the "Care Provision Event" records and summarizes the events The performer is responsible for carrying out the care events.   The author and performer can be the same person.  Care Provision Event messages may be sent during the course of care to describe the progress of care or may be sent at the termination of care to describe all the activities that occurred during the provision of care. In this case, the performer is the sending provider.</p></td></tr><tr><td>DEF (definition) </td><td>Definition mood code can be used to express a guideline or protocol.</td></tr><tr><td>INT (intent)</td><td>Intent can be used to express the intended activities in a care plan. In particular the appropriate selection of observations and activities from a guideline that are included in the care plan for one particular patient. So the intended Acts are individualized from the guideline.  </td></tr><tr><td>PRP (proposal)</td><td>Proposal is used to suggest an idea to someone else, but not with the status of a request. It is further used as placeholder for the use in Care Plan R-MIM. For instance, it can be used by a consultant to recommend a course of action.    Care Provision Acts in different moods are linked by the fact that promises are created to fulfill requests, and events are created to fulfill promises and/or requests.     </td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">id: </emph>This attribute identifies a particular Care Provision. Identifier attributes can be used to identify an instance of a class. Sometimes more than one attribute may be needed to identify an instance of a class. The identifier attributes always have a value. The values of identifier attributes are unique among all instances of the class. Since identity is static, values of identifier attributes never change. Identifier attributes are assigned the set of instance identifier (SET&lt;II&gt;) data type and generally have the name "id" that allow for multiple identifiers to be specified.  The identifier attribute is a set of instance identifiers. This indicates that there may be multiple, unique identifiers for an Act. In the CareProvision Act, the "id" is used to give a unique id to all information that belongs together. It is used to identify the current care provision concerning a particular condition and the responsible providers. It is further used in queries and to trace back information of earlier care provisions for e.g. predecessor conditions, or related conditions and so on.     </p><emph role="strong">code: </emph>This attribute describes a kind of Care Provision Act in accordance with the definition of Act.code in the RIM. At this point in time, this attribute is CWE, and no value set is currently defined. CareProvision.code represents the kind of care provision and the person that is responsible for it. This guidance applies:   Care Provision is a statement of responsibility. The code for this statement should apply to a commonly accepted legal/regulatory/accrediting standard scope for responsibility. It is understood that these may differ by jurisdiction. In the US Realm, examples include: JCAHO; state licensing of hospitals, nursing homes, and home health agencies; medical and nursing specialty boards; etc. For example, a hospital discharge summary in a Wisconsin licensed hospital might use a code for "Wisconsin hospital care" or perhaps a JCAHO-certified acute care designation. This code is not to be interpreted as a setting code or an encounter code, but must be consistent with other related concepts, i.e. document type, encounter type, and scoping organizations for licensure or accreditation of participating providers. Local needs may require extensions of any given value set depending on local regulations and accreditations. A general value set for these concepts (that is expected to be extended by local agreement) will be defined by HL7, since external vocabularies do not at this time support this concept.   <p>The intention for the use of CareProvision.code is to define a traditional scope of domain expertise, e.g. Orthopedic Care; Oncology Care; Acute Care; Long-term Care, etc. This scope described by this general domain of expertise would then be further constrained by the list of Conditions listed as Reasons for Care and the Care Plans identified as components of the Care Provision Act. This entire scope of care is then included in the particular request, promise, or delivery of care represented by the mood codes used in the Care Provision Act.</p><p>For the time being, any act.code from any code system can be included here. For example codes from SNOMED CT:  </p><list role="unordered"><item>Preventive care:169443000: preventive procedure</item><item>Surgery: 257556004: surgery</item><item>Delivery: 386216000: human parturition, function</item></list><p>Each coding system is identified by the Object Identifier (OID), e.g. for SNOMED CT this would be: 2.16.840.1.113883.6.5      </p><p><emph role="strong">derivationExpr: </emph>The derivation expression attribute allows a string expression on derivation and is supported in an observation instance.  The derivationExpr will be replaced by a data type in the near future.  To be used by Decision support. Use cases will be included in a later stage. Is also used in the Care Plan. DSS will provide use cases in the near future and determine how decisions on this attribute will effect its use here.    </p><p><emph role="strong">negationId: </emph>There are 2 answering possibilities for the negation indicator: true, false. True means care is provided, false means no care is provided. However, the use of negation indicator in Care Provision Act is not encouraged. If it is used, a clear use case, and explicit interpretation guidelines must be provided to prevent medical errors. See terminfo project for future guidelines for application of negation.indicator      </p><p><emph role="strong">title: </emph>One title can be given to the Care Provision in free generated text.    </p><p><emph role="strong">text: </emph>This attribute can be used for a brief label of the care provision or short statement of type of Care Provision. It is not intended for a full text explanation of all that happened, or the reason for the care provision or the request. Such use is handled via explicit relationships to the care statement and conditions.     </p><emph role="strong">statusCode:</emph> The statusCode attribute is used to indicate the current state of the CareProvision class.  The statusCode attribute corresponds to the Act state machine and for the Care Provision Act has the following valid values:   <table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Code </emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Definition  </emph></td></tr><tr><td>active </td><td>The care provision can be performed or is being performed.  </td></tr><tr><td>suspended </td><td>A care provision that has been activated (actions could or have been performed against it), but has been temporarily disabled. No further action should be taken against it until it is resumed.  </td></tr><tr><td>completed </td><td>A care provision that has terminated normally after all of its constituents have been performed.  </td></tr><tr><td>aborted </td><td>The care provision has been terminated prior to the originally intended completion.  </td></tr><tr><td>obsolete </td><td>This care provision record has been replaced by a new instance.  </td></tr><tr><td>nullify </td><td>This care provision record was created in error and has been 'removed' and is treated as though it never existed. A record is retained for audit purposes only.    </td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">effectiveTime:</emph> The effectiveTime attribute represents the time interval for which the care provision is provided.  For intent care provision, the time will be proposed start and end date/time where applicable while care provision events, the time will be the actual start and end date/time   (for a more generic description of effective, please refer to the RIM).</p><p><emph role="strong">priorityCode:</emph> The priorityCode attribute has a potential overlap with some vocabularies. This potential conflict is resolved as follows:    </p><list role="unordered"><item>priorityCode should only be used to indicate the urgency with which the communication recipient should respond to the information in the Act. For example, the request for a procedure should be treated as 'urgent'. Consequently, it is desirable that the use of priorityCode should be limited to acts that are in 'Intent' mood.     </item><item>Act.code vocabulary expressions should be used to qualify the clinical immediacy of the expression that is in the code attribute. For example, the concept 'an Emergency appendectomy' should be expressed totally within Act.code   </item></list><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Code </emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Definition  </emph></td></tr><tr><td>A (ASAP)</td><td>As soon as possible, next highest priority after stat.</td></tr><tr><td>R (routine)</td><td>Routine service, do at usual work hours.  </td></tr><tr><td> S (stat)</td><td>With highest priority (e.g., emergency).</td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong"> confidentialityCode: The confientialityCode attribute </emph></p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Code </emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Definition  </emph></td></tr><tr><td>ConfidentialityByAccessKind </td><td>A value set that allows access to information by subject / role and relationship based rights (These concepts are mutually exclusive, one and only one is required for a valid confidentiality coding).  </td></tr><tr><td>ConfidentialityModifiers </td><td>Modifiers of role based access rights (multiple allowed). </td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">reasonCode:</emph> The reasonCode attribute specifies the motivation, cause, or rationale of a Care Provision, when such rationale is not reasonably represented as a "has reason" ActRelationship type linking to a Condition Observation.   </p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Code </emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Definition  </emph></td></tr><tr><td>PAT (patient request)</td><td>The Patient requested the care provision.  </td></tr><tr><td>MEDNEC (Medical Necessity)</td><td>Required for medical reasons(s).</td></tr><tr><td>ActBillableClinicalServiceReason</td><td>An abstract vocabulary domain linked to an external code set representing the reason for the Clinical Service being performed. <p>This domain excludes reasons specified by diagnosed conditions.  Examples of values from this domain include duplicate therapy and fraudulent prescription.    </p></td></tr></tbody></table><p> This CareProvision Focal Act has six Entry points:?</p><list role="unordered"><item>Care Provision: DMIM for Care Provision messages </item><item>CareRecord: Care Record</item><item>Care Transfer Request: Care Transfer Request</item><item>Care Transfer Promise: Accept Care Transfer </item><item>Care Plan: Care Plan Structure</item><item>A_PrincipalCareProvision: This defines the primary performer of a specified care provision. The care provision performer may generally be the primary provider or only within a specific health care facility. This relationship is usually solid over time and is recorder only for administrative purposes; actual care provided by this health care provider is recorder separately.</item></list><p>These RMIMs will be described in more detail in the respective topic section as to what purpose each has. In future additional entry points can be expected.</p><p><emph role="strong">CareProvision Associations</emph></p><p> In the Care Provision DMIM, the Care Provision Act is surrounded by associations.  The associations required for communication responsibility for Care Provision include: </p><list role="unordered"><item>Participations to "Provider" choice box (author, performer, primaryInformationRecipient)  </item><item>Participations to "Target" choice box (subject, recordTarget)</item><item>Participations to "R_AssignedPerson" CMET (verifier, dataEnterer)</item><item>Recursive "Is Sequel" ActRelationship, in which an earlier or a later care provision relationship can be established (sequelTo).</item><item> Recursive "Has Component" ActRelationship (component3) </item><item>Recursive "Has Pertinent Information" ActRelationship (pertinentInformation3) </item><item>The "Refers To" ActRelationship to current Encounter (reference)</item><item>The Care Provision "Has Reason" ActRelationship to Conditions (reason)</item><item>The "Has Component" ActRelationship to Care Statements (component1)</item><item>The "Has Component" ActRelationship to StatementCollector (component2) </item><item>The "Has Pertinent Information" ActRelationship to StatementCollector (pertinentInformation1)</item><item> the "Has Subject Of" ActRelationship to Care Statements (subjectOf) </item><item> the "Has Final Objective" ActRelationship .to Care Statements (final goal) </item></list>



















		These associations along with the Care Provision Act itself provide all the relationships needed to communicate:
		<list role="unordered"><item>Who is the provider with responsibility? </item><item>What or who is provider responsible for?</item><item>What prior lifecycle Act of Care Provision is fulfilled by this Care Provision instance, if applicable?  </item><item>What prior instance of the same Care Provision Act is replaced by this instance, if applicable? </item><item>What encounter this Care Provision Act is created within, if applicable?</item><item> Which Condition(s), i.e. Reasons for Care, are included in the provider's scope of responsibility? </item><item>What Care Plan activities are included in the provider's scope of responsibility?</item><item>What Observations and Acts have been carried out in this care provision or in earlier care provisions? </item></list><p><emph role="strong"><emph>Participations</emph></emph></p><emph>Common Participation Attributes</emph><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode</emph>: Provides a mechanism for specifying how participations contribute to the context of an act and whether the context may be conducted to associated child acts.  The example in the Introduction is an example of how context conduction can be used with participations.  </p>



















This attribute is a two character code that can be used in any combination (AN, AP, ON, OP) specifying the conduction behaviour:  <p>'AN' - the association is only added to the context of this act and is not conducted to any child acts. </p>


















'AP' - the association is added to the context of this act and may be conducted to any child acts.   <p>'ON' - any association(s) of the same or more specific type that are conducted from the parent are replaced by this association and this association is not conducted to any child acts.  </p>



















'OP' - any association(s) of the same or more specific type that are conducted from the parent are replaced by this association and this association may be conducted to any child acts.  <p><emph role="strong"><emph>recordTarget:</emph></emph></p><p>The record target is the entity for which the Care Provision is being recorded, like the details of the baby go in the record of the mother.  There can only be one record target for a Care Provision. The target entity information is captured within the R_Patient CMET or a Maintained Entity provided in the Target choice.  The Maintained Entity can be either a Device or Place, which is further described in the R_CaredEntity section of the Care Structures topic.  </p><p><emph>Attributes </emph></p><p><emph role="strong">typeCode:</emph> The type code is RCT (record target). </p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode</emph>: See description provided above in Common Participation attributes.  The default value is "OP" (overriding, propagating). <p><emph><emph role="strong">subject</emph></emph></p><p>The subject or subjects are the principal target(s) of the care provision when the subject is not the record target, e.g. the patient in physical examination, a specimen in a lab observation. May also be a patient's family member (teaching) or a device or room (cleaning, disinfecting, housekeeping). The subject information is captured within the R_Patient CMET or a Maintained Entity provided in the Target choice.  The Maintained Entity can be either a Device or Place, which is further described in the R_CaredEntity section of the Care Structures topic.   </p><p><emph>Attributes  </emph></p><p><emph role="strong">typeCode: </emph>  The type code is SBJ (subject).  </p><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided above in Common Participation attributes.  The default value is "OP" (overriding, propagating).    </p><emph role="strong"><emph>author </emph></emph><p>The party that requests, promises or records the Care Provision. This may be an assigned person or organization (R_AssignedParty) such as a healthcare provider, a related party (R_RelatedParty) such as a family member or court, or the patient (R_Patient) themselves.   </p><p><emph>Attributes  </emph></p><emph role="strong">typeCode:</emph> The type code is AUT (author (originator)).   <p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided above in Common Participation attributes.  The default value is "OP" (overriding, propagating).  .  </p><emph role="strong">noteText:</emph> Any commentary notes about the author participation.  <p><emph role="strong">time:</emph> The time the author signed or completed the documentation relating to the care provision act.</p><p><emph role="strong">modeCode: </emph>Specifies how the author provided the information, e.g. verbally, electronically or hand written.  Use any value from the ParticipationMode domain.  </p><p><emph role="strong">signatureCode:</emph> Code specifying if the author has, is required or intends to attest to the care provision act using a signature.</p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Code </emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description  </emph></td></tr><tr><td> I (intended) </td><td>The author intends to provide a signature. </td></tr><tr><td>S (signed)</td><td>Signature has been affixed, either written on file, or electronic (incl. digital) signature in signatureText.  </td></tr><tr><td>X (required) </td><td>A signature for the care provision act is required of this author.</td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">signatureText:</emph> A digital signature or multimedia representation of the signature provided by the author, attesting to the care provision act.    </p><p><emph role="strong"><emph>dataEnterer</emph></emph></p>













































The transcriptionist who enters the information of the Care Provision. The data enterer information is captured within the R_AssignedPerson CMET.<emph>Attributes  </emph><p><emph role="strong">typeCode:</emph> The type code is ENT (data entry person).  </p><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided above in Common Participation attributes.  The default value is "OP" (overriding, propagating).  </p><p><emph role="strong">time:</emph> The time the data entry person signed or completed the documentation relating to the care provision act.  </p><p><emph role="strong">modeCode: </emph>Specifies how the data entry person provided the information.  The default value is ELECTRONIC (electronic data).  Alternate values may be drawn from the ParticipationModeWritten domain.  </p><p><emph role="strong">signatureCode: </emph>Code specifying if the data entry person has or is required to attest to the care provision act using a signature.</p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Code </emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description  </emph></td></tr><tr><td> S (signed)</td><td> Signature has been affixed, either written on file, or electronic (incl. digital) signature in signatureText.</td></tr><tr><td> X (required) </td><td>A signature for the care provision act is required of this author.</td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">signatureText:</emph> A digital signature or multimedia representation of the signature provided by the data entry person, attesting to the care provision act.    </p><emph role="strong"><emph>verifier</emph></emph><p>The supervisor who verifies the request for care provision, promises to provide care or records information about the performed care. There is support for more than one level of verification. The verifying party information is captured within the R_AssignedPerson CMET.   </p><p><emph>Attributes  </emph></p><p><emph role="strong">typeCode:</emph> The type code is any value from ParticipationVerifier domain.</p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Code </emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description  </emph></td></tr><tr><td>VRF (verifier) </td><td>A person who verifies the correctness and appropriateness of the care provision act (plan, request, event, etc.) and hence takes on accountability. </td></tr><tr><td>AUTHEN (authenticator) </td><td>A verifier who attests to the accuracy of an care provision act, but who does not have privileges to legally authenticate the act. An example would be a resident physician who sees a patient and dictates a note, then later signs it. Their signature constitutes an authentication.  </td></tr><tr><td> LA (legal authenticator)</td><td>A verifier who legally authenticates the accuracy of a care provision act. An example would be a staff physician who sees a patient and dictates a note, then later signs it. Their signature constitutes a legal authentication.    </td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided above in Common Participation attributes. The default value is "OP" (overriding, propagating).  </p><p><emph role="strong">noteText:</emph> Any commentary notes about the verifier participation.  </p><p><emph role="strong">time:</emph> The time the verifier signed or accepted the care provision act.  </p><p><emph role="strong">modeCode:</emph> Specifies how the verifier provided his acceptance of the care provision act, e.g. verbally, electronically or hand written.  Use any value from the ParticipationModeWritten, ParticipationModeVerbal or ParticipationModeElectronicData domains.  </p><p><emph role="strong">signatureCode:</emph> Code specifying if the verifier has, is required or intends to attest to the care provision act using a signature.    </p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Code </emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description  </emph></td></tr><tr><td>I (intended) </td><td>The author intends to provide a signature. </td></tr><tr><td>S (signed)</td><td>Signature has been affixed, either written on file, or electronic (incl. digital) signature in signatureText. </td></tr><tr><td>X (required)</td><td>A signature for the care provision act is required of this author. </td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">signatureText: </emph>A digital signature or multimedia representation of the signature provided by the verifier, attesting to the care provision act.    </p><p><emph role="strong"><emph>performer </emph></emph></p><p> The party or parties, who are responsible for the scope of care identified by the Care Provision Act and its related conditions and care plans.  However, this person or organization may have "supervisors" or "monitors" who carry related management or regulatory responsibilities for the care.  </p><p>Care may be provided to a target of care by a broad range of providers. In a patient care example, care may be provided by the patient (R_Patient) themselves, the family members or other lay care takers (R_RelatedParty), a myriad of individual professional care providers or care provider organizations (R_AssignedParty).  Medical devices may participate in care, but obviously cannot take responsibility for care. In a non-patient care scenario, care may be provided to geographic sites by environmental engineers (R_AssignedParty).  </p><p>In many cases, the "author" and the "performer" are the same party. However, in a request for care, the "author" is requesting and the "performer" is the one who will take on a responsibility for care.  </p><p><emph>Attributes  </emph></p><p><emph role="strong">typeCode:</emph> The type code is a value from the following list derived from ParticipationPhysicalPerfomrer domain. </p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Code </emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description  </emph></td></tr><tr><td> PRF (performer) </td><td>A person who actually and principally carries out the care provision. Need not be the principal responsible actor, e.g. a surgery resident operating under supervision of attending surgeon, and may be the patient in self-care.  </td></tr><tr><td>PPRF (primary performer)</td><td>The principal or primary performer of the care provision. </td></tr><tr><td>SPRF (secondary performer)</td><td>A person assisting in care provision through his substantial presence and involvement. </td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">functionCode:</emph> An optional code specifying additional detail about the function that the performer has in the care provision, e.g. primary care physician, first surgeon, second surgeon, anesthetist, scrub nurse, attending physician.  </p><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided above in Common Participation attributes.  </p><emph role="strong">time: </emph>The start and/or end time the performer has/had responsibility for the care provision of the subject.  <p><emph role="strong">modeCode:</emph> Specifies how the performer provided the care provision, which involves more than just communication.  The default value is "PHYSICAL" (physical presence).  Allowable values are shown below:    </p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Code </emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description  </emph></td></tr><tr><td>PHYSICAL (physical presence)</td><td>Participation by direct action where subject and actor are in the same location.  </td></tr><tr><td> REMOTE (remote presence) </td><td>Participation by direct action where subject and actor are in separate locations, and the actions of the actor are transmitted by electronic or mechanical means.     </td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph><emph role="strong">primaryInformationRecipient </emph></emph></p>













































The party who is intended to receive the care transfer request or confirmation, or the record of care provision.  In the case of a care transfer request, the recipient is not the requested performer of the care provision but is receiving the request for the recipient's information and they do not need to act on the request.  Alternatively, the intended recipient of a care transfer confirmation (promise) is usually the author of the corresponding request but may also be a "copy to" recipient.  The intended recipient may be an assigned person or organization (R_AssignedParty) such as a healthcare provider, a related party (R_RelatedParty) such as a family member or court, or the patient (R_Patient) themselves. <p><emph>Attributes  </emph></p><p><emph role="strong">typeCode: </emph>The type code is PRCP (primary information recipient). </p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided above in Common Participation attributes.  The default value is "OP" (overriding, propagating).  <emph role="strong"><emph>  ActRelationships </emph></emph><p>In this domain, the pertinent information sent regarding patients is going to vary depending on the needs of the patient and the needs of the healthcare providers. Accordingly, this domain is organized into Care Structures that allow Partial Information Models to be used as building blocks in constructing the larger information model for a specific communication.   </p><emph>Common ActRelationship Attributes</emph><p>The following ActRelationship attributes are commonly used in Act Relationships associated with the Focal CareProvision Act and other associated Acts.  These attributes will be described in the general sense here and described in context with the specific Act Relationship where more specific detail is required.    </p><p>contextConductionInd: When the context conduction indicator attribute is set to "true", all context of the parent act that is marked as 'propagating' is conducted to the associated child act.  Alternatively, when set to "false", no context is conducted to the associated child act.  </p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> Specifies how a child act contributes to the context to the parent act.  If context is conducted to other child acts, then this attribute also specifies whether the context provided by the child is conducted to other children.  This attribute is a two character code that can be used in any combination (AN, AP, ON, OP) specifying the conduction behavior:<p> 'AN' - the association is only added to the context of this act and is not conducted to any child acts.  </p><p>'AP' - the association is added to the context of this act and may be conducted to any child acts.  </p><p>'ON' - any association(s) of the same or more specific type that are conducted from the parent are replaced by this association and this association is not conducted to any child acts.  </p><p>'OP' - any association(s) of the same or more specific type that are conducted from the parent are replaced by this association and this association may be conducted to any child acts.  </p><p><emph role="strong">sequenceNumber:</emph> The sequenceNumber attribute can be used to indicate the order of each component.</p><emph role="strong"><emph>Recursive Care Provision Act Relationships  </emph></emph><p>The Focal CareProvision Act has three relationships that refer back to the central Act itself: these are the so called Recursive relationships.</p><p><emph role="strong">sequelTo  </emph></p><p>
The sequelTo ActRelationship indicates a chronological order or lifecycle of care provision acts.  For example, for preventive care during a third pregnancy, it might be relevant to refer back to the first and second pregnancy's that are completed, and to the children that resulted from them.  Alternatively, a Care Provision Event may be related to the Care Provision Request for which the Event fulfils; or a replacement Care Provision Event that corrects a previous account of the Event.    </p><emph>Attributes  </emph><p><emph role="strong">typeCode: </emph>The type code is a subset of values from the ActRelationshipSequel domain as follows:</p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td>Code </td><td>Description  </td></tr><tr><td>SEQL (is sequel)</td><td>An act relationship indicating that the source care provision act follows the target care provision act. </td></tr><tr><td>FLFS (fulfills)</td><td>The source care provision act fulfills (in whole or in part) the target care provision act.  Source must be in a mood equal or more actual than the target.  </td></tr><tr><td>OCCR (occurrence) </td><td>The source care provision act is a single occurrence of a repeatable target care provision act.  Source must be in a mood equal or more actual than the target.  </td></tr><tr><td>RPLC (replaces) </td><td>A replacement source care provision act replaces an existing target care provision act. The state of the care provision act being replaced becomes obsolete, but the care provision act is typically still retained in the system for historical reference.    </td></tr><tr><td>INST (instantiates (master))</td><td>Used to capture the link between a potential care provision ("master" or plan) and an actual care provision, where the actual care provision instantiates the potential care provision. The instantiation may override the master's defaults.    </td></tr></tbody></table><p><emph role="strong">contextConductionInd:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.</p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.       <p><emph role="strong"><emph>component3</emph></emph></p>











































The component3 relationship has a source of CareProvision and a target that is another Care Provision, and is used to create groupings of CareProvisions in a more or less hierarchical order. E.g. for Care Provision that is given to a patient to treat a complication, like treatment for an allergy for antibiotics, part of an overall care provision for an infection.  <p> Categories of information may not only be considered "pertinent to the care," but also identified as part of the scope of responsibility for care defined by the Care Provision Act. In this case, the "Component" relationship is used instead of the "Pertinent Information" relationship.  For example, care plans or other methods of identifying expectations may be associated by "Component" relationships to the Care Provision Act.   </p><emph>Attributes  </emph><p><emph role="strong">typeCode:</emph> The type code is COMP (has component).   </p><p><emph role="strong">contextConductionInd: </emph>See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes. </p><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.</p><p><emph role="strong">sequenceNumber: </emph>The sequenceNumber attribute can be used to indicate the order of each component. </p><emph role="strong"><emph> pertinentInformation3 </emph></emph><p>The pertinentInformation3 relationship asserts a 'very unspecific relationship from one item of clinical information to another. It does not judge about the role the pertinent information plays.'  This is used to link any detailed existing information to the current Care Provision Act.  Examples include: past surgical history, a family history profile, historical list of dispensed medications.    </p><emph>Attributes  </emph><p><emph role="strong">typeCode:</emph> The type code is value from the following subset derived from the ActRelationshipPertains domain.  </p><table border="1" width="100%"><tbody><tr><td><emph role="strong">Code </emph></td><td><emph role="strong">Description  </emph></td></tr><tr><td>PERT (has pertinent information) </td><td>A very unspecific relationship from the source care provision act to another care provision act.  </td></tr><tr><td> SAS (starts after start of) </td><td> The source Care Provision Act starts after the start of the target Care Provision Act.  </td></tr><tr><td>PREV (has previous instance) </td><td>A relationship in which the target Care Provision act is a predecessor instance to the source Care Provision act. Generally each of these instances is similar, but not identical.  </td></tr><tr><td> SUMM (summarized by)</td><td>A Care Provision act that contains a summary of a list or set of subordinate Care Provision acts. </td></tr></tbody></table><emph role="strong">contextConductionInd:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes<p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes </p><p><emph role="strong">sequenceNumber:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes</p><emph><emph role="strong">Information related to Care Provision</emph></emph><p>The remaining associations from the Act of Care Provision are focused on supplying other pertinent information about the target of care intended to support collaboration between care providers. The types of information, further described in the Care Structures Topic, include: </p><list role="unordered"><item>Basic care statements, i.e. raw data with minimal summarization or interpretation </item><item>Summary information created in lists and other structures, e.g. medication lists, surgery lists, SOAP notes</item><item>Judgement-related care statements, e.g. problem lists, allergy lists</item><item>Care plans and their associated guideline definitions; what is proposed, what is ordered or scheduled, what was completed and what has yet to be completed</item><item>Statements about the condition affecting patient care takers such as family members, e.g. care taker fatigue  </item></list><p><emph><emph role="strong">reason</emph></emph></p><p>The reason act relationship specifies the clinical reason for the Care Provision represented as a Condition Observation.  The full guidance on "Reason for Care" is included in the discussion on "Conditions" in the Care Structures Topic document.  </p><emph>Attributes  </emph><p><emph role="strong">typeCode:</emph> The type code is RSON (has reason).  </p><p><emph role="strong">contextConductionInd:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.  The default value is "true". </p><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes  The default value is "AN" (Additive, non-propagating).    </p><emph><emph role="strong">reference  </emph></emph><p>The reference act relationship provides the Encounter information, which generated the Care Provision act.</p><emph>Attributes  </emph><p><emph role="strong">typeCode: </emph>The type code is REFR (refers to).  </p><p><emph role="strong"> contextConductionInd:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.  The default value is "false".  </p><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes  The default value is "OP" (overriding, propagating).</p><emph role="strong"><emph>pertinentInformation2</emph></emph><p>The pertinentInformation2 act relationship allows care statements pertinent but not part of the associated Care Provision act, such as relevant pathology and imaging observations, clinical findings, family history and assessment scales.  The target of the act relationship is the CareStatement choice, which is discussed in detail in the Care Structures topic.  </p><emph>Attributes  </emph><p><emph role="strong">typeCode: </emph>The type code is PERT (has pertinent information).  </p><p><emph role="strong">contextConductionInd:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.    </p><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.</p><emph role="strong"><emph>component1 </emph></emph><p>The component1 act relationship allows care statements pertinent that explicitly part of the associated Care Provision act, such as pathology and imaging observations, clinical findings, family history and assessment scales performed during the scope of the source care provision act.  The target of the act relationship is the CareStatement choice, which is discussed in detail in the Care Structures topic.  </p><emph>Attributes  </emph><p><emph role="strong">typeCode:</emph> The type code is COMP (component).  </p><p><emph role="strong">contextConductionInd: </emph>See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.  The default value is "true".  </p><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode: </emph>See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes  The default value is "AN" (Additive, non-propagating). </p><p><emph role="strong">sequenceNumber: </emph>See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.    </p><emph role="strong"><emph> pertientInformation1 </emph></emph><p>The pertinentInformation1 act relationship allows a managed collection of care statements pertinent but not directly related to associated Care Provision act.  The target of the act relationship is the StatementCollector choice which is discussed in detail in the Care Structures topic.  </p><emph>Attributes  </emph><p><emph role="strong">typeCode: </emph>The type code is PERT (has pertinent information). </p><p><emph role="strong">contextConductionInd:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.    </p><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode: </emph>See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.</p><p><emph role="strong">sequenceNumbe</emph>r: See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes. </p><emph role="strong"><emph> subjectOf </emph></emph><p>The subjectOf act relationship has the Care Provision act as the target of the "has subject" relationship where the source is the Care Statement.  This allows statements to be made that qualifies or provides additional information about the Care Provision act such as Annotations and planned reviews of a Care Plan.  </p><emph>Attributes  </emph><p><emph role="strong">typeCode: </emph>The type code is SUBJ (has subject). </p><p><emph role="strong">contextConductionInd:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.  The default value is "true". </p><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes  The default value is "AN" (Additive, non-propagating).    </p><emph role="strong"><emph>finalGoal  </emph></emph><p>The finalGoal act relationship allows a clinical statement that reflects the final objective of the Care Provision to be associated with the source act.  </p><emph>Attributes  </emph><p><emph role="strong">typeCode:</emph> The type code is OBJF (has final objective). </p><p><emph role="strong">contextConductionInd:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes.  The default value is "true". </p><p><emph role="strong">contextControlCode:</emph> See description provided in Common ActRelationship attributes  The default value is "AN" (Additive, non-propagating).      </p><p><emph role="strong">Domain Topics: </emph>The Care Provision Domain has been divided into a number of topics and focuses on the part of the information model that surrounds the Care Provision focal class. Other pertinent clinical information will be found in the Clinical Structures Topic mentioned below. A list of topics intended for the Care Provision Domain include:   </p><list role="unordered"><item>Care Structures Topic-This topic includes CMETS for the Care Provision Domain. Specific Care Structures include the Condition Tracking structure, the Care Plans/Guidelines structure, and other specific structures. The Care Statement Structure, which is a constrained and extended version of the Clinical Statement Pattern, is included in this section.   </item><item>Care Record Topic-This topic covers the summary and record extract notifications that are used to communicate the care actually given while a subject was under the care of a responsible party  </item><item>Care Record Query Topic-This topic covers the queries and query responses related to care actually given while a subject was under the care of a responsible party  </item><item>Care Transfer Topic-this topic covers the negotiation messages in the business cycle of requests and promises that occur when arranging the transfer of responsibility for care   </item><item>Care Transfer Query Topic-This topic covers the queries and query responses related to the status of care transfer negotiations  </item><item>International AffiliateTopics-These topics are introduced for comment purposes only. They may one day be submitted as proposals for ballot.</item></list></descriptive><diagref ref="REPC_DM000000UV.gif"/></dmim></dmimdivn><subdivn identifier="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Allergies &amp; Intolerance Topic" familiarName="Allergies &amp; Intolerance" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-ic" id="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="35" baseClass="Allergies &amp; Intolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1"><descriptive identifier="intro-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Introduction" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="intro-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" lastEdit="2007-07-28T19:43:08"><emph role="strong">Scope and Use Cases </emph><p>Allergy and Intolerance observations are some of the most commonly recorded, reviewed and transmitted information in the medical record. Clinicians record allergies and intolerances as a way to remind themselves and other providers to avoid giving substances that are known to potentially cause harm or discomfort to the patient. The process of identifying known adverse reactions and the believed causes for them is a critical element of good clinical practice and is essential for safety and quality (Nehta).   Within the context of allergies, adverse reactions are harmful or undesirable responses after administration of an agent/substance. Intolerance is a condition where the patient has been noted to have an adverse reaction and a judgment is made that the reaction was caused by a given substance.   Administration of substances (in the form of ingestion, inhalation, injection, or direct contact) may result in adverse reactions which may be classified as severe or mild, occur after variable lengths of time, and the relationship between exposure and the adverse reaction may be uncertain. Additionally, the noted exposure may be (usually is) to a mixture of complex substances. Additionally, many substances cross react, so that it may be a class of medications that cause problems. Therefore the assignment of causality of the actual relationship between the offending substance and the reaction is generally always uncertain to some degree. </p><p><emph role="strong">Use Case 1: The clinical "Allergy" list: </emph> Many make the distinction between a true allergy and intolerance. A true allergy is a type of intolerance with where the patient's immune system "hyper" reacts after exposure to that agent/substance or a chemically similar substance. True allergies typically result in a rash or swelling and may be life threatening. They also have defined treatments such as steroids antihistamines, or epinephrine. The classic example of this is the typical penicillin allergy.   Pragmatically, both true allergies and intolerances are recorded in a separate section of the medical record. Although this section is often (usually) called "the allergy list" it more accurately represents a list of "intolerances" or "alerts" since it mixes true allergies and intolerances. Different providers will have varying opinions on the need to specifically note minor intolerances to medications such as gastric upset in this section, however there is general agreement that true allergies and severe intolerances be recorded in this section and reviewed regularly. Some severe intolerances such as heparin induced thrombocytopenia do not follow the same physiologic pathways as true allergy but follow the same need for explicit and clear warning to prescribing or administrating providers and therefore are grouped in with "allergies." Fortunately, the modeling for allergies and intolerances for this purpose does not need to include details of pathogenesis to this degree, so this mixing while technically inaccurate is of little consequence.   Logically, an allergy or intolerance is a type of medical condition or concern. It is an observation (as judged by the clinician) that asserts the patient does or does not have a condition where a substance administration is felt to be associated with an adverse reaction. It may tracked like other medical concerns as a series of observations as further clarification or understanding of the nature of that allergy occurs. For example, an observation of an allergy to percocet may be refined to a mild intolerance to "oxycodone", but tracked separately from the concern about allergy beta-lactams being refined to exclude cephalosporins.   However, there are important distinctions between most medical concerns and allergies concerns. Because they are used as specific reminders not to administer or to alter therapy, they are generally called out as a separately tracked list. Other clinical conditions and patient data may also alter therapy as well (for example dose changes based on age or renal function, or contraindications to medications in certain medical conditions) but allergies are differentiated because they are recorded as the type of therapy to avoid rather than as conditions which usually can't be avoided. Also, in many cases systems may require explicit review and specific negative assertions for various types of known allergens. For example, it is most common to see a section of a document or element of the EMR which explicitly states that the patient does not have any known allergies or any known drug allergies. The degree of granularity for specific negation is variable from specific application to application or from use case to use case. For example, many systems record explicitly that the patient is NOT allergic to Latex or IV contrast.   In general, obviously harmful substance administrations such as poisoning or overdoses are not included in allergy/intolerance lists because there should never be such an intent to treat the patient in such a manor. Similarly, seasonal or pet allergies which share many of the same underlying pathophysiology as true allergy are typically not recorded in allergy lists because there is generally not concern that these substances will be administered as therapy planning. This is not absolute, however as some physicians do prefer to track environmental allergies in this section. Food allergies on the other hand, generally are included in this list since diets may be ordered or prescribed and many medications or immunizations may include food substances, however. Most notably many immunizations are grown in eggs.   </p><emph role="strong">Data Capture:  </emph>Allergies/Intolerance lists are typically reviewed at many points of patient care. For example, physicians typically review patient allergies when they first see a patient or perform History and Physicals. Nurses typically have a similar intake assessment where allergies are reviewed as do pharmacists. Typical use patterns typically involve a review rather than capture of new allergies because allergy information is considered to be important by a wide variety of people and so it is frequent that some records are available which provide this information. For example, a nurse may review a list of the patients allergies from transfer records when he/she does their intake assessment, and a physician may review the nurses list with the patient when he/she does their history and physical.   It is also common that allergy lists are reviewed and updated in the course of care when new information is available. For example, it may be noted that the patient has a new suspect allergy when noted to have an adverse reaction after exposure to a medication. Similarly there is often review and correction a result of need to challenge the certainty that the allergy exists. For example an allergy to Penicillin may be noted. This may persist for quite some time before the patient actually needs antibiotics, and further questioning may reveal that the reaction happened many years ago and that patient is unsure about specifically what happened. Cautious trials of therapy or even further verification testing may proceed as a result. Additional clarification details may be appended such as "patient has tolerated cephalosporins in the past" (i.e. cross reactivity has been ruled out) or the allergy may even be marked as erroneous.   Allergies and some intolerances may be supported by evidence such as allergy sensitivity testing or serology tests.   <p><emph role="strong">Data Use:  </emph>Allergy information is useful for a variety of use cases. First, and importantly, it is used in the simple human review of allergy information. Patients may forget or may be unable to indicate allergy information. Indeed, even the same provider may have difficulty remembering a patients allergies as the patient moves through the continuity of care. As a result, allergy information is usually provided from provider to provider on any patient transfer of care, discharge, or referral. This occurs through paper documents, simple storage in an EMR where both clinicians share the same EMR, or exchange between clinical information systems when the clinicians use different systems. Electronic transfer of this information may be either through structured documents, messages, or queries depending on particular use cases and or system capabilities.   Allergy data always includes some representation of the allergen, however also should ideally include the reaction with or without severity. It may include additional details including when the event occurred or supporting details. The data capture is often incomplete, however, and even the allergen may be at a hazy level of granularity. For example, the patient may only remember that they are allergic to a "-cillins" (several different types of antibiotics)   Allergy information needs to be codified and computer processable since many systems use and exchange allergy data for the expressed purpose of drug order to allergy checks, and may require allergy information to be assessed. Many systems also require statements about the status allergy review within a given time period, thus it is important to include even updates even when the assertion is simply to repeat that no allergies are known to exist.   In some cases allergy information is used for reporting to external agencies.   </p><p><emph role="strong">Walk-Through</emph></p><p>This is a walk through of a generic allergy/intolerance model, which can be constrained to record and list a patient's allergy or intolerances to various levels of agent/substance hierarchy, as well as to more generic concepts such as food and the environment.  The model depicts the three major components of the Allergy/Intolerance structure, namely: </p><list role="unordered"><item>Allergy/Intolerance List</item><item>Allergy/Intolerance Summary Observation</item><item>Allergy/Intolerance Concern</item></list><p><graphic source="T-REPC_DM000320UV.jpg" alt="AllergyIntolerance"></graphic></p><p>These component parts of the allergy/intolerance structure will be described in detail here, beginning with the core Act classes. The definitions for class attributes are available in Reference Information Model (RIM) documentation and will not be repeated here.</p><p><emph role="strong">Allergy/Intolerance Core Act Classes </emph></p><p><emph role="strong">AllergyIntoleranceList - REPC_RM000322UV </emph></p><p>This RMIM is used to create a list from allergy/intolerance detail observation (tracked as allergy concerns) and allergy/intolerance summary observations.  Different providers may use this RMIM to create a list of allergies and intolerances for different custodians/owners.</p><p><emph role="strong"><emph>Attributes </emph></emph></p><p>Code (Allergy/Intolerance Type):  This is a mandatory code that lists the allergy/intolerance(s) and is constructed from allergy/intolerance concerns and allergy/intolerance summary. </p><p><emph role="strong"><emph>Participations</emph></emph></p><p>Informant (Provider or Patient or Related Party):  In the case where the information in the record is being captured second-hand, this identifies the source of the information. Understanding the source of data is essential to its interpretation. If not specified, it is assumed that the author is capturing information of which they have first-hand awareness.  </p><p>recordTarget1 (Patient): This identifies the patient associated with the allergy/intolerance record. </p><p>author1 (Provider):  This identifies the provider who is responsible for the decision to capture the Allergy/Intolerance in the patient's EHR. Used to identify responsibility for accuracy and relevance of the information. </p><p>responsibleParty (Provider):  Identity of the provider who is taking responsibility for the actions of the author, usually a supervisor. Allows for the trail of responsibility for the action. </p><p>location: Indicates the service delivery location where the allergy was recorded. Indicates where records are likely kept for follow-up. May also be useful in understanding the context in which the allergy/intolerance was recorded.   </p><p>custodian: Constitutes the owner of the list.  </p><p><emph><emph role="strong">Act Relationships</emph></emph></p><p>component: Has 'component' relationship to the AllergyIntolerancConcern class, indicating that the allergy/intolerance concerns do contribute to the creation of the allergy/intolerance list.Component1: Has 'component' relationship to the AllergyIntolerancSummaryObservation class, indicating that the allergy/intolerance summary observations contribute to the creation of the allergy/intolerance list.</p><p><emph role="strong">AllergyIntoleranceSummaryObservation - REPC_MT000323UV </emph></p><p>This class is employed by a provider to assert that a patient has no known allergy or intolerance whatsoever, or that the patient has no known allergy or intolerance to any generic concept of an agent/substance such as Drug, Food, etc.  </p><p>This recording of 'No Known Indicator' is not a derivation from the absence of allergy/intolerance concern; instead, it is recorded as an explicit assertion based on the provider making the necessary assessment.  It is about the fact that the list contains no concerns of a particular type.</p><p>The only reason for needing this class, is to be able to assert a 'No Known ...' observation without tying it to a 'Concern', i.e. so as not to raise a concern just to be able to say that there is no concern.</p><p><emph role="strong">Attributes</emph></p><p>code (Allergy or Intolerance): This is a mandatory that indicates that the summary assertion is in reference to an allergy or intolerance. </p><p>negationInd (No Known Indicator): This is a mandatory attribute whose value is fixed to 'true', indicating that this class is used to make negative assertions (assertion of non-existence of an allergy/intolerance concern) only. </p><p>value (Type of Allergy or Intolerance Summary): This is a mandatory whose domain indicates the generic class of concepts for which negative assertion is being made. Include the codes for Allergy (negated as: No Known Allergy), Intolerance (negated as: No Known Intolerances), Drug (negated as: No Known Drug Allergy), Food (negated as: No Known Food Allergy), etc</p><p><emph role="strong">Participations</emph></p><p>Participants in this class are: author (Provider), responsibleParty (Supervisor), subject2 (Patient), informant (Provider, or Patient, or Related Party), participant, and location.  For full descriptions of these participants, please refer to the 'Participations' section for the AllergyIntoleranceList class.</p><p><emph role="strong">Act Relationships</emph></p><p>The only actRelationship from this class is to serve as a source for allergy/intolerance problem list as compiled by the AllergyIntoleranceList class.  </p><p><emph role="strong">AllergyIntoleranceConcern - REPC_RM000324UV</emph></p><p>This class is used to track a patient's allergy or intolerance to a specific agent or substance, as observed by various providers at various points in time and locations. The name and nature of the concern is derived from the first allergy/intolerance observation made for the agent/substance, which could be an indication of a negative assertion for an allergy or intolerance to an agent/substance (e.g. Patient is not allergic to penicillin). </p><p><emph role="strong"><emph>Attributes</emph></emph></p><p>Id (Concern Identifier): A mandatory attribute for uniquely identifying the particular allergy/intolerance concern. Allows on-going observations made on the same initial problem to be tracked as the same concern. </p><p>statusCode (Concern Status): Used to summarize the status of the specific allergy/intolerance as indicated by the last observation made on the allergy or intolerance. For full description of the various statuses of a Concern, please refer to the Concern Tracker CMET: REPC_RM000300UV A_ConcernTracking </p><p>effectiveTime (Time concern started and ended): Used to summarize the period of the concern, based on the information contained in the first and last allergy/intolerance observations made.</p><p>confidentialityCode: Used to assign privacy to the particular allergy/intolerance concern.</p><p><emph role="strong"><emph>Participations</emph></emph></p><p>Participants in this class are: author (Provider), responsibleParty (Supervisor), subject2 (Patient), informant (Provider, or Patient, or Related Party), participant, and location.  For full descriptions of these participants, please refer to the 'Participations' section for the AllergyIntoleranceList class. </p><p><emph role="strong"><emph>Act Relationships</emph></emph></p><p>subject: Has 'subject' relationship to the AllergyIntoleranceObservation class, indicating that the allergy concern is the subject of one or more allergy or intolerance observations.</p><p>For full descriptions of the actRelationships, please refer to the 'Act Relationship' section for the generic PC Concern Tracking CMET: REPC_RM000300UV - A_ConcernTracking. The four main actRelationships of interest are employed to achieve the following:  </p><list role="unordered"><item>replacing an existing concern with a new one</item><item>linking a concern to another concern</item><item>making a concern a sub-concern of another concern</item><item>specifying an existing in various sequel relationships to another concern.</item></list><p><emph><emph role="strong"> Other classes </emph></emph></p><p>The following is a brief description of other classes that are defined as part of the AllergyIntoleranceConcern structure: </p><p>ControlActEvent: This class provides the ability to manage/indicate the state transitions of an allergy/intolerance concern, including the ability to indicate 'resolution' (i.e. the allergy or intolerance had been resolved, and was no longer a concern). </p><p><emph role="strong">AllergyIntoleranceDetailObservation </emph></p><p>The AllergyIntoleranceDetailObservation structure comprises a collection of classes including Observation, Substance Administration, and Control Acts. It also includes modeling of materials and numerous Act Relationships. These will be described in detail here, beginning with the core Act classes. The definitions for class attributes are available in Reference Information Model (RIM) documentation and will not be repeated here. </p><p><emph role="strong"><emph>Attributes </emph></emph></p><p>Id (Allergy or Intolerance Identifier): Identifies unique occurrence of an allergy or intolerance observation record.  </p><p>code (Allergy or Intolerance): Indicates that the object of the observation is to record an allergy or an intolerance concern in the patient's EHR.   </p><p>negationInd: Used to assert that a patient is, or is not allergic/intolerant to the agent in question. The negationInd attribute is set to 'false' when recording that a patient has allergy or intolerance to the agent/substance in question; whereas it is set to 'true' when asserting that a patient has no allergy or intolerance to the agent/substance.  </p><p>statusCode: Has fixed status of 'completed', indicating a point in time observation that is not updateable.  </p><p>value (Type of Allergy/Intolerance): This has either a coded value or a null flavor of 'N/A'. If recording as a code/value, the code should have the semantic of 'allergy to xxx'. If recording the allergy to an agent through the 'participant', then the value should have a null flavor.  </p><p>methodCode: Indicates the provider's overall causality assessment and cognitive procedure for asserting that the patient is, or is not allergic or intolerant to the agent in question.  </p><p><emph role="strong"><emph>Participations</emph></emph></p><p>participant: Identifies the exposed agent (medication or a generic administrable material) that is believed to have triggered the allergy or intolerance. This participation must not be specified if the value attribute of the focal class has a valid code with appropriate semantic. On the other hand, this participation must be specified if the value attribute of the focal class has a null flavor of 'N/A'  </p><p>Other participants in this class are: author (Provider), responsibleParty (Supervisor), subject2 (Patient), informant (Provider, or Patient, or Related Party), participant, and location.  For full descriptions of these other participants, please refer to the 'Participations' section for the AllergyIntoleranceList class.  </p><p><emph role="strong"><emph>Act Relationships  </emph></emph></p><p>subject: Indicates a particular type of reaction experienced by the patient which provides evidence for the existence (or non-existence) of the allergy/intolerance. May help ascertain the severity of the condition, and provide direction for management.   </p><p>subjectOf2: Indicates the gravity of the patient's allergy or intolerance to the agent or the gravity of the patient's reaction to the agent.  </p><p>subjectOf1: Indicates the various comments that providers have recorded about this allergy/intolerance.  </p><p>support: Points to result of a previously conducted allergy test that supports or refutes the allergy/intolerance observation. Provides evidence for recording the allergy or intolerance.   </p><p><emph role="strong"><emph>Other Classes </emph></emph></p><p>The following is a brief description of other classes that are defined as part of the AllergyIntoleranceObservation structure:   </p><p>Reaction: This is a recording of a patient reaction that is believed to be associated with the allergy/intolerance. This aids providers in distinguishing between proper allergies and non-allergy intolerances, and allows the provider recording the allergy/intolerance to assign appropriate severity to the allergy/allergy record.   </p><p>SubstanceAdministration: Incidence of the patient's exposure to some substance (medication, food, etc) through administration that might have caused the reaction.  </p><p>SeverityObservation: Indicates the gravity of the allergy, intolerance or reaction in terms of its actual or potential impact on the patient. Allows for sorting of allergy records. May influence whether contraindications must be managed.   </p><p>Annotation: This is a list of comments made about the record by providers. Information captured here includes the provider making the comments; and excludes information that would render the record invalid. Allows various Providers to attach comments to an existing record, and thus improving cross-provider communications.   </p>









AllergyTestEvent: Indicates the specific allergy test that supports the recording of the allergy/intolerance. Provides evidence for recording the allergy/intolerance in the patient's EHR.   </descriptive><storydivn identifier="sbs-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Storyboards" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="sbs-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><descriptive identifier="sstop-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Reference" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="sstop-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><story identifier="REPC_ST006006UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Patient Report Food Allergy" familiarName="Patient Report Food Allergy" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_ST006006UV01-str" sortPrefix="35|PATIENT REPORT FOOD ALLERGY" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-14T09:13:25"><descriptive identifier="purp-REPC_ST006006UV01" name="Purpose" parent="REPC_ST006006UV01-str" id="purp-REPC_ST006006UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2007-07-14T09:13:25"><p>The purpose of this storyboard is to illustrate the recording of a food allergy and the need to harmonize with CDA.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="REPC_SN006006UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Patient Report Food Allergy" familiarName="Patient Report Food Allergy" parent="REPC_ST006006UV01-str" id="REPC_ST006006UV01-REPC_SN006006UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="35|PATIENT REPORT FOOD ALLERGY" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" lastEdit="2007-07-14T09:12:27"><p><emph role="strong">Precondition: </emph>On evaluation in Dr. Cultures office, Mr. Everyman is queried about the rash, and it is found that the rash occurred after eating peanut oil, which Mr. Everyman forgot to report as a known childhood allergy.   </p><p><emph role="strong">Activities: </emph>Dr. Culture updates the allergy list to reflect the food allergy to peanut oil. He references the previously recorded rash as the reaction and records this information in a CDA consult note back to Dr. Primary. Dr. Primary imports the allergy data from the note into his EMR.   </p><p><emph role="strong">Post-condition: </emph>The food allergy is recorded.   </p></descriptive><diagref ref="REPC_ST006006UV01.gif"/></story><story identifier="REPC_ST006000UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Adds Allergy Information" familiarName="Physician Adds Allergy Information" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_ST006000UV01-str" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN ADDS ALLERGY INFORMATION" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-13T20:42:55"><descriptive identifier="purp-REPC_ST006000UV01" name="Purpose" parent="REPC_ST006000UV01-str" id="purp-REPC_ST006000UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2007-07-13T20:42:55"><p>The purpose of this storyboard is to illustrate a physician adding Allergy information to a patient record.  This information is shared with other providers.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="REPC_SN006000UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Adds Allergy Intolerance" familiarName="Physician Adds Allergy Information" parent="REPC_ST006000UV01-str" id="REPC_ST006000UV01-REPC_SN006000UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN ADDS ALLERGY INFORMATION" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" lastEdit="2007-07-13T21:01:50"><emph role="strong">Precondition:</emph> Patient Adam Everyman is seeing Dr. Patricia Primary for evaluation of a cough. In the process of recording Mr. Everyman's history Dr. Primary states a history of no known drug allergies (NKDA). After reviewing Mr. Everyman's history and exam findings, Dr. Primary decides that Mr. Everyman probably has chronic bronchitis and should be referred to the pulmonologist Dr. Bob Breathright for further evaluation.   <p><emph role="strong">Activities:</emph> Dr Primary creates an electronic referral letter which includes the allergy information embedded in the document. He sends this data to Dr. Breathright as part of the electronic referral documents. Alternative flows include Dr. Primary posts documents or the allergy information to a central repository and Dr. Breathright queries the repository. Other flows might have Dr. Breathright query Dr. Primary's EMR directly.</p><p><emph role="strong">PostConditions:</emph> Dr. Breathright accepts the referral and has the relevant allergy information.  </p></descriptive><diagref ref="REPC_ST006000UV01.gif"/></story><story identifier="REPC_ST006004UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Annotates Allergy" familiarName="Physician Annotates Allergy" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_ST006004UV01-str" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN ANNOTATES ALLERGY" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-15T11:38:07"><descriptive identifier="purp-REPC_ST006004UV01" name="Purpose" parent="REPC_ST006004UV01-str" id="purp-REPC_ST006004UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2007-07-15T11:38:07"><p>The purpose of this storyboard is to show the need to annotate allergies with further test results (e.g. with skin testing) as evidence, and to correct prior allergy assumptions, where the allergy is refuted.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="REPC_SN006004UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Annotates Allergy" familiarName="Physician Annotates Allergy" parent="REPC_ST006004UV01-str" id="REPC_ST006004UV01-REPC_SN006004UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN ANNOTATES ALLERGY" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" lastEdit="2007-07-15T11:39:09"><p><emph role="strong">Precondition:</emph> Mr. Everyman is subsequently noted to have Endocarditis with cultures growing Enterococcus. Dr. Ida D. Culture, the Infectious Disease consultant is called onto the case. Dr. Culture suggests that Penicillin skin testing be performed since it is much more effective than alternative agents.</p><p><emph role="strong">Activities:</emph> Skin testing is performed which shows that Mr. Everyman is NOT allergic to penicillin after all. Dr. Culture records the correction to the allergy list. The updated information is shared with the pharmacy system.
</p><p><emph role="strong">Post-condition:</emph> The allergy list reflects no known drug allergies (NKDA) and the penicillin allergy is explicitly negated.</p></descriptive><diagref ref="REPC_ST006004UV01.gif"/></story><story identifier="REPC_ST006003UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Clarifies Allergy Information" familiarName="Physician Clarifies Allergy Information" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_ST006003UV01-str" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN CLARIFIES ALLERGY INFORMATION" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-28T19:30:27"><descriptive identifier="purp-REPC_ST006003UV01" name="Purpose" parent="REPC_ST006003UV01-str" id="purp-REPC_ST006003UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2007-07-28T19:30:27">The purpose of this storyboard is to clarify allergy information and the use of allergy information for drug/allergy checking.  Allergens may cross react, therefore allergy information may require annotations that clarify the nature and scope of the allergy.  Furthermore updates to allergy information is synchronized between multiple hospital systems.  
</descriptive><descriptive identifier="REPC_SN006003UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Clarifies Allergy Information" familiarName="Physician Clarifies Allergy Information" parent="REPC_ST006003UV01-str" id="REPC_ST006003UV01-REPC_SN006003UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN CLARIFIES ALLERGY INFORMATION" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" lastEdit="2007-07-28T19:29:41"><p><emph role="strong">Preconditions: </emph>Mr. Everyman has been admitted to the hospital and has had a single dose of antibiotics in the emergency room. Dr. Primary has written for Levofloxicin as an alternative to the standard formulary choice of Cefuroxime. Cefuroxime is a type of Cephalosporin. Cephalosporins generally have about a 10% cross reactivity with Penicillin.  Culture results later show that the organism in Mr. Everyman's sputum sample are growing Staphalococcus which is resistant to Levofloxicin, but sensitive to Cefuroxime. Dr. Primary asks Mr. Everyman more about the nature of his penicillin allergy. Mr. Everyman admits that he has had other Cephalosporins in the past without any problem.   </p><p><emph role="strong">Activities: </emph>Dr. Primary discontinues the order for Levofloxicin, and adds an order for Cefuroxime. The system generates an alert indicating that there is a known cross reactivity between Cefuroxime and penicillin. Dr. Primary overrides the alert and adds an annotation about the fact that Mr. Everyman has tolerated other cephalosporins in the past without difficulty.  The updated allergy information is transmitted to the pharmacy system.  On reviewing the order, Dr. Drew Drugger, the pharmacist sees the annotation about cephalosporins.    </p><p><emph role="strong">Post condition: </emph>The system places the order, and also updates the pharmacy system. The allergies in both systems are updated to reflect the comment that cephalosporins are OK.</p></descriptive><diagref ref="REPC_ST006003UV01.gif"/></story><story identifier="REPC_ST006007UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Enters Suspect Environmental Allergy" familiarName="Physician Enters Suspect Environmental Allergy" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_ST006007UV01-str" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN ENTERS SUSPECT ENVIRONMENTAL ALLERGY" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-15T09:17:39"><descriptive identifier="purp-REPC_ST006007UV01" name="Purpose" parent="REPC_ST006007UV01-str" id="purp-REPC_ST006007UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2007-07-15T09:17:39"><p>The purpose of this storyboard is to demonstrate the linking of information in assessing a response to an allergy, and highlights the need to record the level of certainty, and reuse allergy information in related parts of a modular EMR such as a separate documentation solution.  This storyboard refers to <artref ref="Introduction" alt="Use Case 2"></artref>.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="REPC_SN006007UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Enters Suspect Environmental Allergy" familiarName="Physician Enters Suspect Environmental Allergy" parent="REPC_ST006007UV01-str" id="REPC_ST006007UV01-REPC_SN006007UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN ENTERS SUSPECT ENVIRONMENTAL ALLERGY" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" lastEdit="2007-07-14T09:23:00"><p><emph role="strong">Precondition:</emph> Dr. Primary is viewing the EMR of Patient Everyman. Mr. Everyman has come to clinic to have a rash evaluated. The allergy list records the peanut oil food allergy but "NKDA" (no known drug allergies) and "NKEA" (no known environmental allergies).   </p><p><emph role="strong">Activities:</emph> Dr. Primary elicits the patient history. The patient has visited an Indian restaurant for the first time and was exposed to many new spices. The patient wonders whether the rash is due to the spices. Dr. Primary examines the rash and notices the typical linear pattern associated with a plant exposure. She questions the patient further and finds the patient had been working in the garden earlier in the week. The patient has never had cedar wood chips. Dr. Primary assures the patient that allergy to Indian spices is unlikely to be the cause of this rash. Rather, Dr. Primary identifies probable cedar wood chips and educates the patient on the disease. She places the problem "rash - probably due to cedar wood chips" on his problem list and gives the patient a prescription for Prednisone. She adds cedar wood chips to the allergy list with a certainty level of "probable" linking the problem as evidence.  Dr. Primary dictates a note of the event.  The transcription system accepts a feed including the allergy data. </p><p><emph role="strong">Post-condition: </emph>Mr. Everyman has progress notes, findings, impressions, care plans, and a populated allergy list in the EMR that are captured in a manner that allows navigation from one related data item to the next. Specifically, the user is able to navigate from the current name of the allergy on the allergy list to the string of observations and treatment activities associated with management of that allergy over time. Additionally, the user is able to navigate from a data item to the allergy management programs supported by the data element.   </p></descriptive><diagref ref="REPC_ST006007UV01.gif"/></story><story identifier="REPC_ST006008UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Notes Severe Intolerance" familiarName="Physician Notes Severe Intolerance" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_ST006008UV01-str" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN NOTES SEVERE INTOLERANCE" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-14T09:24:48"><descriptive identifier="purp-REPC_ST006008UV01" name="Purpose" parent="REPC_ST006008UV01-str" id="purp-REPC_ST006008UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2007-07-14T09:24:48"><p>The purpose of this storyboard is to demonstrate the flow of information in tracking an allergy and highlighting the need to record reaction severity.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="REPC_SN006008UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Notes Severe Intolerance" familiarName="Physician Notes Severe Intolerance" parent="REPC_ST006008UV01-str" id="REPC_ST006008UV01-REPC_SN006008UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN NOTES SEVERE INTOLERANCE" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" lastEdit="2007-07-14T09:27:14"><p><emph role="strong">Precondition:</emph> Mr. Everyman is bitten by a bee in his back yard. A few hours later he notices that his face and lips are swollen. He feels generally unwell so proceeds to the Emergency room. In the emergency room he develops low blood pressure and shortness of breath. Dr. Eric Rescue, the emergency room physician diagnoses anaphylaxis due to a bee sting, and begins appropriate treatment.   </p><p><emph role="strong">Activities: </emph>Dr. Rescue records the problem "Anaphylaxis secondary to Bee sting" in the Problem List and "Bee's" in the allergy list, with a reaction of "anaphylaxis", and a severity of "severe"   </p><p><emph role="strong">Post-Conditions: </emph>Dr. Primary follows up with the patient to track problem of Bee allergy tracked on his problem list and prescribes an epinephrine pen, and also keeps the bee allergy on the allergy list.</p></descriptive><diagref ref="REPC_ST006008UV01.gif"/></story><story identifier="REPC_ST006002UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Reviews Verifies Allergy Information" familiarName="Physician Reviews Verifies Allergy Information" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_ST006002UV01-str" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN REVIEWS VERIFIES ALLERGY INFORMATION" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-13T21:16:32"><descriptive identifier="purp-REPC_ST006002UV01" name="Purpose" parent="REPC_ST006002UV01-str" id="purp-REPC_ST006002UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2007-07-13T21:16:32"><p>The purpose of this storyboard is to illustrate the communication flow in reviewing and confirming allergy information, ensuring the hospital information system and pharmacy system has correct and updated information that is synchronized.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="REPC_SN006002UV01" name="Allergyintolerance  Physician Reviews Verifies Allergy Information" familiarName="Physician Reviews Verifies Allergy Information" parent="REPC_ST006002UV01-str" id="REPC_ST006002UV01-REPC_SN006002UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN REVIEWS VERIFIES ALLERGY INFORMATION" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" lastEdit="2007-07-13T21:28:14"><p><emph role="strong">Precondition: </emph>Mr. Everyman calls Dr. Primary with complaint that he has a fever and is coughing copious amounts of sputum, mostly green in color but sometimes including streaks of blood. Dr. Primary advises Mr. Everyman to go to the Emergency Room for evaluation.</p><p><emph role="strong">Activities:</emph> Dr. Primary prepares an emergency department referral which includes allergy information as it's recorded in his EMR. In the emergency room, Nurse Carrie Careful reviews allergies with Mr. Everyman. Mr. Everyman is coughing severely and finds it hard to speak without coughing. The history goes a little faster because she has seen the referral note from Dr. Primary that includes the penicillin allergy. She quickly confirms this with Mr. Everyman with the statement "I see from your records that you have an allergy to penicillin, is that correct?" Mr. Everyman nods, yes. She asks about other allergies to which Mr. Everyman nods, no. She notes the Penicillin Allergy in her nurse assessment. The system prompts explicitly for Latex and IV contrast. She reviews these with Mr. Everyman, who again nods no. She records "no latex allergy" "no IV contrast allergy". Dr. Eric Rescue, the physician on call in the emergency department, also reads Nurse Careful's assessment and confirms this with Mr. Everyman. Dr. Rescue decides Mr. Everyman has pneumonia and needs to be admitted. Dr. Rescue verifies the penicillin allergy in his note and prescribes Levaquin.  Orders and Allergy information are sent to the hospital pharmacy system. 
</p><p><emph role="strong">Post Condition:</emph> Drugs that might cause adverse reactions are avoided by the system alerts. The hospital information system has a correct and updated allergy list and this is shared with the pharmacy system. Verification that the patient does not have IV and latex allergies is recorded.</p></descriptive><diagref ref="REPC_ST006002UV01.gif"/></story><story identifier="REPC_ST006001UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Updates Allergy Information" familiarName="Physician Updates Allergy Information" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_ST006001UV01-str" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN UPDATES ALLERGY INFORMATION" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-13T21:04:29"><descriptive identifier="purp-REPC_ST006001UV01" name="Purpose" parent="REPC_ST006001UV01-str" id="purp-REPC_ST006001UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2007-07-13T21:04:29"><p>The purpose of this storyboard is to illustrate a specialist updating allergy information and notifying Dr. Primary so appropriate updating of his system can occur.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="REPC_SN006001UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Physician Updates Allergy Information" familiarName="Physician Updates Allergy Information" parent="REPC_ST006001UV01-str" id="REPC_ST006001UV01-REPC_SN006001UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="35|PHYSICIAN UPDATES ALLERGY INFORMATION" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" lastEdit="2007-07-13T21:10:22"><p><emph role="strong">Precondition:</emph> Dr. Breathright, a pulmonologist is seeing Mr. Everyman in his office after a referral from Dr. Primary. Dr. Breathright reviews the allergy information with Mr. Everyman noting the prior assessment of no known drug allergies (NKDA) from Dr. Primary. On review, Mr. Everyman recalls that he failed to mention an allergy to Penicillin. Mr. Everyman cannot recall what reaction happened, only that his mom told him as a child not to take it.  </p><p><emph role="strong">Activities: </emph>Dr. Breathright records the updated allergy to penicillin in his EMR. He includes this information in his consult note back to Dr. Primary. Alternative flows include Dr. Primary receiving message of the updated allergy information via message sent either directly, or forwarded from the central repository.  </p><p><emph role="strong">Post condition:</emph> Dr. Primary receives notification of the updated allergy information, and can update his system appropriately.   </p></descriptive><diagref ref="REPC_ST006001UV01.gif"/></story></storydivn><approledivn identifier="roles-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Application Roles" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="roles-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><descriptive identifier="arop-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Reference" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="arop-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gapprole" alt="the discussion of application roles"/> and their relationships in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><artree><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="REPC_AR000009UV01-ar" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Informer" refFamiliarName="Allergy/Intolerance Entry System" refIdentifier="REPC_AR000009UV01"/></artreeitem><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="REPC_AR000010UV01-ar" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Allergy Intolerance Information Solicitor" refFamiliarName="Allergy/Intolerance Querying System" refIdentifier="REPC_AR000010UV01"/></artreeitem><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="REPC_AR000008UV01-ar" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Allergy Intolerance Manager" refFamiliarName="Allergy/Intolerance Repository" refIdentifier="REPC_AR000008UV01"/></artreeitem></artree><approle identifier="REPC_AR000009UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Informer" familiarName="Allergy/Intolerance Entry System" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_AR000009UV01-ar" sortPrefix="35|99|99|25|" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:16:20"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_AR000009UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_AR000009UV01-ar" id="desc-REPC_AR000009UV01-ar" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:16:20"><p>This is a system through which information about patient allergies and intolerances is recorded and maintained</p></descriptive></approle><approle identifier="REPC_AR000010UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Allergy Intolerance Information Solicitor" familiarName="Allergy/Intolerance Querying System" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_AR000010UV01-ar" sortPrefix="35|99|99|99|ALLERGY INTOLERANCE INFORMATION SOLICITOR" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2006-11-09T15:27:31"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_AR000010UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_AR000010UV01-ar" id="desc-REPC_AR000010UV01-ar" lastEdit="2006-11-09T15:27:31"><p>This is a system which is capable of retrieving information about patient allergies and intolerances</p></descriptive></approle><approle identifier="REPC_AR000008UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Allergy Intolerance Manager" familiarName="Allergy/Intolerance Repository" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_AR000008UV01-ar" sortPrefix="35|99|99|99|ALLERGY INTOLERANCE MANAGER" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:15:52"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_AR000008UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_AR000008UV01-ar" id="desc-REPC_AR000008UV01-ar" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:15:52"><p>This is a system that stores and exposes information about patient allergies and intolerances</p></descriptive></approle></approledivn><triggerdivn identifier="tes-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Trigger Events" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="tes-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><descriptive identifier="teop-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Reference" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="teop-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gtrigger" alt="the discussion of trigger events"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><trigger identifier="REPC_TE000023UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Request List Updated" familiarName="Allergy/ intolerance request list updated" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_TE000023UV01-te" role="User-request" sortPrefix="35|10|99||99|LIST UPDATED" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-29T12:12:34"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_TE000023UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_TE000023UV01-te" id="desc-REPC_TE000023UV01-te" lastEdit="2007-07-29T12:12:34"><p>A new or updated allergy list is recorded, and request is made to update another system.  This notification requires confirmation of the update by the receiving system.  The entire list is sent.</p></descriptive></trigger><trigger identifier="REPC_TE000003UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Event Activate Rejection" familiarName="Decision to not record allergy or intolerance" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_TE000003UV01-te" role="User-request" sortPrefix="35|20|16||20|" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-10-30T13:10:09"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_TE000003UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_TE000003UV01-te" id="desc-REPC_TE000003UV01-te" lastEdit="2006-10-30T13:10:09"><p>A request to record an allergy or intolerance in a patient's record has been refused.  (E.g. contraindication, patient not found, etc.)</p></descriptive><intref role="fires" ref="REPC_IN000014UV01-int" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Event Activate Rejection" refFamiliarName="Add allergy/intolerance request refused" refIdentifier="REPC_IN000014UV01"/></trigger><trigger identifier="REPC_TE000025UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Event Revise Rejection" familiarName="Decision to not record allergy/ intol. change" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_TE000025UV01-te" role="User-request" sortPrefix="35|20|22||20|" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:29:16"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_TE000025UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_TE000025UV01-te" id="desc-REPC_TE000025UV01-te" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:29:16"><p>A request to modify a previously-recorded allergy or intolerance has been refused (e.g. no permission, patient not found).</p></descriptive><intref role="fires" ref="REPC_IN000022UV01-int" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Event Revise Rejection" refFamiliarName="Update allergy/intolerance request refused" refIdentifier="REPC_IN000022UV01"/></trigger><trigger identifier="REPC_TE000006UV01" name="Allergyintolerance List Query" familiarName="Allergy and intolerances list query" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_TE000006UV01-te" role="User-request" sortPrefix="35|99|99|LIST|05|" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-29T12:09:47"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_TE000006UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_TE000006UV01-te" id="desc-REPC_TE000006UV01-te" lastEdit="2007-07-29T12:09:47"><p>Allergy/Intolerance information is requested.</p></descriptive></trigger><trigger identifier="REPC_TE000002UV01" name="Allergyintolerance List Response" familiarName="Allergy or intolerance list response" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_TE000002UV01-te" role="State-based" sortPrefix="35|99|99||99|LIST RESPONSE" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-29T12:08:50"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_TE000002UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_TE000002UV01-te" id="desc-REPC_TE000002UV01-te" lastEdit="2007-07-29T12:08:50"><p>Allergy or intolerance data is returned.</p></descriptive><intref role="fires" ref="REPC_IN000013UV01-int" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Event Activate Confirmation" refFamiliarName="Add allergy/intolerance request accepted" refIdentifier="REPC_IN000013UV01"/></trigger><trigger identifier="REPC_TE000024UV01" name="Allergyintolerance List Updated" familiarName="Allergy or intolerance list updated" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_TE000024UV01-te" role="State-based" sortPrefix="35|99|99||99|LIST UPDATED" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-29T12:13:32"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_TE000024UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_TE000024UV01-te" id="desc-REPC_TE000024UV01-te" lastEdit="2007-07-29T12:13:32"><p>A new allergy list has been created, or an old allergy list has been updated.  This is an unsolicited notification.  The entire list and history is included.</p></descriptive><intref role="fires" ref="REPC_IN000021UV01-int" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Event Revise Confirmation" refFamiliarName="Update allergy/intolerance request accepted" refIdentifier="REPC_IN000021UV01"/></trigger></triggerdivn><rmimdivn identifier="rmims-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="rmims-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><descriptive identifier="rmop-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Reference" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="rmop-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><rmim identifier="REPC_RM000324UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Concern" familiarName="Allergy/Intolerance Concern" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_RM000324UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="35|99|99|CONCERN" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-20T11:57:57"><diagref ref="REPC_RM000324UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="REPC_HD000324UV01-hmd" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Concern" refFamiliarName="Allergyintolerance Concern" refIdentifier="REPC_HD000324UV01"/></rmim><rmim identifier="REPC_RM000322UV01" name="Allergyintolerance List" familiarName="Allergy/Intolerance List" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_RM000322UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="35|99|99|LIST" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-20T12:03:13"><diagref ref="REPC_RM000322UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="REPC_HD000322UV01-hmd" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance List" refFamiliarName="Allergyintolerance List" refIdentifier="REPC_HD000322UV01"/></rmim><rmim identifier="REPC_RM000323UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Summary Observation" familiarName="Allergy/Intolerance Summary Observation" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_RM000323UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="35|99|99|SUMMARY OBSERVATION" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-20T11:59:56"><diagref ref="REPC_RM000323UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="REPC_HD000323UV01-hmd" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Summary Observation" refFamiliarName="Allergy/Intolerance Summary Observation" refIdentifier="REPC_HD000323UV01"/></rmim></rmimdivn><hmddivn identifier="hmds-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="hmds-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><descriptive identifier="hdop-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Reference" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="hdop-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><hmd identifier="REPC_HD000324UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Concern" familiarName="Allergyintolerance Concern" parent="REPC_RM000324UV01-rmi" id="REPC_HD000324UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="35|99|99|CONCERN" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-20T11:58:45"><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="REPC_HD000324UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="REPC_RM000324UV01-rmi" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Concern" refFamiliarName="Allergy/Intolerance Concern" refIdentifier="REPC_RM000324UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="REPC_MT000324UV01-msg" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Concern" refFamiliarName="Allergyintolerance Concern" refIdentifier="REPC_MT000324UV01"/></hmd><hmd identifier="REPC_HD000322UV01" name="Allergyintolerance List" familiarName="Allergyintolerance List" parent="REPC_RM000322UV01-rmi" id="REPC_HD000322UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="35|99|99|LIST" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-20T12:03:37"><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="REPC_HD000322UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="REPC_RM000322UV01-rmi" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance List" refFamiliarName="Allergy/Intolerance List" refIdentifier="REPC_RM000322UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="REPC_MT000322UV01-msg" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance List" refFamiliarName="Allergyintolerance List" refIdentifier="REPC_MT000322UV01"/></hmd><hmd identifier="REPC_HD000323UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Summary Observation" familiarName="Allergy/Intolerance Summary Observation" parent="REPC_RM000323UV01-rmi" id="REPC_HD000323UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="35|99|99|SUMMARY OBSERVATION" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-20T12:00:38"><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="REPC_HD000323UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="REPC_RM000323UV01-rmi" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Summary Observation" refFamiliarName="Allergy/Intolerance Summary Observation" refIdentifier="REPC_RM000323UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="REPC_MT000323UV01-msg" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Summary Observation" refFamiliarName="Allergy/Intolerance Summary Observation" refIdentifier="REPC_MT000323UV01"/></hmd></hmddivn><msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="msgs-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><msgtype identifier="REPC_MT000324UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Concern" familiarName="Allergyintolerance Concern" parent="REPC_HD000324UV01-hmd" id="REPC_MT000324UV01-msg" sortPrefix="35|99|99|CONCERN" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-20T11:59:03"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="REPC_MT000324UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="REPC_HD000324UV01-hmd" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Concern" refFamiliarName="Allergyintolerance Concern" refIdentifier="REPC_HD000324UV01"/></msgtype><msgtype identifier="REPC_MT000322UV01" name="Allergyintolerance List" familiarName="Allergyintolerance List" parent="REPC_HD000322UV01-hmd" id="REPC_MT000322UV01-msg" sortPrefix="35|99|99|LIST" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-20T12:03:45"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="REPC_MT000322UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="REPC_HD000322UV01-hmd" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance List" refFamiliarName="Allergyintolerance List" refIdentifier="REPC_HD000322UV01"/></msgtype><msgtype identifier="REPC_MT000323UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Summary Observation" familiarName="Allergy/Intolerance Summary Observation" parent="REPC_HD000323UV01-hmd" id="REPC_MT000323UV01-msg" sortPrefix="35|99|99|SUMMARY OBSERVATION" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2007-07-20T12:01:05"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="REPC_MT000323UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="REPC_HD000323UV01-hmd" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Summary Observation" refFamiliarName="Allergy/Intolerance Summary Observation" refIdentifier="REPC_HD000323UV01"/></msgtype></msgtypedivn><interactiondivn identifier="ints-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Interactions" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="ints-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><descriptive identifier="inop-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance" name="Reference" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="inop-REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gintact" alt="the definition of Interactions"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><interaction identifier="REPC_IN000013UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Event Activate Confirmation" familiarName="Add allergy/intolerance request accepted" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_IN000013UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="35|20|16|15|" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:25:14"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_IN000013UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_IN000013UV01-int" id="desc-REPC_IN000013UV01-int" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:25:14"><p>Indicates that the requested allergy or intolerance record has been successfully added to the patient's record.</p></descriptive><teref role="trigger" ref="REPC_TE000002UV01-te" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance List Response" refFamiliarName="Allergy or intolerance list response" refIdentifier="REPC_TE000002UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000300UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Application Level Acknowledgement" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000300UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="COMT_MT001103UV-msg" sectID="imcomt" sectType="SB" refName="Act generic Status - Event" refIdentifier="COMT_MT001103UV"/></interaction><interaction identifier="REPC_IN000014UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Event Activate Rejection" familiarName="Add allergy/intolerance request refused" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_IN000014UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="35|20|16|20|" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:25:32"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_IN000014UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_IN000014UV01-int" id="desc-REPC_IN000014UV01-int" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:25:32"><p>Indicates that the request to add the specified allergy or intolerance to the patient record has been denied.</p></descriptive><teref role="trigger" ref="REPC_TE000003UV01-te" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Event Activate Rejection" refFamiliarName="Decision to not record allergy or intolerance" refIdentifier="REPC_TE000003UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000300UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Application Level Acknowledgement" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000300UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/></interaction><interaction identifier="REPC_IN000021UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Event Revise Confirmation" familiarName="Update allergy/intolerance request accepted" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_IN000021UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="35|20|22|15|" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:31:30"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_IN000021UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_IN000021UV01-int" id="desc-REPC_IN000021UV01-int" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:31:30"><p>Indicates that the status, severity and/or other information about the requested allergy or intolerance record has been updated.</p></descriptive><teref role="trigger" ref="REPC_TE000024UV01-te" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance List Updated" refFamiliarName="Allergy or intolerance list updated" refIdentifier="REPC_TE000024UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000300UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Application Level Acknowledgement" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000300UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="COMT_MT001103UV-msg" sectID="imcomt" sectType="SB" refName="Act generic Status - Event" refIdentifier="COMT_MT001103UV"/></interaction><interaction identifier="REPC_IN000022UV01" name="Allergyintolerance Event Revise Rejection" familiarName="Update allergy/intolerance request refused" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-Allergyintolerance-ic" id="REPC_IN000022UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="35|20|22|20|" baseClass="Allergyintolerance" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:31:47"><descriptive identifier="desc-REPC_IN000022UV01" name="Description" parent="REPC_IN000022UV01-int" id="desc-REPC_IN000022UV01-int" lastEdit="2006-03-12T22:31:47"><p>Indicates that the requested modification to the defined allergy or intolerance record has been denied.</p></descriptive><teref role="trigger" ref="REPC_TE000025UV01-te" sectID="hmrepc" sectType="SB" refName="Allergyintolerance Event Revise Rejection" refFamiliarName="Decision to not record allergy/ intol. change" refIdentifier="REPC_TE000025UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000300UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Application Level Acknowledgement" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000300UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="COMT_MT001103UV-msg" sectID="imcomt" sectType="SB" refName="Act generic Status - Event" refIdentifier="COMT_MT001103UV"/></interaction></interactiondivn></subdivn><indexdivn identifier="cindx-REPC_DO000000UV" name="Common Message Elements Indexes" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-ic" id="cindx-REPC_DO000000UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-1" name="Common Message Elements Defined in this Domain" parent="cindx-REPC_DO000000UV-ic" id="REPC_DO000000UV-icc1id"/><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-2" name="Common Message Elements Used by this Domain" parent="cindx-REPC_DO000000UV-ic" id="REPC_DO000000UV-icc2id"/></indexdivn><indexdivn identifier="indx-REPC_DO000000UV" name="Interaction Indexes" parent="REPC_DO000000UV-ic" id="indx-REPC_DO000000UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="indx-List-1" name="Interaction Index by Application Role" parent="indx-REPC_DO000000UV-ic" id="REPC_DO000000UV-ic1id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-2" name="Interaction Index by Trigger Event" parent="indx-REPC_DO000000UV-ic" id="REPC_DO000000UV-ic2id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-3" name="Interaction Index by Message Type" parent="indx-REPC_DO000000UV-ic" id="REPC_DO000000UV-ic3id"/></indexdivn></body></spec>

