<!-- $Id: mIntCategory.cls,v 1.4 2007/11/18 02:48:41 wbeeler Exp $ -->
<!--<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "DTDVersion-4" "../../support/dtd/v3mDomain.dtd">-->
<spec id="PORT_DO000001UV-ic" sectionCode="HMPORT" lastEdit="2011-06-15T15:51:51" rendered="2011-06-22T11:42:41"><header><title>Domain: Regulated Studies</title><version>V 00-00</version><ballot type="NormativeStandard" number="1"/><date>6/22/2011</date><authlist><author><role>Primary Contributor - CTR&amp;R</role><name>Scott Getzin</name><affiliation>Lilly, Inc.</affiliation></author><author><role>Publishing Facilitator</role><name>Becky Angeles</name><affiliation>Scenpro, Inc.</affiliation></author><author><role>CTLabR2 Primary Contributor</role><name>Clinical Genomics SIG</name><affiliation>HL7</affiliation></author><author><role>RCRIM Co-Chair</role><name>Dave Iberson-Hurst</name><affiliation>CDISC</affiliation></author><author><role>Primary Contributor</role><name key="Brown, Barry">Barry Brown</name><affiliation>Mortara Instruments</affiliation></author><author><role>Primary Contributor</role><name key="CDISC">CDISC Laboratory Standards Team</name><affiliation>Clinical Data Standards Interchange Consortium (CDISC)</affiliation></author><author><role>Publishing Facilitator</role><name key="Evans, Julie">Julie Evans</name><affiliation>Clinical Data Standards Interchange Consortium (CDISC)</affiliation></author><author><role>Primary Contributor</role><name key="Gregory, Norman">Norman Gregory</name><affiliation>US Food and Drug Administration</affiliation></author><author><role>RCRIM Co-Chair</role><name key="Helton, Edward">Edward Helton</name><affiliation>National Cancel Institute</affiliation></author><author><role>RCRIM Co-Chair</role><name key="Levin, Randy">Randy Levin</name><affiliation>US Food and Drug Administration</affiliation></author><author><role>CTLabR3 Primary Contributor</role><name key="Neat, Jennifer">Jennifer L. Neat</name><affiliation>City of Hope</affiliation></author><author><role>Primary Contributor</role><name key="Pochon, Phil">Phil Pochon</name><affiliation>Covance</affiliation></author><author><role>RCRIM Co-Chair/Facilitator</role><name key="Quade, Linda">Linda Quade</name><affiliation>Eli Lilly and Company</affiliation></author><author><role>Primary Contributor - Study Participation and Study Design</role><name key="Rock, Jason">Jason Rock</name><affiliation>GlobalSubmit</affiliation><email xlink-form="simple" href="jason.rock@globalsubmit.com" show="embed" actuate="auto">jason.rock@globalsubmit.com</email></author><author><role>Primary Contributor</role><name key="Schadow, Gunther">Gunther Schadow, M.D., PhD.</name><affiliation>Regenstrief Institute for Health Care</affiliation></author><author><role>CTLabR3 Facilitator</role><name key="Shakir, Abdul-Malik">Abdul-Malik Shakir</name><affiliation>Shakir Consulting</affiliation></author><author><role>RCRIM Co-Chair</role><name key="Tardiff, Barbara">Barbara Tardiff</name><affiliation>Clinical Data Standards Interchange Consortium (CDISC)</affiliation></author><author><role>RCRIM Co-Chair</role><name key="Tripp, Ed">Ed Tripp</name><affiliation>Independent</affiliation></author><author><role>Facilitator</role><name key="Walker, Mead">Mead Walker</name><affiliation>Mead Walker Consulting</affiliation></author></authlist><legalese copyRightDate="2011" copyRightOwner="Health Level Seven, Inc." copyRightNotation="All rights reserved." renderer="RoseTree 4.2.54" renderNotation="This document was rendered into XML using software provided to HL7 by Beeler Consulting LLC." contactEmail="HQ@HL7.org" contactName="HL7 Headquarters Staff" contactNote="Comments or questions about this document may be may be addressed to:"/></header><front><div1 id="spec-preface"><head>Notes to Readers</head><p>In Normative Edition 2011, the Regulated Studies domain contains two standards, two draft standards for trial use and the approved informative documents.  The domain is organized under three "topics" as outlined below.</p><p>Annotated ECG topic</p><list role="unordered"><item>Annotated ECG, Release 1 - ANSI approved standard</item><item>Annotated ECG, Release 1 Implementation Guide - HL7 approved informative document</item></list><p>Clinical Research Filtered Query topic</p><list role="unordered"><item>Clinical Research Filtered Query Service Functional Model, Release 1 - Draft Standard for Trial Use</item></list><p>Drug Stability Reporting topic</p><list role="unordered"><item>Drug Stability Reporting, Release 2 - HL7 approved standard</item><item>Drug Stability Reporting Implementation Guide - HL7 approved informative document</item></list><p>Clinical Trials Registration and Results topic</p><list role="unordered"><item>Clinical Trials Registration and Results, Release 1 - Draft Standard for Trial Use</item></list><p>Clinical Trials Registration and Results Domain Analysis Model topic</p><list role="unordered"><item>Clinical Trials Registration and Results Domain Analysis Model, Release 1 - HL7 approved informative document</item></list></div1><div1 id="navigate-divs"><head>Message Design Element Navigation</head><artree role="NAVIGATE"><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="PORT_RM020001UV01-rmi" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="AnnotatedECG - Clinical Trials" refIdentifier="PORT_RM020001UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="PORT_HD020001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="AnnotatedECG  - Clinical Trials" refIdentifier="PORT_HD020001UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="PORT_MT020001UV01-msg" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="AnnotatedECG. base  - Clinical Trials" refIdentifier="PORT_MT020001UV01"/></artreeitem><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="PORT_MT020002UV01-msg" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="AnnotatedECG, deletion - Clinical Trials" refIdentifier="PORT_MT020002UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="PORT_RM090002UV01-rmi" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Stability Study RMIM" refIdentifier="PORT_RM090002UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="PORT_HD090002UV01-hmd" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Stability Study HMD" refIdentifier="PORT_HD090002UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="PORT_MT090002UV01-msg" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Stability Study Message Type" refIdentifier="PORT_MT090002UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem><artreeitem><rmimref role="rmim" ref="PORT_RM140001UV01-rmi" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinical Trial Registration RMIM" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORT_RM140001UV01"/><artreeitem><hmdref role="hmd" ref="PORT_HD140001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry HMD" refIdentifier="PORT_HD140001UV01"/><artreeitem><msgref role="msg" ref="PORT_MT140001UV01-msg" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Message Type" refIdentifier="PORT_MT140001UV01"/></artreeitem></artreeitem></artreeitem></artree></div1></front><body><div1 id="intro-PORT_DO000001UV-ic" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><head>Overview</head><div2 id="spec-scope" lastEdit="2008-06-05T16:44:22"><head>Introduction &amp; Scope</head><p>This domain includes standards developed as part of the family of messages targeted for the exchange of information about the conduct of regulated studies, and  the exchange of the data collected during those studies.  This family includes, but is not limited to, standards for submission of clinical trial and product stability information and data to a regulatory agency.</p><p>The principal contributor to this domain is the Regulated Clinical Research Information Management (RCRIM) technical committee.</p><p>This committee supports the HL7 mission to create and promote its standards by developing standards to improve or enhance information management during research and regulatory evaluation of the safety and efficacy of therapeutic products or procedures worldwide.  The committee defines messages, document structures, and terminology to support the systems and processes used in the collection, storage, distribution, integration and analysis of such information.  The work of this committee will facilitate the availability of safe and effective therapies by improving the processes and efficiencies associated with regulated clinical research.</p><p><emph role="strong">SCOPE</emph></p><p>The Regulated Studies domain currently contains specifications addressing Product Stability Reporting (to a national regulatory agency), Annotation of ECGs (for submission to a drug regulatory agency); and the Periodic Reporting of Clinical Trial Laboratory Results (to a study sponsor or sponsor's agent).</p><p><emph role="strong">Summary of Clinical Trial Interactions in the Regulated Studies Domain</emph></p><p>An Interaction is the formatted package of data to be exchanged between a named sender and a named receiver in response to a named trigger event.</p><p><diagref ref="T-PORT_NA010010.gif"></diagref></p><p>The diagram above  provides a context for understanding all clinical trial interactions in Regulated Studies.  Each storyboard will be accompanied with a similar diagram showing only the interactions described in that storyboard.</p><p>The large gray boxes represent potential application systems that might be involved in the exchange of Regulated Studies information.  There is no expectation that these application systems must reside at different physical locations.  Nor need they be under the control of different parties.  All application systems could, for example, be present at and managed by the sponsor.  Alternatively, they could be distributed among several parties and locations.</p><p>The smaller boxes within represent system functionality that should be present in the application system to handle the exchange.  These application system functionalities are called <emph>Application Roles</emph>.</p><p>The horizontal arrows represent the actual interchange of information between application roles, using the messages in this domain.</p><p>This interaction diagram shows the four clinical trial interactions currently included in this domain.</p><p>Also shown are four potential future interactions  -- a request for ECG analysis from the study site; a request for ECG analysis from the Sponsor/Agent; a request for laboratory analysis from the study site; and a report of laboratory results from the laboratory to the study site.</p></div2></div1><dmimdivn identifier="dmims-PORT_DO000001UV" name="Domain Message Information Models" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="dmims-PORT_DO000001UV-ic"/><subdivn identifier="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="AnnotatedECG Topic" familiarName="AnnotatedECG" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="10" baseClass="AnnotatedECG" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><descriptive identifier="intro-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Introduction" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="intro-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" lastEdit="2005-07-22T12:46:02"><p>Annotated ECG (aECG), Release 1 is an HL7 and ANSI approved standard..</p><p>The Implementation Guide for aECG, Release 1 has also been approved as an HL7 Informative Document.  You can download the implementation guide from the Annex at the end of this topic.</p><p>The aECG standard is presented here for reference and implementation.</p><p><emph role="strong"> aECG Background</emph></p><p>Clinical trials on candidate drug products often collect biological data from trial subjects as waveforms or algorithmic representations of those waveforms. After the data have been collected, derived measurements such as QT interval are used to draw conclusions about the safety and effectiveness of the candidate drug. Standards exist for transmitting these derived data and their analysis results from the trial sponsor to the regulatory agencies; but these submissions have not historically included representation of the waveforms, or have at best included an image of the device-generated paper waveform. A new request to include the digital waveform, the algorithmic representations, and the annotations identifying the relevant landmarks (e.g. QRS-wave onset, T-wave offset) that support derived ECG measurements has been proposed by the US FDA.  This specification will be used to package such annotated digital waveform data produced by an ECG analysis system for transmission from trial sponsor to a regulatory agency.  A medical device that acquires waveforms directly from patients for presentation to caregivers in support of patient care (e.g., ECG monitors, 12 lead ECG carts, ambulatory ECG recorders, pulse oximeters, etc.) may, but is not required to, comply with this specification.</p><p><emph>Limitations on the Annotated ECG Standard</emph></p><p>Application of this Annotated ECG message is limited to human subjects only.  At this time, no provisions have been made to capture information about animals such as breed and species.</p><p>There is no capability to break down the trial into phases, parts, arms, etc. in this message.  Therefore, treatment assignments and study events all apply to the trial as a whole.</p><p>This message is intended to interchange annotated ECG waveforms recorded only from the person designated as the trial subject.</p><p>Future extensions may include the ability to reference non-human subjects, to specify subparts of trials, and to collect waveforms from individuals of interest other than trial subjects.</p></descriptive><storydivn identifier="sbs-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Storyboards" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="sbs-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic"><descriptive identifier="sstop-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="sstop-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="sstoScp-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Introduction" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="sstoScp-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic"><p>The Storyboard is presented as a high-level description of the business situation the standard is designed to address, accompanied by a diagram of the interactions that will be described in the narratives that follow.  Interactions were discussed in the <artref ref="PORT_DO000001" alt="Introduction and Scope"></artref> section of the Regulated Studies domain chapter, under the heading<emph> "Summary of Clinical Trial Interactions in the Regulated Studies Domain"</emph>.  There you will find a diagram of the AnnotatedECG and Clinical Trial laboratory interactions in context.</p><p>A number of narrative sections follow each high-level description, each describing a scenario in which one of the interactions might be used.  These narratives are for illustrative purposes only.  They are not meant to limit the applicability of the standard, nor to proscribe minimum requirements for using the standard.  In particular, <emph role="strong">there is no intent to establish regulatory agency policy on management of data or processes through these scenarios</emph>.  Such policy will be separately published by the regulatory agencies (eg. as Implementation Guides or Guidances).</p></descriptive><story identifier="PORT_ST020001UV01" name="AnnotatedECG_01" familiarName="Managing AnnotatedECGs from Clinical Trials" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="PORT_ST020001UV01-str" sortPrefix="10|_01" baseClass="Annotatedecg" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:08:10"><descriptive identifier="purp-PORT_ST020001UV01" name="Purpose" parent="PORT_ST020001UV01-str" id="purp-PORT_ST020001UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:08:10"><p>The purpose of this storyboard is to illustrate a typical  process of collecting, analyzing, and annotating ECGs taken during a clinical trial, and submitting the annotated ECG waveforms to a regulatory agency.</p><p>The following diagram illustrates the overall workflow for this storyboard.</p><p><graphic source="PORT_NA020010.gif" alt="PORT_NA020010.gif"></graphic></p><p>The Storyboard Narratives that follow illustrate the interactions pictured below.  It is important to understand that the interaction "AnnotatedECGRevised, Notification" includes creation of new AnnotatedECGs (revised from non-existence into existence).</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="PORT_SN020001UV01" name="AnnotatedECG_02" familiarName="Preparing Annotated ECGs" parent="PORT_ST020001UV01-str" id="PORT_ST020001UV01-PORT_SN020001UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|_01" baseClass="Annotatedecg" lastEdit="2008-06-05T16:49:47"><p>Interactions: AnnotatedECG Revised, Notification (<artref ref="PORT_IN020001UV01" alt="PORT_IN020001"></artref>) AnnotatedECG Deleted, Notification (<artref ref="PORT_IN020002UV01" alt="PORT_IN020002"></artref>)</p><p>The story starts when the Sponsor decides to study the effects of a new drug on a population's cardiac electrophysiology.  The sponsor decides the effects to be studied can be seen in ECG data, or information derived from ECG data.  The sponsor designs a protocol specifying the population to be studied, the data to be collected, the equipment to be used for gathering the ECG data, the analysis tools to use, and how any effects will be studied using the ECG data and analysis tools.</p><p>The sponsor (or a Contract Research Organization (CRO) engaged by the sponsor) hires investigators to collect the data, and the investigators in turn enroll subjects in the trial.  The subject visits the collection site.  During the subject's visit, equipment is connected to the subject.  The equipment records the subject's ECG along with other physiologic parameters, if appropriate.  Trial and subject identifying information is associated with the ECG data, such as subject id, gender, date of birth, investigator and site id's, protocol id, etc.  After the individual ECGs are collected from the subject for that visit, it is transferred to a central ECG lab for analysis.</p><p>The ECG waveforms can be loaded into an analysis tool for making findings (measurements) and possibly deriving other data according to the trial protocol.  The findings are oftentimes in the form of time and amplitude values for the parts of the cardiac process being studied.  The analysis produces two types of information: findings to be used for further statistical analysis on the entire population enrolled in the trial, and annotated ECG waveforms with trial specific fiducial markings, etc. indicating key features used for obtaining the findings.  The annotated ECG waveforms are forwarded to the trial sponsor (interaction: AnnotatedECG Revised, Notification (<artref ref="PORT_IN020001UV01" alt="PORT_IN020001"></artref>)), who can include them without ammendment in a trial submission, or may supply some additional data not present in the notification from the central ECG lab.  In the latter case, the sponsor is responsible for maintaining an audit trail of changes made to the message as received.</p><p>Should any errors be discovered in the message after notification, the deletion interaction (interaction: AnnotatedECG Deleted, Notification (<artref ref="PORT_IN020002UV01" alt="PORT_IN020002"></artref>)) is issued by the central ECG lab, and a new notification message with the corrected information is issued (interaction: AnnotatedECG Revised, Notification (<artref ref="PORT_IN020001UV01" alt="PORT_IN020001"></artref>)).</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="PORT_SN020002UV01" name="AnnotatedECG_03" familiarName="Submitting Annotated ECGs" parent="PORT_ST020001UV01-str" id="PORT_ST020001UV01-PORT_SN020002UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|_01" baseClass="Annotatedecg" lastEdit="2008-06-05T16:50:05"><p>Interaction: AnnotatedECG Submittable, Notification (<artref ref="PORT_IN020003UV01" alt="PORT_IN020003"></artref>)</p><p>The supporting annotated ECG waveforms become part of the sponsor's submission to the regulatory agency.   The communication of the annotated ECG waveforms from the sponsor to the regulatory agency (interaction: AnnotatedECG Submittable, Notification (<artref ref="PORT_IN020003UV01" alt="PORT_IN020003"></artref>)) is the primary focus of this standard.</p><p>During the regulatory agency's review of a submission, the Agency may come across a conclusion drawn from a statistical analysis of ECG findings it wishes to investigate further.  The reviewer may review the ECG analysis protocol and the analysis dataset.  The reviewer may question an ECG finding in the dataset and review the annotated ECG waveforms.  The reviewer may be satisfied with what he sees or may investigate further the ECG measurement protocol and its consistent application during the trial.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="PORT_SN020003UV01" name="AnnotatedECG_04" familiarName="Business Requirements for this Storyboard" parent="PORT_ST020001UV01-str" id="PORT_ST020001UV01-PORT_SN020003UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="10|_01" baseClass="Annotatedecg" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:10:43"><p><emph role="strong">Data Describing the Clinical Trial Context of the Annotated ECG</emph></p><p><emph>Clinical Trial Context Diagram for Annotated ECGs: </emph><graphic source="T-PORT_NA020020.gif" alt="T-PORT_NA020020.gif"></graphic></p><p>The annotated ECG waveforms are the focus of this message.  For each annotated ECG, information is included describing the trial conditions under which the ECG was recorded.  At a minimum, the unique identifiers for the ECG, the trial subject, the trial itself are required.  In addition to the required identifiers, the message must contain the time of the ECG data collection.  This is the minimal set of data considered necessary to properly identify an ECG within a regulatory submission.</p><p>These requirements are included in the diagram above, which shows the annotated ECG itself as a category of data to be included in the message.  Other trial context categories are also shown, along with the relationships among the categories.  All of the individual trial context data items that can be communicated using the HL7 Annotated ECG message are listed and categorized on the diagram, with an indication of whether they are optional or required.  Some entity-relationship (ER) constructs and conventions have been used in this diagram, as described in the key, but this is not intended to be a formal ER diagram.</p><p><emph role="strong">Data Describing the Annotations and Waveforms</emph></p><p><emph>ECG Data Breakdown Diagram for Annotated ECGs: </emph><graphic source="PORT_NA020030.gif" alt="PORT_NA020030.gif"></graphic></p><p>The diagram above shows how the waveforms and annotations are organized relative to the main Annotated ECG object from the previous diagram.  Starting from the bottom of the diagram, each lead and the time associated with the samples is represented as a Sequence -- a sequence of values.  Each Sequence has a type (lead name or time type) and the list of values.</p><p>Sequences that were recorded simultaneously are grouped as Sequence Sets.  A modern electrocardiograph can represent a 12-lead ECG as a single Sequence Set.  A 3 channel electrocardiograph would typically use 4 Sequence Sets for a 12-lead ECG (e.g. set 1 having leads I, II, III, set 2 having leads aVR, aVF, aVL, set 3 having leads V1, V2, V3, and set 4 having leads V4, V5, V5).</p><p>A Series contains all the Sequence Sets that share a common frame of reference.  Typically, the Series will contain the data collected from a single device with a single time reference.  If a representative beat is algorithmically derived from the rhythm data, it will form another Series (derived from the rhythm data Series).</p><p>A number of Annotation Sets can be attached to the Series.  The Annotation Sets contain an arbitrary nesting of Annotations.  The nesting of Annotations allows parent/child relationships to be communicated.  For example, a Beat annotation can be the parent of Wave Component annotations (P-wave, QRS-wave, T-wave, etc.).</p><p>If an annotation has a location within the Series, it is associated with a Region Of Interest (ROI).  The ROI specifies the leads and time period for the annotation.   A fully specified ROI contains a Boundary for each lead and/or time dimension within it.  A partially specified ROI will contain a Boundary for each lead and/or time that is not wholly in it.  For example, if a global QRS onset is to be specified, a partially specified ROI will only have a Boundary for the time dimension.  It is assumed that all the other dimensions (leads) are wholly in the ROI.</p></descriptive><diagref ref="PORT_ST020001UV01.gif"/></story></storydivn><approledivn identifier="roles-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Application Roles" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="roles-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic"><descriptive identifier="arop-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="arop-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gapprole" alt="the discussion of application roles"/> and their relationships in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="arScp-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Introduction" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="arScp-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic"><p>The AnnotatedECG topic has three application roles, two of which are shared with the CTLaboratory topic in this domain.  </p><p>Those shared application roles are defined under the CTLaboratory topic.  Click on their names below to see those definitions:</p><p><artref alt="Clinical Trial Observation Event Global Tracker " ref="PORT_AR010001"></artref></p><p><artref alt="Clinical Trial Observation Event Global Informer " ref="PORT_AR010002"></artref></p></descriptive><artree><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="PORT_AR020001UV01-ar" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="AnnotatedECG_06" refFamiliarName="AnnotatedECG Event Global Informer - CT" refIdentifier="PORT_AR020001UV01"/></artreeitem></artree><approle identifier="PORT_AR020001UV01" name="AnnotatedECG_06" familiarName="AnnotatedECG Event Global Informer - CT" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="PORT_AR020001UV01-ar" sortPrefix="10|99|99|99|_06" baseClass="Annotatedecg" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2004-03-15T17:34:17"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_AR020001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_AR020001UV01-ar" id="desc-PORT_AR020001UV01-ar" lastEdit="2004-03-15T17:34:17"><p>An application that is capable of notifying another system about any state change of a Clinical Trial  Annotated ECG Event.</p></descriptive></approle></approledivn><rmimdivn identifier="rmims-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="rmims-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic"><descriptive identifier="rmop-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="rmop-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><rmim identifier="PORT_RM020001UV01" name="AnnotatedECG_08" familiarName="AnnotatedECG - Clinical Trials" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="PORT_RM020001UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="10|99|99|_08" baseClass="Annotatedecg" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:06:53"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_RM020001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_RM020001UV01-rmi" id="desc-PORT_RM020001UV01-rmi" lastEdit="2008-06-05T17:06:53"><p>The Refined Message Information Model (RMIM) recasts the committee's business models in terms of the HL7 Reference Information Model (RIM).  Click on the links below to open diagrams of those business models.</p><p><emph>Business Model - Clinical Trial Context: </emph></p><p><graphic source="T-PORT_NA020020.gif"></graphic></p><p><emph>Business Model - ECG Data Breakdown: </emph></p><p><graphic source="PORT_NA020030.gif"></graphic></p><p>It will be helpful to open the RMIM at this time to follow along with the discussion of how the RMIM represents the business requirements.</p><p><emph role="strong">REPRESENTATION IN THE R-MIM OF THE INFORMATION ABOUT CLINICAL TRIAL CONTEXT</emph></p><p><emph>Business Model Category: Annotated ECG</emph></p><p>ID, start/end datetimes, blinded status, and protocol conformance specified in the business model are all represented in the R-MIM class AnnotatedECG, which appears in the approximate center of the RMIM diagram. Note that start and end date and time are all captured in the effectiveTime attribute, which can represent an interval of dateTimes.</p><p>The relative timepoint information for the ECG is represented in the R-MIM classes ProtocolTimepointEvent, ReferenceEvent and RelativeTimepoint. The ProtocolTimepointEvent is the protocol definition of the TimepointEvent during which the ECG is taken. If the protocol does not include the notion of timepoint or study events, then the entire trial is considered a single timepoint event for purposes of establishing the ReferenceEvent and RelativeTimepoint.</p><p>The ReferenceEvent class corresponds to the benchmark for the ECG within the TimepointEvent. This could be a dosing for example, or a meal or any other benchmark to which the ECG is related. The protocol-specified name and code (if any) for the benchmark are captured in the code attribute of this Reference Event class.</p><p>The RelativeTimepoint class represents the (scheduled) time for the specific ECG relative to the Reference Event, and the offset value (positive or negative amount and UOM for the offset of the ECG from the benchmark) is captured in the pauseQuantity attribute of the componentOf relationship between the ProtocolTimepointEvent and the RelativeTimepoint classes.</p><p>Performer information for each ECG Series is captured in the R-MIM's ECGPerformer role and its related Person.</p><p>The Transaction Action information is captured in the message wrapper (not shown here).</p><p><emph>Business Model Category: Annotated ECG Related Observation</emph></p><p>All business information in this category is captured in the R-MIM's RelatedObservation class, where the code identifies the type and name for the observation (eg. age, fasting status) and the value captures the observation itself.</p><p><emph>Business Model Category: Annotated ECG Related Comment</emph></p><p>All business information in this category is captured in the R-MIM's FindingComment class, where the code identifies the type and name for the comment and the value captures the comment itself.</p><p><emph>Business Model Category: Study Event</emph></p><p>All of the business information in this category is captured in the TimepointEvent class of the R-MIM, except performer information, which is represented by the StudyEventPerformer class and its related Person.</p><p>Each AnnotatedECG must be assigned to exactly one TimepointEvent. If the protocol does not include the notion of timepoint or study events, then the entire trial is considered a single timepoint event.</p><p><emph>Business Model Categories: Clinical Trial; Trial Site; Trial Site Investigator</emph></p><p>The Clinical Trial category in the business model has a counterpart ClinicalTrial class in the R-MIM. This class captures the sponsor's name and code for the trial (not the protocol) in the id and title attributes. The activityTime attribute captures the start and end dates (and times, if necessary) for the entire trial.</p><p>The name and identifier for the sponsor is represented in the Organization class, which plays the role of ClinicalTrialSponsor, and participates in the trial as the trial's author.</p><p>Trial site information (id, name, country) is captured in the TrialSite role class, or in the Location entity class which plays that role.</p><p>Similarly, trial investigator information (id, name) is captured in the TrialInvestigator and Person classes. The identifier of the person as an investigator should appear in the TrialInvestigator role id.</p><p><emph>Business Model Category: Planned Study</emph></p><p>Planned Study in the business model represents the protocol controlling the individual clinical trial. It is possible for several individual clinical trials to be controlled by the same protocol. The id and name for the controlling protocol for this specific trial are captured in the ClinicalTrialProtocol class of the R-MIM.</p><p><emph>Business Model Categories: Trial Subject; Subject Assignment</emph></p><p>Most of the trial subject information is captured in the R-MIM classes TrialSubject (subject id) and DemographicPerson (initials, birthdate, gender, race).</p><p>As in the business model, the R-MIM class SubjectAssignment serves to associate the subject with a particular trial, site and investigator. Assignment to a trial is mandatory; assignment to a site and investigator are optional.</p><p>In the R-MIM, the SubjectAssignment class also serves to associate the subject with the treatment group to which he/she is assigned for the trial.</p><p><emph role="strong">REPRESENTATION IN THE R-MIM OF THE INFORMATION ABOUT WAVEFORMS AND ANNOTATIONS</emph></p><p>The R-MIM class Series contains the rhythm waveforms directly recorded from the subject, or the representative beat waveforms derived from the rhythm waveforms. The code attribute indicates if the series contains rhythm waveforms or representative beat waveforms.</p><p>The Series attribute effectiveTime captures the interval of time for the waveforms (usually recorded by the device). The effectiveTime for rhythm waveforms is the actual time of data collection. The effectiveTime for a representative beat is the period of time from which the beat was derived.</p><p>The Series can have a unique id, usually assigned by the device that authored it. This unique id can be different from the id of the AnnotatedECG because there can potentially be several Series contributing to a single AnnotatedECG (for a single TimepointEvent and RelativeTimepoint). The Series id also allows annotations in other messages to be associated with the Series.</p><p>The Series is authored by a Device playing a ManufacturedProduct role. The role is scoped by the Organization that manufactured the device. The Device entity captures the id, code (type), model name, and software name. The Organization entity captures the manufacturer's id and name.</p><p>If necessary, id's and names (or initials) of one or more technicians acquiring the ECG data can be captured as the Series SecondaryPerformer.  The SecondaryPerformer is commonly referred to as the "ECG Technician".</p><p>If the Series is a representative beat, and it was derived from a portion of the rhythm series, it is supported by an ROI (Region Of Interest). The ROI specifies which segment of time the representative beat was derived from.</p><p>The Series has one or more SequenceSet components. There is one SequenceSet for each set of ECG leads that were simultaneously acquired. A modern electrocardiograph can simultaneously capture all 12 leads of a 12-lead ECG, and therefore only requires a single SequenceSet. A 3-channel electrocardiograph, on the other hand, must acquire the 12 leads 3 at a time. A 3-channel device would typically use 4 SequenceSets for a 12-lead ECG.</p><p>Each SequenceSet contains a Sequence for the time base and each lead simultaneously acquired. For example, a 12-lead ECG represented in a single SequenceSet would have 13 Sequences: one for time, and one for each of the 12 leads. The type of Sequence is captured in the code attribute, and the sample values are captured in the value attribute (as a list). The ECG lead types from the ISO/IEEE 11073-10101 standard will be used for the code attribute whenever appropriate.</p><p>It is important to note that HL7 provides a couple of special datatypes for representing the values of a Sequence. If the Sequence contains a regular pattern of values (such as evenly sampled time), the GLIST (generated list) collection type can generate the sequence of values from a few parameters (e.g. initial value and increment). If the Sequence contains values in native integer device units, the SLIST (sampled list) collection type can specify scale and translate factors so the native integers can be placed in the message</p><p>The Series, SequenceSet, and/or Sequence can be associated with one or more ControlVariables. A ControlVariable captures additional information about how the waveforms were created. For example, if the waveforms had filtering applied, the filter settings should be captured as ControlVariables. The ControlVariable code captures the type of variable (e.g. low pass filter), and the value captures the variable's setting (e.g. 150 Hz).</p><p>AnnotationSets can be associated with a Series.  The activityTime of the set captures when the set of annotations were made.  Each set of annotations can have a common author and common ControlVariables.  The author can be a Device or a Person playing the AssignedEntity role. The id of the AssignedEntity captures the trial specific id of the annotator. The scoping Organization captures the id and name of the organization making the annotation via the Device or Person.  ControlVariables can be associated with the AnnotationSet to capture important details about the annotation method (e.g. algorithm settings such as criteria used to classify tachycardia, etc.).</p><p>Each AnnotationSet contains one or more annotations for the Series. Each Annotation has a code specifying what type of annotation it is, and when appropriate, the value attribute specifies the annotations's value. The ECG nomenclature from the ISO/IEEE 11073-10101 standard will be used for the Annotation codes and values whenever possible.</p><p>Annotations can contain child annotations when appropriate. For example, it may be necessary to communicate that a P-wave, QRS-wave, and T-wave all belong to the same beat. A beat annotation could then contain child annotations for each of the wave components. Likewise, it might be necessary to group all the fiducial markings related to a particular ECG measurement, like QTc. A QTc annotation could have child annotations for a couple R-peaks, a QRS-wave, and a T-wave. If the QTc was calculated from several beats, each beat's QTc fiducial markings could make up another level in the hierarchy.</p><p>Each Annotation can be supported by an ROI. The ROI specifies where in the Series the Annotation applies. For example, if the Annotation is a T-wave, the ROI will specify a Boundary in time for the beginning and end of the T-wave, and optionally a Boundary for each Lead that is included.</p><p>The ROI code attribute says whether the ROI is partially or fully specified by its Boundaries. A partially specified ROI only include Boundaries for dimensions that are constrained. All other unspecified dimensions would be included in the ROI. For example, a global QRS-wave could be annotated with a partially specified ROI with only a time Boundary. A fully specified ROI, on the other hand, only includes the dimensions that are named as Boundaries. So, if the QRS-wave is only observed in Lead II, then a Boundary for time and a Boundary for Lead II would be specified. All other unnamed dimensions would not be included in the ROI.</p><p>The code attribute of the Boundary names the dimension being bounded. These codes should match the codes used in the Sequence instances. For example, if the Series contains a Sequence for absolute time, and an ROI needs to bound that time, the same code for absolute time is used as the Boundary code. The Boundary's value attribute is usually an interval capturing the optional start and optional end of the ROI within that dimension. However, if the value is truly a single point (e.g. R-wave peak), then the value attribute will contain a single value, not an interval.</p><p>The Boundary values can be used to communicate several things. If a T-wave Annotation is used to communicate the offset of T, the ROI's time boundary would only specify the interval's high value. The low value can be unspecified. Likewise, if the beginning of the a P-wave is to be communicated, the ROI time boundary would only specify the interval's low value.</p><p>The relationship between the Annotation and its ROI can also be used to communicate a couple of different concepts. If the relationship is the more general "has support", the ROI communicates boundaries that aren't necessarily the true boundaries of the annotation. For example, if atrial flutter is observed in the waveforms, but the true beginning and ending of the flutter episode is not observed, the annotation "has support" from the ROI (but it's not the full story). On the other hand, if the true beginning and end of atrial flutter is observed, the "has bounded support" relationship can be used. In other words, the annotation's ROI supports AND defines the true boundaries. </p></descriptive><diagref ref="PORT_RM020001UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="PORT_HD020001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="AnnotatedECG_09" refFamiliarName="AnnotatedECG  - Clinical Trials" refIdentifier="PORT_HD020001UV01"/></rmim></rmimdivn><hmddivn identifier="hmds-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="hmds-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic"><descriptive identifier="hdop-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="hdop-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><hmd identifier="PORT_HD020001UV01" name="AnnotatedECG_09" familiarName="AnnotatedECG  - Clinical Trials" parent="PORT_RM020001UV01-rmi" id="PORT_HD020001UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="10|99|99|_09" baseClass="Annotatedecg" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-07-22T19:01:26"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_HD020001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_HD020001UV01-hmd" id="desc-PORT_HD020001UV01-hmd" lastEdit="2004-07-22T19:01:26"><p>The AnnotatedECG - Clinical Trials HMD is based upon the Annotated ECG - Clinical Trials R-MIM.   All information available from that RMIM is included in this HMD.  Message types based upon this HMD are used to communicate ECG annotations and waveforms.</p></descriptive><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="PORT_HD020001UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="PORT_RM020001UV01-rmi" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="AnnotatedECG_08" refFamiliarName="AnnotatedECG - Clinical Trials" refIdentifier="PORT_RM020001UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="PORT_MT020001UV01-msg" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="AnnotatedECG_10 (base)" refFamiliarName="AnnotatedECG. base  - Clinical Trials" refIdentifier="PORT_MT020001UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="PORT_MT020002UV01-msg" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="AnnotatedECG_10 (deletion)" refFamiliarName="AnnotatedECG, deletion - Clinical Trials" refIdentifier="PORT_MT020002UV01"/></hmd></hmddivn><msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="msgs-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic"><msgtype identifier="PORT_MT020001UV01" name="AnnotatedECG_10 (base)" familiarName="AnnotatedECG. base  - Clinical Trials" parent="PORT_HD020001UV01-hmd" id="PORT_MT020001UV01-msg" sortPrefix="10|99|99|_10 (BASE)" baseClass="Annotatedecg" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-07-22T19:03:32"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="PORT_MT020001UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="PORT_HD020001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="AnnotatedECG_09" refFamiliarName="AnnotatedECG  - Clinical Trials" refIdentifier="PORT_HD020001UV01"/></msgtype><msgtype identifier="PORT_MT020002UV01" name="AnnotatedECG_10 (deletion)" familiarName="AnnotatedECG, deletion - Clinical Trials" parent="PORT_HD020001UV01-hmd" id="PORT_MT020002UV01-msg" sortPrefix="10|99|99|_10 (DELETION)" baseClass="Annotatedecg" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2004-07-22T19:03:29"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="PORT_MT020002UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="PORT_HD020001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="AnnotatedECG_09" refFamiliarName="AnnotatedECG  - Clinical Trials" refIdentifier="PORT_HD020001UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="PORT_IN999999UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="annotat" refFamiliarName="Explanation" refIdentifier="PORT_IN999999UV01"/></msgtype></msgtypedivn><annexdivn identifier="annx-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Implementation Guide" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="annx-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" role="IG" baseClass="Annotatedecg" ballotStatus="InformativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><descriptive identifier="annxInt-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg" name="Introduction" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" id="annxInt-PORT_DO000001UV-Annotatedecg-ic" lastEdit="2009-06-03T13:51:07"><p>This annex presents the HL7 implementation guide for the approved standard <emph>Annotated ECG, Release 1</emph>.  The guide is a stand-alone document.</p><p><loc href="V3_RT_AECG_R1_IMPL_INFORM_2004.pdf">Click here to view a PDF of the approved implementation guide.</loc></p></descriptive></annexdivn></subdivn><subdivn identifier="PORT_DO000001UV-Crfqsreleaseone" name="Clinical Research Filtered Query Service Release 1 Topic" familiarName="Clinical Research Filtered Query Service Release 1" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORT_DO000001UV-Crfqsreleaseone-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="14" baseClass="Clinical Research Filtered Query Service Release 1" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1"><descriptive identifier="intro-PORT_DO000001UV-Crfqsreleaseone" name="Introduction" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Crfqsreleaseone-ic" id="intro-PORT_DO000001UV-Crfqsreleaseone-ic" lastEdit="2009-06-03T14:01:23"><p>The general content of this document is specified under the Service Development Framework (SDF) process under the auspices of the Healthcare Services Specification Project (HSSP). Readers of this document should keep in mind that the SFM provides a Service interface specification, not a specification of a Service implementation. (A more detailed contextual discussion of this point is given in the Overview section of this document.) The distinction between a service interface specification and a service implementation is a critical point of distinction in context of Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) methodologies and implementations. In particular, a single service interface specification can - an often does - have more than one associated service implementation, i.e., there are different, semantically consistent ways of implementing all or part of the functionality specified in the SFM and therefore to support the behavior described in this SFM/specification. </p><p>The Clinical Research Filtered Query (CRFQ) service is one of several 'business-level' services which are anticipated to utilize other HSSP 'infrastructure' and 'process' services (e.g. RLUS, DSS, Consent, Anonymization, etc.) in business-process-driven orchestrations designed to achieve critical business goals in an automated/semi-automated fashion. </p><p>Readers may want to target to review of this document based on their perspective of the CRFQ service.  The document provides a high-level guide for readers based on their association with:</p><list role="unordered"><item>the Regulated Clinical Research Information Management Technical Committee or other organizations, groups, or committees consisting primarily of Subject Matter Experts (SMEs); 
</item><item>architecture- or design-level groups such as HL7SOA or HSSP; and/or </item><item>responders to the OMG RFP that will be issued once the CRFQ becomes an ANSI Draft Standard for Trial Use (DSTU) through the HL7-supervised ANSI balloting process, as well as other institutions or organizations that may be interested in building initial implementation of the CRFQ service independent of the OMG RFP process.</item></list><p><loc href="HL7_V3_CRFQSFM_R1_DSTU_2008.pdf">Click to view a PDF of the CRFQ SFM document.</loc></p></descriptive></subdivn><subdivn identifier="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Drug Stability Reporting R2 Topic" familiarName="Drug Stability Reporting R2" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="25" baseClass="Drug Stability Reporting R2" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><descriptive identifier="intro-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Introduction" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="intro-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" lastEdit="2011-06-15T13:49:56"><p>Release 2 of the stability message (including material for drug stability testing) passed its HL7 Normative ballot following the HL7 May 2010 ballot cycle.  The specification is designed to capture the contents of a stability report to be submitted to a national regulatory agency.  At this point, the primary point of reference is current stability reporting within the United States.  The scope of a single transaction or message in this specification has been restricted to only include studies with a single set of storage conditions.  However, the stability studies that are filed with regulatory authorities are not simply a study with a single set of storage conditions - the studies include a number of storage conditions plus multiple orientations (upright and inverted).  This is especially true for injectable/Parenteral products.  These more complex situations, that is to say, studies that require multiple storage conditions  and or orientations (e.g., accelerated, room temperature, inverted, upright, etc.), will be handled through the submission of multiple linked reports, with each report covering a single storage condition and orientation.  </p><p>The changes from the initial DSTU to this normative ballot are as follows: 1) Added the attribute "text:  ED [0..1]" to the AssociatedStudy class, 2) Added the attribute "expirationTime*:  IVL_TS [1..1]" to Substance class; and 3) Changed the cardinality of component5 going from the class StabilityStudy to the class StudyOnBatch from"1..* studyOnBatch*" to 1..1 studyOnBatch*".
</p><p>The changes from R1 to Release 2 DSTU (now Normative) are as follows:  1) Added AssociatedStudy with an order (sequenceNumber) so stability reports can be linked and in a specific order if needed, 2) Changed the name Organization to StudySponser, 3) Made organization ID zero to many (StudySponser, Manufacturer, TestingSite, and SiteStub) to allow an organization to be identified by many systems (e.g., OID, FEI, DUNS, etc.), 4) Linked Storage directly to StudyOnBatch eliminating the prior choice box holding Storage and Testing because only a single set of storage conditions is supported, and 5) Moved TestingSite under Testing with zero to many and added SiteStub under Test so the site performing the test may be identified by ID number reducing the redundancy of information for Test.
</p></descriptive><storydivn identifier="sbs-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Storyboards" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="sbs-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><descriptive identifier="sstop-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="sstop-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="sstoScp-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Introduction" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="sstoScp-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><p>The Storyboard is presented as a high-level description of the business situation the standard is designed to address, accompanied by a diagram of the interactions that will be described in the narratives that follow.  Interactions were discussed in the <artref ref="PORT_DO000001" alt="Introduction and Scope"></artref> section of the Regulated Studies domain chapter, under the heading<emph> "Summary of Clinical Trial Interactions in the Regulated Studies Domain"</emph>.  There you will find a diagram of the AnnotatedECG and Clinical Trial laboratory interactions in context.</p><p>A number of narrative sections follow each high-level description, each describing a scenario in which one of the interactions might be used.  These narratives are for illustrative purposes only.  They are not meant to limit the applicability of the standard, nor to proscribe minimum requirements for using the standard.  In particular, <emph role="strong">there is no intent to establish regulatory agency policy on management of data or processes through these scenarios</emph>.  Such policy will be separately published by the regulatory agencies (eg. as Implementation Guides or Guidances).</p></descriptive><story identifier="PORT_ST090001UV01" name="StabilityStudyRtwo Stability Reporting" familiarName="Stability Reporting" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="PORT_ST090001UV01-str" sortPrefix="25|STABILITY REPORTING" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:54:58"><descriptive identifier="purp-PORT_ST090001UV01" name="Purpose" parent="PORT_ST090001UV01-str" id="purp-PORT_ST090001UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:54:58"><p>The storyboard provides an example of a situation in which the Public Health Stability Reporting message would be used.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="PORT_SN090001UV01" name="Stabilitystudy Event Report" familiarName="Stability Study Event Report" parent="PORT_ST090001UV01-str" id="PORT_ST090001UV01-PORT_SN090001UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="25|STABILITY REPORTING" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" lastEdit="2010-05-18T16:34:42"><p>Interactions: Stability Report (<artref ref="PORT_IN090001" alt="PORT_IN090001"></artref>)</p><p>ChemCentric Drug Company has been working on a new product, CureAll. Development work on the product has been completed, as have many aspects of the regulatory process. One aspect of the regulatory process is to demonstrate the stability of the CureAll product by testing it against an established Testing Specification using an acceptable protocol. 

ChemCentric has carried out the necessary testing, and reports the test results to the applicable regulatory authority.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="PORT_SN090002UV01" name="Stabilitystudy Event Report Revise" familiarName="Stability Study Event Report Revise" parent="PORT_ST090001UV01-str" id="PORT_ST090001UV01-PORT_SN090002UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="25|STABILITY REPORTING" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" lastEdit="2010-05-18T16:34:54"><p>Interactions: Stability Report Revision (<artref ref="PORT_IN090002" alt="PORT_IN090002"></artref>)</p><p>Last month, ChemCentric Drug Company submitted a stability study for its new product, CureAll, to the FDA</p><p>However, Dr. Reggie Review has been going over the results of the test.  He has discovered a transcription error that could lead reviewers to get an unfair estimation of CureAll's efficacy even after lengthy storage.  In order to correct this state of affairs, ChemCentric submits a revised Stability Study.</p></descriptive><diagref ref="PORT_ST090001UV01.gif"/><intref ref="PORT_IN090004UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Complete" refFamiliarName="Stability Study Event Report" refIdentifier="PORT_IN090004UV01" sequence="1"/><intref ref="PORT_IN090005UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Revise" refFamiliarName="Stability Study Event Report Revision" refIdentifier="PORT_IN090005UV01" sequence="2"/></story></storydivn><approledivn identifier="roles-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Application Roles" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="roles-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><descriptive identifier="arop-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="arop-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gapprole" alt="the discussion of application roles"/> and their relationships in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><artree><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="PORT_AR090002UV01-ar" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Existence Receiver" refFamiliarName="Stability Report Receiver" refIdentifier="PORT_AR090002UV01"/></artreeitem><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="PORT_AR090001UV01-ar" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Existence Informer" refFamiliarName="Stability Report Sender" refIdentifier="PORT_AR090001UV01"/></artreeitem></artree><approle identifier="PORT_AR090002UV01" name="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Existence Receiver" familiarName="Stability Report Receiver" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="PORT_AR090002UV01-ar" sortPrefix="25|20|09|22|" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="yes" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:05"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_AR090002UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_AR090002UV01-ar" id="desc-PORT_AR090002UV01-ar" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:05"><p>A regulatory or other organization that is concerned with product stability, and that receives, stores, evaluates the results of stability testing. 

 </p></descriptive><intref role="receives" ref="PORT_IN090004UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Complete" refFamiliarName="Stability Study Event Report" refIdentifier="PORT_IN090004UV01"/><intref role="receives" ref="PORT_IN090005UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Revise" refFamiliarName="Stability Study Event Report Revision" refIdentifier="PORT_IN090005UV01"/></approle><approle identifier="PORT_AR090001UV01" name="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Existence Informer" familiarName="Stability Report Sender" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="PORT_AR090001UV01-ar" sortPrefix="25|20|09|25|" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" hidden="yes" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:09"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_AR090001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_AR090001UV01-ar" id="desc-PORT_AR090001UV01-ar" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:09"><p>An organization that carries out stability testing on a regulated pharmaceutical product.</p></descriptive><intref role="sends" ref="PORT_IN090004UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Complete" refFamiliarName="Stability Study Event Report" refIdentifier="PORT_IN090004UV01"/><intref role="sends" ref="PORT_IN090005UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Revise" refFamiliarName="Stability Study Event Report Revision" refIdentifier="PORT_IN090005UV01"/></approle></approledivn><triggerdivn identifier="tes-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Trigger Events" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="tes-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><descriptive identifier="teop-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="teop-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gtrigger" alt="the discussion of trigger events"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><trigger identifier="PORT_TE090001UV01" name="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Create Notification" familiarName="Stability Report Notification" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="PORT_TE090001UV01-te" role="State-transition based" sortPrefix="25|20|04||05|" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:15"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_TE090001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_TE090001UV01-te" id="desc-PORT_TE090001UV01-te" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:15"><p>Indicates the report of stability testing is ready for transmission to an eligible receiver.</p></descriptive><intref role="fires" ref="PORT_IN090004UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Complete" refFamiliarName="Stability Study Event Report" refIdentifier="PORT_IN090004UV01"/></trigger><trigger identifier="PORT_TE090002UV01" name="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Revise Notification" familiarName="Stability Report Revise Notification" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="PORT_TE090002UV01-te" role="State-transition based" sortPrefix="25|20|22||05|" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:18"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_TE090002UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_TE090002UV01-te" id="desc-PORT_TE090002UV01-te" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:18"><p>Indicates that the creating institution has made changes to the material covered in a previous stability report, and is transmitting a revised version.</p></descriptive><intref role="fires" ref="PORT_IN090005UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Revise" refFamiliarName="Stability Study Event Report Revision" refIdentifier="PORT_IN090005UV01"/></trigger></triggerdivn><rmimdivn identifier="rmims-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="rmims-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><descriptive identifier="rmop-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="rmop-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><rmim identifier="PORT_RM090002UV01" name="StabilityStudyRtwo Event" familiarName="Stability Study RMIM" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="PORT_RM090002UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="25|20|99|" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:25"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_RM090002UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_RM090002UV01-rmi" id="desc-PORT_RM090002UV01-rmi" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:25"><emph role="strong"> Model Overview</emph><p>The Drug Stability Report RMIM captures information relevant for the drug stability testing process.  This testing is required in the United States as a component of the drug regulatory process.  It verifies the correctness of a manufacturer's claims related to the stability - the ability to be stored over time without losing its therapeutic effectiveness - of a product.</p><p>It is important to note that the material that can be reported as part of a Stability Study is not limited to the items explicitly listed as attributes within the RMIM.  This is because the "text' attribute in Acts (shown in red on the diagram), and the "desc" attribute in Entities (shown in green on the diagram) can be valued with a URL which provides a link to additional documentation.  This additional documentation would either be provided along with the stability report, or would be stored at the sender's site at the location indicated by the URL.  </p><p>The HMD file provides a discussion of the classes, associations, and attributes within the model.
</p></descriptive><diagref ref="PORT_RM090002UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="PORT_HD090002UV01-hmd" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event" refFamiliarName="Stability Study HMD" refIdentifier="PORT_HD090002UV01"/></rmim></rmimdivn><hmddivn identifier="hmds-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="hmds-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><descriptive identifier="hdop-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="hdop-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><hmd identifier="PORT_HD090002UV01" name="StabilityStudyRtwo Event" familiarName="Stability Study HMD" parent="PORT_RM090002UV01-rmi" id="PORT_HD090002UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="25|20|99|" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:56:06"><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="PORT_HD090002UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="PORT_RM090002UV01-rmi" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event" refFamiliarName="Stability Study RMIM" refIdentifier="PORT_RM090002UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="PORT_MT090002UV01-msg" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Complete" refFamiliarName="Stability Study Message Type" refIdentifier="PORT_MT090002UV01"/></hmd></hmddivn><msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="msgs-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><msgtype identifier="PORT_MT090002UV01" name="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Complete" familiarName="Stability Study Message Type" parent="PORT_HD090002UV01-hmd" id="PORT_MT090002UV01-msg" sortPrefix="25|20|40|" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:56:14"><msgextref role="tabular" ref="PORT_MT090002UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="PORT_HD090002UV01-hmd" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event" refFamiliarName="Stability Study HMD" refIdentifier="PORT_HD090002UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="PORT_IN090005UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Revise" refFamiliarName="Stability Study Event Report Revision" refIdentifier="PORT_IN090005UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="PORT_IN090004UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Complete" refFamiliarName="Stability Study Event Report" refIdentifier="PORT_IN090004UV01"/></msgtype></msgtypedivn><interactiondivn identifier="ints-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Interactions" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="ints-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><descriptive identifier="inop-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="inop-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gintact" alt="the definition of Interactions"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="intScp-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Introduction" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="intScp-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic"><p>An Interaction is the formatted package of data to be exchanged between a named sender and a named receiver in response to a named trigger event.</p></descriptive><interaction identifier="PORT_IN090005UV01" name="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Revise" familiarName="Stability Study Event Report Revision" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="PORT_IN090005UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="25|20|22|99|" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:34"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_IN090005UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_IN090005UV01-int" id="desc-PORT_IN090005UV01-int" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:34"><p>The interaction  supports revisions to previously sent stability messages.</p></descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="PORT_AR090001UV01-ar" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Existence Informer" refFamiliarName="Stability Report Sender" refIdentifier="PORT_AR090001UV01"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="PORT_AR090002UV01-ar" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Existence Receiver" refFamiliarName="Stability Report Receiver" refIdentifier="PORT_AR090002UV01"/><teref role="trigger" ref="PORT_TE090002UV01-te" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Revise Notification" refFamiliarName="Stability Report Revise Notification" refIdentifier="PORT_TE090002UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="PORT_MT090002UV01-msg" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Stability Study Message Type" refIdentifier="PORT_MT090002UV01"/></interaction><interaction identifier="PORT_IN090004UV01" name="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Complete" familiarName="Stability Study Event Report" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="PORT_IN090004UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="25|20|40|99|" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:39"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_IN090004UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_IN090004UV01-int" id="desc-PORT_IN090004UV01-int" lastEdit="2010-07-27T09:55:39"><p>The interaction supports the communication of a new stability report</p></descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="PORT_AR090001UV01-ar" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Existence Informer" refFamiliarName="Stability Report Sender" refIdentifier="PORT_AR090001UV01"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="PORT_AR090002UV01-ar" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Existence Receiver" refFamiliarName="Stability Report Receiver" refIdentifier="PORT_AR090002UV01"/><teref role="trigger" ref="PORT_TE090001UV01-te" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="StabilityStudyRtwo Event Create Notification" refFamiliarName="Stability Report Notification" refIdentifier="PORT_TE090001UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="PORT_MT090002UV01-msg" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Stability Study Message Type" refIdentifier="PORT_MT090002UV01"/></interaction></interactiondivn><annexdivn identifier="annx-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Drug Stability Reporting Release 2 Implementation Guide" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="annx-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" role="IG" baseClass="Stabilitystudyrtwo" ballotStatus="InformativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><descriptive identifier="annxInt-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo" name="Introduction" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" id="annxInt-PORT_DO000001UV-Stabilitystudyrtwo-ic" lastEdit="2011-04-26T16:04:31"><p>This Implementation Guide (IG) is for the use of the Health Level 7 (HL7) Stability Standard.  The IG describes the basic requirements needed for using the standard and the requirements needed for submitting information to the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) using the standard.  This standard is meant to be used for all regulated products (e.g., test kits, drugs, reagents, medicated feeds, etc.), excluding foods. The IG is based on the most up-to-date information from HL7.</p><p>The HL7 Stability Standard is for one way communication between contractor to company, company to company, company to regulatory agency.</p><p>The Drug Stability Reporting Implementation Guide can be found <loc href="V3_IG_DSRR2_R2_INFORM_2010NOV.pdf">here.</loc></p></descriptive></annexdivn></subdivn><subdivn identifier="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Clinical Trials Registration and Results Topic" familiarName="Clinical Trials Registration and Results" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="34" baseClass="Clinical Trials Registration and Results" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1"><div2 id="intro-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><head>Introduction</head><div3 id="prefDSTU"><head>HL7 Draft Standard for Trial Use</head><p>This is a Draft Standard for Trial Use of the Version 3 Clinical Trial Registration and Results (CTR&amp;R), Release 1 topic.  This topic, in the Regulated Studies domain, was approved as a DSTU following a successful DSTU ballot during HL7 International's May 2010 ballot cycle.</p><p>"Publication of this draft standard for trial use and comment has been approved by Health Level Seven, Inc. (HL7). This draft standard is not an accredited American National Standard. The comment period for use of this draft standard shall end 12 months from the date of publication. Suggestions for revision should be submitted at <loc href="http://www.hl7.org/dstucomments/index.cfm">//www.hl7.org/dstucomments/index.cfm.</loc></p><p>Following this 12 month evaluation period, this draft standard, revised as necessary, will be submitted to a normative ballot in preparation for approval by ANSI as an American National Standard. Implementations of this draft standard shall be viable throughout the normative ballot process and for up to six months after publication of the relevant normative standard</p></div3><p>The Clinical Trial Registration message is a message specification for an interaction containing a clinical trial protocol specification between a clinical trial protocol authoring organization and a registration authority and for interaction between clinical trial registration authorities.</p></div2><storydivn identifier="sbs-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Storyboards" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="sbs-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><descriptive identifier="sstop-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="sstop-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gstory" alt="the storyboard discussion"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="sstoScp-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Introduction" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="sstoScp-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><p>The Storyboard is presented as a high-level description of the business situation the standard is designed to address, accompanied by a diagram of the interactions that will be described in the narratives that follow.  Interactions were discussed in the <artref ref="PORT_DO000001" alt="Introduction and Scope"></artref> section of the Regulated Studies domain chapter, under the heading<emph> "Summary of Clinical Trial Interactions in the Regulated Studies Domain"</emph>.  There you will find a diagram of the AnnotatedECG and Clinical Trial laboratory interactions in context.</p><p>A number of narrative sections follow each high-level description, each describing a scenario in which one of the interactions might be used.  These narratives are for illustrative purposes only.  They are not meant to limit the applicability of the standard, nor to proscribe minimum requirements for using the standard.  In particular, <emph role="strong">there is no intent to establish regulatory agency policy on management of data or processes through these scenarios</emph>.  Such policy will be separately published by the regulatory agencies (eg. as Implementation Guides or Guidances).</p></descriptive><story identifier="PORT_ST140001UV01" name="Clinicaltrialsregistry" familiarName="ClinicalTrialRegistration" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="PORT_ST140001UV01-str" sortPrefix="34|" baseClass="Clinicaltrialsregistry" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2010-04-05T14:02:09" class="changed"><descriptive identifier="purp-PORT_ST140001UV01" name="Purpose" parent="PORT_ST140001UV01-str" id="purp-PORT_ST140001UV01-str" role="purpose" lastEdit="2010-04-05T14:02:09"><p>The clinical trial registration process includes a submission of a clinical trial protocol specification to a registration authority.  This same payload structure may also be useful for data exchange from one registry authority to another or from a sponsoring organization to a ethics review body; however, these specific alternate use cases have not been fully explored.
	</p><p>Only the Clinical Trial Registration submission from the sponsoring organization to the registration authority is being balloted at this time.
	</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="PORT_SN140001UV01" name="Clinicaltrialsregistry" familiarName="Clinical Trial Registration Submission" parent="PORT_ST140001UV01-str" id="PORT_ST140001UV01-PORT_SN140001UV01-stex" role="storyExample" sortPrefix="34|" baseClass="Clinicaltrialsregistry" lastEdit="2010-04-05T19:15:45"><p>A Sponsoring Organization submits Clinical Trial Registration Information to a Registration Authority.
	</p><p><diagref ref="PORT_IN140001UV.gif"></diagref></p></descriptive><diagref ref="PORT_ST140001UV01.gif"/><intref ref="PORT_IN140001UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" refFamiliarName="Clinical Trial Registration" refIdentifier="PORT_IN140001UV01" sequence="1"/></story></storydivn><approledivn identifier="roles-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Application Roles" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="roles-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><descriptive identifier="arop-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="arop-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gapprole" alt="the discussion of application roles"/> and their relationships in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><artree><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="PORT_AR140002UV01-ar" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent Receiver" refFamiliarName="Registration Authority" refIdentifier="PORT_AR140002UV01"/></artreeitem><artreeitem><arref role="included" ref="PORT_AR140001UV01-ar" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent Informer" refFamiliarName="Sponsor Organization" refIdentifier="PORT_AR140001UV01"/></artreeitem></artree><approle identifier="PORT_AR140002UV01" name="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent Receiver" familiarName="Registration Authority" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="PORT_AR140002UV01-ar" sortPrefix="34|15|99|22|" baseClass="Clinicaltrialsregistry" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2009-11-25T08:18:57"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_AR140002UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_AR140002UV01-ar" id="desc-PORT_AR140002UV01-ar" lastEdit="2009-11-25T08:18:57"><p> The organization that maintains a registry of clinical trial protocols.
</p></descriptive><intref role="receives" ref="PORT_IN140001UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" refFamiliarName="Clinical Trial Registration" refIdentifier="PORT_IN140001UV01"/></approle><approle identifier="PORT_AR140001UV01" name="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent Informer" familiarName="Sponsor Organization" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="PORT_AR140001UV01-ar" sortPrefix="34|15|99|25|" baseClass="Clinicaltrialsregistry" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" hidden="no" lastEdit="2009-11-25T08:18:30"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_AR140001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_AR140001UV01-ar" id="desc-PORT_AR140001UV01-ar" lastEdit="2009-11-25T08:18:30"><p>The organization that prepares a clinical trial protocol specification and submits the specification to a registration authority.
</p></descriptive><intref role="sends" ref="PORT_IN140001UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" refFamiliarName="Clinical Trial Registration" refIdentifier="PORT_IN140001UV01"/></approle></approledivn><triggerdivn identifier="tes-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Trigger Events" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="tes-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><descriptive identifier="teop-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="teop-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gtrigger" alt="the discussion of trigger events"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><trigger identifier="PORT_TE140001UV01" name="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" familiarName="Clinical Trial Registration Submission" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="PORT_TE140001UV01-te" role="User request" sortPrefix="34|15|99||99|" baseClass="Clinicaltrialsregistry" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2009-11-24T13:32:59"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_TE140001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_TE140001UV01-te" id="desc-PORT_TE140001UV01-te" lastEdit="2009-11-24T13:32:59"><p>The act of submitting a clinical trial protocol specification to a registration authority.
</p></descriptive><intref role="fires" ref="PORT_IN140001UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" refFamiliarName="Clinical Trial Registration" refIdentifier="PORT_IN140001UV01"/></trigger></triggerdivn><rmimdivn identifier="rmims-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Refined Message Information Models" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="rmims-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><descriptive identifier="rmop-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="rmop-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3grmim" alt="the description of RMIMs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><rmim identifier="PORT_RM140001UV01" name="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" familiarName="Clinical Trial Registration RMIM" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="PORT_RM140001UV01-rmi" sortPrefix="34|15|99|" baseClass="Clinicaltrialsregistry" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" class="inserted" lastEdit="2010-04-05T14:07:30"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_RM140001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_RM140001UV01-rmi" id="desc-PORT_RM140001UV01-rmi" lastEdit="2010-04-05T14:07:30">The clinical trial registration RMIM is a model of the payload included in a clinical trial registration interaction.  It contains protocol data describing the study in sufficient detail to enable assessment and registration by the registration authority.  The specific elements required vary by registration authority.  For this iteration of the message data requirements from CT.gov, WHO.CTR, and EudraCT were considered.  Future iterations will include data requirements from additional registration authorities.  There are many data requirements in common among the authorities and a few elements which are unique to particular authorities.  This RMIM is designed to encompass universal requirements with the idea that regional/realm specific implementation guides will be developed to further constrain the RMIM as needed.  The content of the RMIM is based entirely upon the CTRR Domain Analysis Model.  The RMIM contains references from RMIM clone attributes to class attributes in the DAM.  For a complete understanding of the RMIM the reader should also refer to the CTRR DAM and the mapping spreadsheets linking elements in the DAM to requirements specified by CT.gov, WHO.CTR, and EudraCT.</descriptive><diagref ref="PORT_RM140001UV.gif"/><hmdref role="containedHMD" ref="PORT_HD140001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" refFamiliarName="Clinicaltrialsregistry HMD" refIdentifier="PORT_HD140001UV01"/></rmim></rmimdivn><hmddivn identifier="hmds-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Hierarchical Message Descriptions" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="hmds-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><descriptive identifier="hdop-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="hdop-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3ghmd" alt="the description of HMDs"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><hmd identifier="PORT_HD140001UV01" name="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" familiarName="Clinicaltrialsregistry HMD" parent="PORT_RM140001UV01-rmi" id="PORT_HD140001UV01-hmd" sortPrefix="34|15|99|" baseClass="Clinicaltrialsregistry" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2009-12-03T11:35:12"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_HD140001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_HD140001UV01-hmd" id="desc-PORT_HD140001UV01-hmd" lastEdit="2009-12-03T11:35:12"><p>The clinical trial registration HMD is the serialized version of the RMIM used to model the payload included in a clinical trial registration interaction.  It contains protocol data describing the study in sufficient detail to enable assessment and registration by the registration authority.</p></descriptive><hmdextref role="tabular" ref="PORT_HD140001UV01"/><rmimref role="parent" ref="PORT_RM140001UV01-rmi" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" refFamiliarName="Clinical Trial Registration RMIM" class="inserted" refIdentifier="PORT_RM140001UV01"/><msgref role="definedMsgType" ref="PORT_MT140001UV01-msg" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" refFamiliarName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Message Type" refIdentifier="PORT_MT140001UV01"/></hmd></hmddivn><msgtypedivn identifier="msgs-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Message Type Definitions" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="msgs-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><msgtype identifier="PORT_MT140001UV01" name="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" familiarName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Message Type" parent="PORT_HD140001UV01-hmd" id="PORT_MT140001UV01-msg" sortPrefix="34|15|99|" baseClass="Clinicaltrialsregistry" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2009-11-24T12:42:57"><descriptive identifier="devnote-PORT_MT140001UV01" name="Design Note" parent="PORT_MT140001UV01-msg" id="devnote-PORT_MT140001UV01-msg" role="designComment" lastEdit="2009-11-24T12:42:57">The clinical trial registration message type is the serialized version of the RMIM used to model the payload included in a clinical trial registration interaction.  It contains protocol data describing the study in sufficient detail to enable assessment and registration by the registration authority.</descriptive><msgextref role="tabular" ref="PORT_MT140001UV01"/><hmdref role="parent" ref="PORT_HD140001UV01-hmd" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" refFamiliarName="Clinicaltrialsregistry HMD" refIdentifier="PORT_HD140001UV01"/><intref role="sentIn" ref="PORT_IN140001UV01-int" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" refFamiliarName="Clinical Trial Registration" refIdentifier="PORT_IN140001UV01"/></msgtype></msgtypedivn><interactiondivn identifier="ints-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Interactions" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="ints-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><descriptive identifier="inop-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Reference" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="inop-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><p>For details on the interpretation of this section, see <xspecref spec="v3guide.htm" ref="v3gintact" alt="the definition of Interactions"/> in the Version 3 Guide.</p></descriptive><descriptive identifier="intScp-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry" name="Introduction" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="intScp-PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic"><p>An Interaction is the formatted package of data to be exchanged between a named sender and a named receiver in response to a named trigger event.</p></descriptive><interaction identifier="PORT_IN140001UV01" name="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" familiarName="Clinical Trial Registration" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-Clinicaltrialsregistry-ic" id="PORT_IN140001UV01-int" role="interaction" sortPrefix="34|15|99|99|" baseClass="Clinicaltrialsregistry" ballotStatus="DSTU" ballotNumber="1" lastEdit="2009-11-27T13:15:48"><descriptive identifier="desc-PORT_IN140001UV01" name="Description" parent="PORT_IN140001UV01-int" id="desc-PORT_IN140001UV01-int" lastEdit="2009-11-27T13:15:48"><p>Submission of an protocol specification for an intended study.  Submitted by the study sponsoring organization to a registration authority.</p></descriptive><arref role="sendrole" ref="PORT_AR140001UV01-ar" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent Informer" refFamiliarName="Sponsor Organization" refIdentifier="PORT_AR140001UV01"/><arref role="rcvrole" ref="PORT_AR140002UV01-ar" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent Receiver" refFamiliarName="Registration Authority" refIdentifier="PORT_AR140002UV01"/><teref role="trigger" ref="PORT_TE140001UV01-te" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Intent" refFamiliarName="Clinical Trial Registration Submission" refIdentifier="PORT_TE140001UV01"/><msgref role="transwrap" ref="MCCI_MT000100UV01-msg" sectID="immcci" sectType="SB" refName="Send Message Payload" refIdentifier="MCCI_MT000100UV01"/><msgref role="cactwrap" ref="MCAI_MT700201UV01-msg" sectID="immcai" sectType="SB" refName="Trigger Event Control Act" refIdentifier="MCAI_MT700201UV01"/><msgref role="msgtype" ref="PORT_MT140001UV01-msg" sectID="hmport" sectType="SB" refName="Clinicaltrialsregistry Message Type" refIdentifier="PORT_MT140001UV01"/></interaction></interactiondivn></subdivn><subdivn identifier="PORT_DO000001UV-ClinicaltrialsregistryDam" name="CTRR Domain Analysis Model Topic" familiarName="CTRR Domain Analysis Model" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORT_DO000001UV-ClinicaltrialsregistryDam-ic" role="BC" sortPrefix="35" baseClass="CTRR Domain Analysis Model" ballotStatus="NormativeStandard" ballotNumber="1"><descriptive identifier="intro-PORT_DO000001UV-ClinicaltrialsregistryDam" name="Introduction" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-ClinicaltrialsregistryDam-ic" id="intro-PORT_DO000001UV-ClinicaltrialsregistryDam-ic" lastEdit="2011-05-14T12:25:12"><p>The CTRR Domain Analysis Model is a UML representation of the information and behavior requirements for the Clinical Trial Registration process.  The DAM is rendered as a PDF document containing a behavioral model (Use Case, Activity, and Sequence diagrams); Structural Model (Class and Object diagrams); and a mapping from the DAM to sources of Clinical Trial Registration requirements (WHO.CTR, EudraCT, and CT.Gov).  The CTRR Domain analysis model is a subset of the BRIDG domain analysis model containing the classes, attributes, and relationships of interest to CTRR.</p><loc href="V3DAM_CTRR_R1_INFORM_2011MAY.zip">Click here to download the Domain Analysis Model document.</loc></descriptive></subdivn><indexdivn identifier="cindx-PORT_DO000001UV" name="Common Message Elements Indexes" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="cindx-PORT_DO000001UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-1" name="Common Message Elements Defined in this Domain" parent="cindx-PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORT_DO000001UV-icc1id"/><indexlist identifier="cindx-List-2" name="Common Message Elements Used by this Domain" parent="cindx-PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORT_DO000001UV-icc2id"/></indexdivn><indexdivn identifier="indx-PORT_DO000001UV" name="Interaction Indexes" parent="PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="indx-PORT_DO000001UV-ic"><indexlist identifier="indx-List-1" name="Interaction Index by Application Role" parent="indx-PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORT_DO000001UV-ic1id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-2" name="Interaction Index by Trigger Event" parent="indx-PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORT_DO000001UV-ic2id"/><indexlist identifier="indx-List-3" name="Interaction Index by Message Type" parent="indx-PORT_DO000001UV-ic" id="PORT_DO000001UV-ic3id"/></indexdivn></body></spec>

